PROFESSOR: You're considering a project
that requires immediate investment
in year zero of $37,000.
You expect that it will generate $20,000 in year one,
$15,000 in year two, $10,000 in year three,
and $2,500 in year four.
The first question asks, what is the payback period
of this project?
Well, let's solve this question.
By definition, the payback period
is the amount of time it takes to pay back
the initial investment.
In our case, the initial investment is $37,000.
In the first year, the project returns
$20,000, which is less than the initial investment.
Therefore, this project does not pay back our initial investment
within one year.
In the second year, the project returns $15,000.
Therefore, during the first two years,
the project returns 20,000 plus 15,000,
which equals to $35,000.
This is still less than $37,000, which
means that the project does not pay back the initial investment
within the first two years.
In the third year, the project pays off $10,000.
Therefore, during the first three years
of life of this project, it returns 20,000 plus 15,000
plus $10,000.
Altogether, this equals $45,000.
Now, this is more than the initial investment of $37,000.
Therefore, the payback period of this project
is three years because it pays back our initial investment
within the first three years.
The second question asks if you require
a payback period of two years, will you take this project?
Let's solve this question.
If you follow a payback period rule,
then you only take projects that pay back
within two years of initial investment.
In part a, we computed the payback period of the project
under consideration.
This payback period was three years.
Since this project pays back within three years,
and you only take projects that pay back within two years,
you will not take this project.
Third question-- what is the net present value of this project
if the cost of capital is 12%?
According to the net present value rule,
should you take this project?
If the cost of capital is 12%, the NPV of this project
is as follows.
Negative $37,000, which is the initial investment,
plus $20,000 that we receive in year one discounted to present.
Plus $15,000 that we receive in the year two
discounted to present.
Plus $10,000 we receive in year three discounted to present.
And finally, $2,500 received in year four
discounted to present.
Altogether, this equals to $1,521.65.
Since the net present value of this project is positive,
we should take this project.
Now, let us pause and think.
Payback period rule tells us not to take this project,
while the net present value rule says that we
should take this project.
Recall that following the net present value rule
is always optimal because it increases
the value of the firm.
Therefore, by following the payback period rule
in this case, we would have made the wrong decision
and would not have increased firm value.
Let us summarize this lesson.
Payback period rule can lead to wrong investment decisions.
This happens because, one, payback period rule relies
on ad hoc decision criterion.
Why we decided to take projects with payback period of two
years or less and not three years or four years?
Who have made this decision?
There are clearly no good a priori
reasons for this decision.
Two, payback period rule ignores cash flows that
occur after the payback period.
In our case, this project returns $10,000 in year three
and $2,500 in year four.
By following the payback period rule
we carve off two years while ignoring these cash flows.
As shown by NPV calculation, these cash
flows clearly make a difference in this case
because the net present value of this project is positive.
And three, payback period rule ignores project's cost
of capital and time value of money.