PROFESSOR: Cyber Vision, a computer vision startup
in Cambridge, Massachusetts, considers
opening a new division to explore the viability
of a new technology.
To evaluate its decision, Cyber Vision
first needs to forecast working capital
needs for the new division.
Its Chief Financial Officer developed
the following projections in thousands of dollars.
Accounts receivable are expected to be $0, $50,000, $60,000,
and $75,000 in years zero, one, two, and three respectively.
Inventory is expected to be at $120,000, $150,000, $200,000,
and another $200,000 in years zero, one, two,
and three respectively.
Accounts payable are expected to be $40,000, $40,000, $80,000,
$100,000 in years zero, one, two, and three respectively.
Calculate the cash flows associated
with changes in working capital for the first three years
of this investment.
This question is designed to help
us understand the impact of working capital
requirements on cash flow.
First, let's use forecasts of accounts receivable, inventory,
and accounts payable to compute net working
capital in each year.
By definition, net working capital
equals to accounts receivable plus inventory minus accounts
payable, therefore in year zero, net working capital
will equal to $0 plus $120,000 minus $40,000 or $80,000.
In subsequent years, in years one, two, and three,
net working capital will equal $160,000, $180,000 and $175,000
respectively.
Now, recall that it's not the net working capital itself,
but rather changes in net working capital
is what affects the cash flow, so let's compute
increases in net working capital each year.
In year zero, this increase is just
$80 because we go from up $0 up to $80,000.
In the year one, this increase will
equal to $160,000, which is the level of net working
capital in year one minus $80, which
was the level of net working capital in the year zero,
so this is the increase of another $80,000.
In year two, net working capital increases by $20,000,
from $160,000 to $180,000 and in year three decreases by $5,000,
from $180,000 down to $175,000.
Now, the final step is to compute
the associated impact of increases
in net working capital on cash flow.
Recall that, by definition, cash flow equals to 1 minus tax rate
times operating profit minus capital
expenditures plus depreciation tax shield minus change
in net working capital, therefore the cash flow
will be of the opposite sign from increases
in net working capital.
So in year zero, cash flow is going to be equal
to negative $80,000.
In year one, it will also equal to negative $80,000.
In year two, it will equal to negative $20,000,
and in year three, it is going to equal to positive $5,000.
Now let's try to understand the intuition here.
Why in year one we have a cash outflow of $80,000?
Well, let's look at the components
of net working capital.
Accounts payable don't change.
They remain at $40,000.
But accounts receivable go up from $0 to $50,000,
and inventory goes up from $120,000 to $150,000,
therefore it's this build-up in the receivables
and the inventory that causes an outflow of $80,000 in year one.