PROFESSOR: In this video, we will
consider an example of hedging commodity price risk.
Cartier, the maker of fine jewelry
uses 76,000 of troy ounces of silver per year
in production of their jewelry and would
like to hedge its price risk for next year.
The current price of silver is $22.35 per troy ounce.
Cartier is considering two hedging strategies.
First, it can enter into a one year forward contract with BNP
Paribas for 76,000 troy ounces at a price of $25.70 per ounce.
Second, it can trade silver futures
on Chicago Mercantile Exchange.
The current price of a one year futures contract is $25.25.
The contract unit is 5,000 troy ounces.
The picture on the right shows contract details
for silver futures.
We will answer the following questions:
assuming that Cartier does not hedge,
what would be its cost of silver consumption if silver price
increases to $23.00?
What if the silver price increases to $27.00?
Suppose that you enter into a 1-year forward contract
with BNP Paribas.
What is the total cost of your silver consumption in year one?
Is this a perfect hedge?
Suppose that you use futures for your hedging needs.
Assuming that you cannot buy fractions of standard
contracts, how many contracts you need to buy or sell?
Is this a perfect hedge?
Let's first see what would be our silver consumption
costs in year one, if we do not hedge.
If in year one, the silver price is $23.00,
our costs would be $1.75 million.
If in year one, the silver prices $27.00,
our costs would be $2.05 million.
Next, let's compute Cartier silver consumption
costs, if it enters into a Forward contract
agreement with BNP Paribas.
The contract price is $25.70 per ounce of silver.
Therefore, the total cost is 25.70 times 76,000 ounces,
which equals to $1.95 million.
By entering into this forward agreement,
Cartier fully hedges its silver price
a risk over the next year.
Therefore, this is a perfect hedge.
Let's compute Cartier's silver consumption costs,
if it buys silver futures on CME.
First, let's determine how many contracts we need to buy.
Recall that the standard contract is for 5,000 ounces.
Therefore, we usually need 15.2 contracts,
which we computed by dividing 76,000 by 5,000.
Since we cannot buy fractions of a contract,
we will buy 15 contracts.
This will guarantee the price of 75,000 ounces and the remaining
1,000 ounces Cartier would need to buy at the market
price in year one.
Let's now compute Cartier's silver consumption costs,
if he buys 15 futures contracts.
If in year one, the price of silver is $23.00,
our costs would be $25.25 times 75,000 ounces plus $23.00 times
1,000 ounces, which gives us $1.917 million.
If in year one, the price of silver is $27.00,
our cost would be $25.25 times 75,000 ounces plus $27.00 times
1,000 ounces, which gives us $1.921 million.
Based on this analysis, we see that we cannot achieve
a perfect hedge with futures contracts.
The reason for this is that we cannot buy a fraction
of a contract, which leaves 1,000 ounces of our silver
needs exposed to the silver price risk.
However, most of our consumption needs
(75,000 out of 76,000 ounces) is hedged.
Therefore, while our hedge is not perfect,
it is close to being perfect.