PROFESSOR: Let's dive right into the questions.
Question 1-- software development costs amortization.
Suppose a firm's software costs capitalized for years 2015
to 2017 are as follows.
If the useful life is two years, how much
is the amortization in 2017?
We first capitalize 2015 software costs for 2016 and 17.
Since the useful life is two years,
and 2015's capitalized software costs is $100,
we record $50, which is $100 divided by 2, for years
both 2016 and 2017.
For year 2017, we need to amortize 2016
to capitalize costs as well.
2016 capitalized costs will be amortized over 2017 and 18.
In 2017, we record an additional $55 in 2017
to account for 2016's capitalized software costs,
which is $110 divided by 2.
Therefore, the total amortized cost in 2016 is $50,
and end cost in 2017 is $105, which is the sum of $50 and $5.