PROFESSOR: Our third question asks
us to calculate CFO using the indirect method.
Note that the numbers written under the balance sheet
are the changes in each account or items in the balance sheet.
So for example, this firm increased cash by $1,180
and increased interest payables by 200 and so forth.
In this slide, these are the income statement, revenues,
cost, interest expenses, all the specific items
inside the income statement, and also the changes in the balance
sheet of the firm.
Its revenues are $5,000.
Cost is 600.
Interest expense is 320.
Depreciation expense 500.
And gain on sale of a fixed asset is $800.
So the net income is $4,380.
If you look at the right hand side,
the part called the balance sheet,
as I've mentioned briefly before,
this denotes the changes in each account over the fiscal year.
For example, accounts receivables
increase by 4,500 and so on.
So the total assets increase by $6,080.
And our objective in this question
is to obtain cash flow from operations
using the indirect method.
Recall that we begin with net income in the indirect benefit.
So the net income is $4,380.
Next then we'll look at the depreciation expense
or any non-cash expense.
And our depreciation expense is 500.
This is not cash so therefore we add 500 to the net income.
We then subtract the gain on sale.
We do this because gain on sale is under cash flows
from investing.
So not subtracting this would be double counting.
Next we look at the changes in current assets and changes
in current liabilities.
We first subtract changes in current assets
from net income except for changes in cash.
Accounts receivables increase by 4,500,
inventory increased by 400, and interest payable
increased by 200, which is change in current liabilities.
So to reiterate, starting from net income 4,380,
I added non-cash expense of 500 and also subtracted
investing gain or loss by 800.
I also subtracted changes in current assets
since current assets increased by 4,500
for accounts receivable and for 400 for inventory.
I also added increase in payables.
So taking all those factors into account,
you can see that the total cash flow from operations
decreased by 620.