PROFESSOR: Second question on intangibles--
ABC Corp has the following intangibles information
during and at the end of fiscal year 2019.
How much R&D expense did ABC Corp
incur during fiscal year 2019?
Internally developed software costs are typically
expensed as I described before.
And ABC has spent $83 million in developing and software.
ABC Corp incurred $83 million in R&D expenses.
How much intangibles amortization expense
that ABC incur during 2019?
Capitalized software costs in 2018 was $170 million,
with a useful life of 10 years.
Therefore, in 2019, dividing one million
by 10 years of useful life gives us $17 million
of amortization expense.