PROFESSOR: Here's a giant gumball machine.
Notice that you put the gumballs in on top,
and then the gumballs come out in the middle of the machine.
So now we're going to talk about LIFO,
which is last in, first out, versus FIFO, which is first in,
first out.
So the giant gumball machine we just looked at,
let's suppose it has 100,000 gumballs in it.
Let's suppose the gumball prices have been rising over time,
and we want to know the value of the ending inventory
of the gumballs in the machine.
So we need a cost flow assumption.
One we'll look at today is LIFO, which is last in, first out.
So when you go to the grocery store,
you're going to look around for the newest milk, typically
in the back of the container, and you're
going to grab that newest milk because you want the new milk,
you want the new eggs, and the new produce.
So your shopping behavior is to try to get the last in,
the newest stuff, bring it out first.
FIFO is the other assumption that we'll look at.
This is first in, first out.
This is how the grocery stores wish you would shop,
so they spent a lot of time organizing the shelves so
that the oldest product is the first one that you would reach
if you don't reach to the back.
So depending on the cost flow assumption,
it's going to change how we value the inventory.
But notice that in practice cost flow assumption is
independent of physical flow.
So we might choose LIFO cost flow assumption
for this gumball machine, but what's
the physical flow of this gumball machine?
Gumball goes in the top of the machine
and then works its way down to the middle of the machine.
So this is first in, first out.
So lots of physical flows are first in, first out,
but for accounting purposes, we don't
have to recognize the physical flows.
We can choose to cost things however
way it makes more sense for us.