INSTRUCTOR: Now to do an example to illustrate the difference
between LIFO and FIFO.
And we've got a simple company.
In its first year of operations, it began its operations,
it issued stock for $100 in cash.
With that cash, it purchased seven tires for $8 each.
Then later that year, it sold three tires for $10 each.
And in its second year of business,
it purchased five tires for $10 each.
And then it sold four tires for $12 each.
All of these transactions are in cash just to make it simple.
So here's our inventory equation.
We started Year 1, we had no tires.
We bought seven tires for a total price of $56.
So the goods available for sale were seven tires,
each purchased at $8 a tire.
And our Year 1 inventory was $56 available for sale.
Now in this first year, does LIFO or FIFO matter?
The answer is no it doesn't because all the tires
in inventory are either new or old
depending on your perspective, but they all
had the same price.
So when we go to sell some tires,
we sell three tires at $8, so cost of goods sold is $24.
And our ending inventory is four tires at $8,
so our ending inventory is $32 worth of tires.
Ending inventory this year becomes
beginning inventory next year.
We purchased five tires for $50.
And our goods available for sale is
a mixture of $8 tires and $10 tires
with a total value of $82.
Now when we go to sell tires, which costs are we
going to allocate to the sale.
Is it going to be the new tires, or is it
going to be the old tires?
This is where LIFO and FIFO comes into play.
Let's first do LIFO.
So LIFO means last in, first out.
So the newest tires that we bought
are going to be the ones that we sold.
So we're going to ascribe to cost of goods sold a $10 value.
Our ending inventory is going to be a mixture of one new tire
and four old tires for a total ending inventory of $42.
Now let's compare that to what happens under FIFO.
Which tires are we going to sell under FIFO accounting?
Well, FIFO is first in, first out,
so we're going to sell the oldest tires
in the cost of goods sold.
So our cost of goods sold will be four tires at $8 a tire
or $32 in total.
And then our ending inventory will be more valuable.
It'll be $50 in total.