INSTRUCTOR: So now let's summarize
these in the Mackenzie 2 by 2 box
and compare last in, first out cost to first in,
first out costs.
So on our income statement, remember, FIFO puts old costs
on the income statement.
It puts $32 of costs on the income statement.
But the new costs stay on the balance sheet.
So with FIFO, the older costs hit
cost of goods sold, hit current income,
but the new cost stay on our balance sheet.
With LIFO, it's just the opposite.
The new costs hit the cost of goods sold and become
part of income.
The old costs stay on our balance sheet.
So that's just one example.
Notice that it ultimately doesn't
matter because total costs are the same
under both LIFO and FIFO.
They're $82.
But what changes is how the costs are distributed
across the income statement and across the balance sheet.
And this just says that this is a general phenomenon.
So FIFO puts old costs on the income statement,
new costs on the balance sheet.
LIFO, on the other hand, puts new costs
on the income statement, old costs on the balance sheet.
Total costs are going to be the same.
So we're just distributing cost differently
across the income statement and the balance sheet.
And when you think about it, the new costs
are the more accurate costs because they're
closer to replacement cost.
So if you went out and bought tires right now,
the new cost would approximate how much you would have
to pay for tires right now.
So FIFO gives you a more accurate balance sheet
because it has the new costs on the balance sheet,
whereas LIFO method of accounting
gives you a more accurate income statement because the new costs
are on the income statement.
So over time, say like year two, ending inventory under LIFO
is going to be less than ending inventory under FIFO.
Now does that mean LIFO firms' inventories are less valuable?
Now when you think about it, it's
exactly the same thing in both inventories.
There's a bunch of tires in there.
It's just a costing method is different.
So the cost flow assumption is independent
of the physical flow.
We've got the same tires in the inventory in both cases,
but we've costed them or we've accounted for them differently.
Same thing on the income statement.
So cost of goods sold under LIFO are, in general,
going to be higher than cost of goods sold under FIFO.
That means that our gross profit under LIFO
is going to be lower than our gross profit under FIFO.
Now do these profit differences say
that there's something going on differently in terms
of economic performance?
So no, again, it's just an accounting difference.
Here, accounting and economics are different.
The economics is the same across the two firms,
we just got differences in financial reporting.