PROFESSOR: So now we want to talk about some comparability
issues.
So as we talked about earlier, the balance sheet
and the income statement of a LIFO firm
is going to be different from a FIFO firm.
First, remind ourselves why US firms use LIFO.
So if you have rising costs and you report taxable income
using LIFO, that means your taxable profits
will be lower and that--
and LIFO also results in a more accurate income statement.
But if a firm uses LIFO and one of its peer firms uses FIFO,
they have different accounting, so we're
going to need to adjust the accounting numbers to make them
comparable so we can analyze the two firms on an apples
to apples basis.
And as it turned out, data is available to adjust the LIFO
firm to FIFO but we can't adjust the FIFO firm to LIFO.
So what we're going to do in the next example
is to pick a LIFO firm and talk about how
to adjust that firm to FIFO so that we can compare the two
firms apples to apples.
Remember earlier when we did our example,
the LIFO firm had some cost layers.
It had one tire at the new price of $10,
and it had four tires at the old price of $8.
The FIFO firm, at least in our example,
only had the new tires in inventory at $10.
So if companies are using LIFO the requirement
is they disclose the current cost of their LIFO inventory
in the footnotes.
So notice that $42 is less than $50,
so the difference between current FIFO cost of $50
and LIFO value of $42 is referred to as the LIFO
reserve.
And most companies will tell you the difference
between ending inventory of FIFO, so $50 in our example
here, and ending inventory in LIFO, so
$42 in our example here.
Now let's look at a real financial statement.
So this is ExxonMobil, the big oil company as of 2011.
So if you read the financial statement,
you see that the replacement cost of inventory,
so the current cost of inventory exceeds their LIFO carrying
value by $25.6 billion as of 2011.
What are these inventory values shown
in their financial statements?
These are their LIFO values.
So what would the 2011 FIFO value be?
It would be the $11.7 billion LIFO of value
plus the $25.6 billion LIFO reserve.
So the FIFO inventory is $37 billion.
So that inventory is actually worth $37 billion,
even though it's shown on their balance sheet
at about $12 billion.
Now if ExxonMobil switched to first in,
first out at the end of 2011, what
would happen to their taxes?
So this was what we were talking about a few minutes ago.
So we could reword this question as how large
is ExxonMobil's cumulative tax savings by using LIFO?
We're going to assume a tax rate of 30%.
Notice that their LIFO reserve again is $25.6 billion,
and that really when you think about it,
it represents the additional amount that ExxonMobil
has charged to cost of goods sold since the firm
began using LIFO.
So if it switched to FIFO, all that $25.6 billion
would come into income, and assuming that ExxonMobil
pays a 30% tax rate, it would pay an additional $7.7 billion
in taxes.
So by using LIFO, ExxonMobil has saved itself $7.7 billion
in taxes over time.
Now let's look at the income statement for ExxonMobil.
We see the cost of goods sold number in 2011
is $306.8 billion and what we want to do now
is compute ExxonMobil's cost of goods sold under FIFO.
And to do this we have to adjust the LIFO cost of goods
sold number that we just saw to a FIFO
cost of goods sold number.
I'm going to flip ahead a couple of lines
here, so all you need to know is the--
pardon the box there, which is the change in the LIFO reserve
is equal to the difference between cost
of goods sold under LIFO, and cost of goods sold under FIFO.
And then those of you that are interested in a little bit
of algebra, I'm going to show you how we came up
with that equation.
So the first equation is the inventory equation under first
in, first out.
So ending inventory under FIFO is
equal to beginning inventory under FIFO,
plus additions, minus the cost of goods sold under FIFO.
We write the same inventory equation under LIFO
and then we subtract them from each other.
Notice that the additions there cancel out
because they're going to be the same under both accounting
methods.
And notice that we've got an expression for the ending LIFO
reserve equals the beginning LIFO reserve
plus the difference in cost of goods sold.
And so we come back to the change in LIFO reserve
tells us what the difference in cost of goods sold is.
So the change in LIFO reserve tells us
difference in cost of goods sold between LIFO and FIFO.
So now let's apply this in ExxonMobil.
So we want to know the cost of goods
sold under FIFO for ExxonMobil, so we just rearrange
our equation a little bit.
Now we've got cost of goods sold under FIFO
equals cost of goods sold under LIFO,
minus the change in LIFO reserve.
Notice that we know the cost of goods sold under LIFO,
we know the change in LIFO reserve from above.
So the cost of goods sold under FIFO is $302.5 million.
Now, does that pass the smell test?
Going back to what we were doing earlier,
remember the cost of goods sold under LIFO
is going to be more than the cost of goods sold under FIFO.