PROFESSOR: All right.
So we just finished talking about inventory.
So the remaining agenda we have is to talk about
property, plant, and equipment.
And to do that, we're going to work
through the accounting for property plant and equipment,
starting in acquisition.
You buy a car, you buy an airplane, you build a building.
So you acquire some property, plant, and equipment.
We'll talk about what it means to depreciate that property,
plant, and equipment.
We'll talk about what happens if you change your depreciation
estimates.
And then finally, we'll talk about what
happens when, as we all do, we sell our car,
we sell our airplane, or we sell the building.
And then, the last part of this class
is we're going to talk about the Hertz case.
We're going to see how a rail company changes
their estimates.
We're going to talk about why those estimate changes were
because the company was trying to manipulate their earnings
or whether it was simply because the company was
changing their strategy.
So let's think about how we record
an acquisition of property, plant, and equipment.
Imagine a company buys a car for $20,000 in cash--
just balance sheet equation.
We're going to reduce cash by $20,000.
We're going to increase PP&E, or Property, Plant, and Equipment
by $20,000.
And when the purchase happens, that's all that happens.
The cost of this fixed asset, or the cost of this PP&E,
doesn't enter the income statement.
Why not?
Well, as a review from last time,
we haven't used the car to generate revenues.
So until we use the car to generate revenues,
we're not going to match any expenses to the car.
When does a car enter the income statement?
Again, the same principle-- once it starts to generate revenues.
And then, what happens someday if we sell the car?
We're going to talk about that a little bit later in this class.
So to account for property, plant, and equipment,
we need to answer the following four questions.
What's the acquisition cost, how much
did we pay for the car, what's the salvage value, how much do
we think we can sell the car for some time in the future?
And that's how much we're going to depreciate.
And depreciate means, reduce in value over time.
And the third and fourth questions are,
what's the expected useful service life?
So how long do we plan to use the car for?
And then, what's our depreciation pattern?
Is it going to be straight-line or accelerated?
So this tells us how we're going to depreciate the asset.
So in terms of two of our estimates, useful life
and salvage value, let's just talk a little bit about them
because these can be a little subtle.
So useful life-- you buy a car.
It's the time period--
you're useful life on that car is the time period over which
you're going to use the car.
It's not necessarily the same as the physical life of the asset
because you might sell the car after two years
even though the car has got 10 years' worth or the mileage
says you can still put on it.
Salvage value is, given how long you
intend to use the car, what do you think
you can get when you sell it or dispose
of it, net of selling costs?
Now, obviously, the longer you intend
to use the car, in general, the less likely
the car is going to be worth at the time that you sell it.
So notice that both of these estimates,
both salvage value and useful life,
require managerial judgment.
So we have some estimate of how long
we're going to use the car.
And then, based on that estimate of how long
we're going to use the car, we're
making a forecast of how much we can sell the car for when
we're done using it.
Let's look at an example here just to fix these ideas.
And think about two types of car owners.
First type as the Sunday driver that's sort of
like my grandfather used to be.
And the second type is drive till it dies.
That's kind of like how I am.
So Sunday driver drives it 2,000 miles a year.
So Sunday driver just takes it out for a drive on Sunday.
He or she trades it in every two years.
So given that they intend to have a new car every two years,
they're going to trade it in every two years,
the useful life of their car is two years.
So they intend to use the car for two years.
And then, given that they're not driving it very much,
and they're not driving it very long, the salvage value, or how
much they expect to sell that car for,
is going to be very high.
On the other hand, another type of driver
is, drive till it dies.
So they drive it lots and lots and lots.
They drive it 20,000 miles a year.
They never trade it in.
And then some day, the car just quits working,
and they leave it on the side of the highway.
So their salvage value is zero.
And the useful life for that owner
just depends, but probably 10 or 15 years.
So the key thing is that salvage value and useful life
depend on what the user expects to do with the asset.
In terms of GAAP depreciation methods,
we're going to focus on straight-line depreciation
where the value of an asset just goes down in a linear function.
This is actually used by almost all US firms.
It's easy to calculate.
And it just gives you a constant allocation
of the cost of the asset from the balance sheet to the income
statement.
Another type of depreciation is accelerated depreciation.
We'll talk about this in the class on taxes.
So most firms, for their tax purposes,
use accelerated depreciation even though they
use straight-line depreciation for their financial reporting
purposes.
So accelerated depreciation for tax--
straight-line for financial reporting
is what we're going to focus on now.
Now, as an aside, how is accounting depreciation related
to economic depreciation?
To get this one, just think about buying a car.
So you buy a brand new car.
You buy it at the dealer, and you drive it home.
So if you bought a car, and it costs $100,000,
and you drove it home, how much is it worth
when you get it home?
So rule of thumb is that, once you've
driven a car home from the dealer,
the car's worth 25% less.
So economic depreciation, you have this rapid depreciation
in the early period of the asset's life.
Then, straight-line otherwise.
And accounting depreciation, straight-line throughout,
is an approximation to economic depreciation,
but it's not going to be 1 for 1.
So in terms of calculating depreciation expense, if we're
doing straight-line, which is what we'll
be doing in this course, is the straight-line method is just
acquisition cost, how much do you pay for the car,
minus the salvage value, how much you expect
to sell the car for, and then divide that
by the estimated useful life.
So we're just trying to match the asset
costs with the benefits over long periods of time.