PROFESSOR: So now let's do an example.
And here's the facts for our example.
So January 1, 2006, Zsa Zsa Co buys a car for $20,000 in cash.
Zsa Zsa plans to use the car for five years.
So the useful life of the car is five years.
And at the time that they buy the car,
Zsa Zsa Co estimates that the salvage value will
be 25% of the purchase price.
So here's our questions.
What's the acquisition price?
We're buying the car for $20,000.
What's the salvage value?
25% of $20,000 is $5,000.
How much are we going to depreciate then?
The difference between $20,000 and $5,000, or $15,000.
What's our useful life?
Five years.
So what's the annual depreciation expense then?
It's going to be the acquisition costs minus the salvage
value divided by the useful life, or $3,000.
So now let's look at how the balance sheet
equation records depreciation expense over the asset's life.
We're going to introduce a contra-asset here, which
is accumulated depreciation.
And this is very similar to the contra-asset we had.
Allowance for doubtful accounts was a contra-asset to accounts
receivable.
So we buy the car for $20,000.
Cash goes down, and property, plant, and equipment goes up.
The next year we depreciate it.
So we've got $3,000 of depreciation expense
in the right hand column there.
And then we put that in the contra-asset accumulated
depreciation.
The next year we do the same thing, and then so
on out until the end of the asset's life as of 12/31/2010.
Now importantly, and we're going to come back to this point
again later, notice the only time that cash goes out
is when we buy the car.
There's no other cash transaction.
So depreciation is an expense.
But it is a non-cash expense.
So it does not affect our cash flows.
Here's the same thing, just shown in the depreciation
schedule.
So the far right column shows depreciation expense,
five years of $3,000 a year.
Gross PP&E, the acquisition cost, doesn't change over time.
We're going to gradually accumulate more depreciation
in our contra-asset account so that the net PP&E,
or the net book value is going to go down
over time from $20,000 to the salvage value of $5,000.