PROFESSOR: Now we're just going to make a little change here.
We're going to suppose that Zsa Zsa Co.
decides to change the depreciation policy a year
after it buys a car 1/1/2007.
So it decides, you know, I like this car.
I'm going to keep it for six years rather than five years.
OK.
So I'm going to keep it an extra year.
But because of the fact that I'm keeping it an extra year,
the used car market is going to be not worth as much
for the car.
So we're going to reduce the salvage value to 20%.
So this kind of accounting change is made prospectively.
Prospectively means look ahead.
So we're not going to adjust any old financial statements.
All we're going to do is adjust our financial statements
on a going forward basis.
So in other words, we're going to recalculate the depreciation
rate using our new estimates.
So salvage value is decreased to 20%.
So that's going to drop to $4,000.
Useful life was five years.
So now we're going to take it to six years.
But we've been using the car for a year
now so the remaining useful life is
the six year total useful life minus the one year
that we've used it or five years.
And then continuing on with our work
on this change of depreciation policy, the amount remaining
to be depreciated at the time we make
the change is gross PP&E of $20,000 minus 1 year
depreciation of $3,000.
So we got a net book value of $17,000
at the time we make the change.
Remaining useful life is five years
so our adjusted depreciation expense
is going to be the net book value
of $17,000 minus the new salvage value divided
by the new remaining useful life of five years.
And we divide that out.
That gives us a lower depreciation rate of $2,600.
So notice what happened is by stretching the useful life
and not reducing the salvage value all that much,
the new depreciation rate is lower than the old depreciation
rate.
And so we could sort of see that again
in this table where depreciation expense on the right hand
column drops from 3,000 a year to 2,600 a year.
We add an additional year of useful life to it.
So over time, we're going to accumulate depreciation
of $16,000 and depreciate the asset down to its salvage value
or net book value at the time of the end of the asset's
life of $4,000.
So we've done two examples now.
We bought the car.
We had an original depreciation rate.
We changed the depreciation rate.
We talked about what happened then.
Now we're going to talk about what
happens if we sell the car at the start of 2010 for $7,000.
So notice that at this point, the car,
just looking back on our prior slide,
the car has accumulated depreciation of 10,800.
And the net book value the asset is historical cost or what
we purchase it for of $20,000 minus accumulated
depreciation of 10,800 gives us a net book value of 9,200.
Now what happens when we sell the car for $7,000?
So we're going to go through a calculation
on the next couple of slides.
So computing a gain or loss on the sale--
so sometimes you sell an asset.
Sometimes you dispose of an asset.
So if you're like the drive until it drops guy,
he doesn't have a positive value for his car
because he driven it to such an extent
that he's got to call a tow truck to pick it up.
And so when he disposes of it, he's
going to actually get negative value for it.
But in general, you're going to sell the asset.
And we have a four step process.
First of all, keep track of cash or keep
track of the market value of another asset
if you traded something for the property, plan, and equipment.
So the second step is record the disposal of the asset
by taking the cost of the asset off the balance sheet
then take the accumulated depreciation off the balance
sheet.
And then we're going to solve for the gain or the loss
as how much cash we got or what the sales price was
minus the net book value.
And that gives us our gain or loss.
So in terms of the balance sheet equation,
remember as of 12/31/2009, we had gross property, plant,
and equipment of $20,000, accumulated
depreciation of 10,800.
When we sell the car, step one, keep track of cash.
So that's pretty easy to do.
So we got $7,000 worth of cash.
Step two.
Remove the PP&E from the balance sheet.
So we no longer own the car so we're
going to take it off our balance sheet.
Step three.
Remove the accumulated depreciation
from the balance sheet.
Again, we no longer own the car so we no longer have
any accumulated depreciation.
And then solve for the gain or the loss on the transaction.
This transaction we're getting $7,000 for something that
has a net book value of 9,200.
So our loss on the transaction is $2,200.
So first solve for the cash.
Second and third, remove the net book value
of the asset of $9,200 and then solve for the gain or the loss
on the transaction.