PROFESSOR: So we were just talking
about a sale of PP&E. Now, we're going
to do an example of PPE impairment.
Let's suppose instead that Zsa Zsa Company does not
sell the car.
She holds it another year until December 31, 2010.
And let's suppose at that time, the fair value of the car
is 3,600, but we have a net book value of 6,600.
So the fair value is $3,000 less than the net book value.
So in this case, the company must impair, or write down,
the asset.
And it's going to do this by increasing accumulated
depreciation by $3,000.
Let's look at the balance sheet equation entry.
So December 31, we start off with a PP&E balance of $20,000.
We start off with accumulated depreciation of 13,400.
So that's our net book value of 6,600.
When we impair the car, we're going
to increase accumulated depreciation by $3,000.
That's going to give us a write-off
of $3,000 in retained earnings.
And that's our impairment loss.
And our ending balance will be $20,000 in PP&E
and accumulated depreciation of 16,400.
So notice now the net book value of the asset, or the car,
is $3,600 because we increased accumulated depreciation
by $3,000.
Notice that we increase depreciation
instead of reducing property, plant and equipment.
The reason for this is that we want
to keep a record of the acquisition cost
to property, plant, and equipment on our balance sheet.
So we maintain that cost by instead increasing
accumulated depreciation.
Warren Buffett, in the Berkshire Hathaway 2002 Annual Report,
talks about this idea that depreciation is not
truly an expense because it's a non-cash charge.
Warren Buffett says that's nonsense.
Depreciation is particularly unattractive
because we put the cash out front when we buy the building
or when we buy the asset before the asset has
delivered any benefits.
So another way to look at this is
imagine, at the beginning of a year,
a company paid all of its employees
for the next 10 years of their service,
the way we would do with a fixed asset with a useful life
of 10 years.
In the following nine years, compensation
would be a non-cash expense.
But nobody's going to argue that this is just a bookkeeping
formality because we paid our workers for 10 years
in advance.