PROFESSOR: So as review from what we did earlier
in this class, remember gain or loss
on a sale of property, plant, and equipment
is going to equal the sales price minus the net book
value, which is gross PPE minus accumulated appreciation.
Just going to rearrange this a little
bit to put accumulated depreciation up front,
and then a term which is gross PPE minus the sales price.
And if you notice, the first term is accounting depreciation
and the second term is economic depreciation.
So you bought the asset for the gross PPE price,
and you later sold it for the sales price.
So that's economic depreciation.
So if we look back to the Zsa Zsa company example above,
I'm just to make a little table where
we vary accounting depreciation and then recompute
the gain or the loss.
So notice that the first column is the sales price.
The second column is the cost.
Third column is economic depreciation,
which is PPE cost minus the sales price.
And what we're bearing is accounting depreciation
from 10.8 as in our first example down to 15.2.
And then notice that as accounting depreciation is
small, we have a loss.
And that's telling us that there was too little depreciation.
And when we go down to the bottom of the chart
we have a gain which tells us that we, sort of,
over-depreciated the asset or we depreciated the asset
in a conservative fashion so that when we sold it
accounting depreciation was bigger
than economic depreciation, which
means that we had a gain on the sale of the asset.
So let's look back at exhibit 14 again and notice that in 2013
in the four year period.
We have a gain, which is equal to accounting depreciation
minus economic depreciation.
That gain implies that Hertz is actually
being conservative in their depreciation policy.
And it suggests that Hertz is not depreciating too little.
One further piece of information we can look at from the case
is we can compare Hertz to its big competitor, Avis Budget
Group.
Then notice that four year average
drops for Avis even more than it drops for Hertz.
So there's something going on in the industry
where depreciation rates are dropping.
And this suggests that Hertz is in line with its peers,
and it suggests that Hertz is not, in fact,
cooking the books.