PROFESSOR: OK, our last topic, securitization,
draws on many of the concepts and methods
that you've learned throughout this class
and demonstrates their adaptability
for valuing novel and complex claims.
We'll start with definitions, a product
overview, a little history, and a discussion of the uses
and sometimes abuses of securitization.
Securitization is used to diversify, restructure,
and redistribute credit risk.
We'll look at how this is done with CDOs
and see why default correlation is a critical input
into valuing these securities.
Then we'll turn to mortgages and some
of the many types of mortgage-backed securities
or MBSs that have been created.
This is the largest part of the securitization market
and the oldest in modern history.
In this market, securitization is
used to diversify, restructure, and redistribute
prepayment risk and, to a lesser extent, credit risk.
The biggest challenges for pricing and risk management
of MBSs arise from the complexity of modeling
prepayment behavior.