PROFESSOR: In optimization, critical points
are often critical.
We have a function that may be a scalar
function of multiple variables.
We'd like to find its largest value in one
of the necessary conditions.
It may be that the partial derivatives with respect
to the variables vanish.
We also need to check possible boundary terms.
So let's take a look at critical points or continuous functions,
multiple variables, and see how we can classify them,
so we can keep that in mind as we
look at financial applications.
For a function of a single variable,
critical points are places where the first derivative vanishes.
Consider the Taylor expansion for a continuous function.
I have f of x expanding around a point x0,
and I have a linear term times the first derivative
plus a quadratic times the second derivative
evaluated at a point and so on for higher term.
Now, if the first derivative varnishes,
then I have the special result. If I move the f of x0
to the other side, I have that the amount
by which f differs from the value at point f0
is a parabola.
It looks like a quadratic term in the vicinity of x0
when x minus x0 is small and the higher order
terms x minus x0 cubed, to the fourth,
and so on are small compared to the term that we keep.
Now, we need to check that the second derivative, in fact,
is not vanishing.
For the generic case, it will be.
If it vanishes, then we go to the next higher order term.
This is typical unless there's either a very accidental reason
why it vanishes where there's a particular symmetry.
Now, in higher dimensions this parabola,
which might be concave or convex depending
on the sign of f double prime, is
described by a quadratic form.
It's described by the matrix of second partial derivatives.
So for a function of several variables,
Taylor's theorem tells us that for a scalar function
in the neighborhood of a vector point, a fixed point x0,
that we can do an expansion.
f of x is being the gradient of f
times the difference between x and x0 as a vector quantity.
That's a leading order term plus a second-order term
plus cubic terms and so on.
And the second-order term is of particular interest.
It's a vector, this difference vector x minus x0
transpose times Q times the same vector on the right-hand side
with a 1/2 in front.
And this Q defines a quadratic form.
This is just a matrix of second partial derivatives.
You can write it out in terms of components if you'd like.
And f is the gradient function, and this
varnishes at a critical point.
So when the gradient of f vanishes,
which means that all of the first derivatives
vanish, not just one of them or two of them--
when they all vanish and when x minus x0 is small in magnitude,
then we can approximate the deviation of the function
from a particular point by this quadratic behavior.
So this quadratic behavior, as in the single-variable case,
is somewhat universal.
It's worth studying because every function, unless Q
vanishes for some particular reason,
is going to have this form when we're sufficiently
close in the neighborhood.
So there are more possibilities than two,
just the two signs of f double prime
in the single-variable case, and we can take a look
at how they're classified.
The eigenvalues determine the type of critical point we have.
If the eigenvalues of Q are all positive,
the function is convex up and then the critical point
is a minimum.
If the eigenvalues of Q are all negative,
the function is concave and the critical point is the maximum.
If Q has both positive and negative values,
then it's called a saddle point.
There are some maximum in one direction.
It's a minimum in some other direction.
And if any of the eigenvalues are 0,
they define flat directions where the function is neither
increasing or decreasing.
Now, the reason we talk about the eigenvalues
is because the eigenvectors determine,
really, the axes of orientation, and the eigenvalues
tell us how things vary along those directions.
Because Q is a symmetric matrix--
remember, the order of partial derivatives doesn't matter--
the eigenvectors are going to be orthogonal.
So the general cases we might get
with all kinds of mixed partials really
are set of cases if we think of diagonalizing
and having orthogonal indices--
or excuse me, and having orthogonal axes, then
the eigenvalues whether they're positive or negative
along different directions tell us
whether in that particular direction
along that particular axis the shape of the curve
is like a parabola, it's convex up, convex down,
or if it's a flat direction.
We can take a look at a few examples.
So let's look at a few examples of functions of two variables.
So I can plot them on the screen in projected three dimensions.
Let's consider a function f.
It's a function of x and y.
So for example, suppose I have this function. f of xy
is x times e to the minus x squared plus y squared.
And I think of z, the z-coordinate,
as being the height of this plot,
and this is one way, a prospective plot.
And I've given you code in R so that you can run this and get
this pretty picture yourself.
But where do we see critical points?
Well, the critical points that we see
are local maximum here, a local minimum here.
And in fact, if this is what we've got,
these are global max and global min as well.
They're places where the first derivatives vanish.
We can also visualize this in terms of a contour plot, where
we see-- in a contour plot, we see
lines of constant value of f drawn together.
We notice-- now, of course, contour lines
never cross because we can't have two different values
at the same place.
But we can see over here, there's
a height scale on the right-hand side.
So white is high.
Black is low.
But otherwise, you see an interesting symmetry
on the left and right parts of the graph.
So here's a function that typifies
the kind of classic example where we have a minimum value.
This is just instead of a parabola, it's circular.
It's a paraboloid.
x squared plus y squared, so the minimum value is obviously
the origin where its value is 0 and everywhere else it's
greater.
Here's a 3D plot.
We noticed that with this particular description,
the function is rotationally symmetric.
If I'd put in different coefficients for x and y,
then the axes would have-- the circles
would have been ellipses.
And if it had been those axes were then rotated along
some other direction, the quadratic form
might have a cross term as well, a term in xy.
But geometrically, it's the same idea of what's going on.
There's a single minimum.
There's some contours around it.
This is an example of the function,
which has a saddle point.
Here, I have f of x is x squared minus 4y squared.
So you notice that not only is the sign of the x term
and the y term different, but the coefficient
is as well so that the speed of change or the rate of curvature
can be different in the two different directions.
So if I move along the x direction, I'm increasing.
If I move along the y direction for the origin, I'm decreasing.
Here's a contour plot of the same thing.
Now here's an interesting case where we have a flat direction,
and we also have a mistake in the equation.
So that should just be f of x equals--
f of x and y equals y squared.
So you notice that because there's no y dependence,
the function has a symmetry.
I can translate in y.
I can take any value.
And that means that as I move in the y direction,
not only is the direction flat, but every cross section,
the x dependence at any given point y in that valley,
is exactly the same.
So this is an example where we have a flat direction,
and it's due to asymmetry in the problem.
And in this case, one of the eigenvalues
of our quadratic form Q, our matrix of second derivatives,
is going to be 0.
This is a case where, like the other one,
I have a flat direction along the y equal 0.
But unlike the other one, it's not symmetric.
It's not translationally symmetric.
And you can see that as I move along the y-axis
for different values of y, the cross section,
the cross-sectional curvature, as I move in the x direction
changes.
So in one perpendicular direction, I'm completely flat.
But in the other direction, there
are changes that are seen once I move in the perpendicular
direction.
And here's a picture of the same thing shown as a contour plot.