PROFESSOR: In the presence of constraints,
it's not enough to just find critical points.
Constraints are everywhere in the real world
and certainly in finance and economics.
We have finite resources that we need to allocate.
We have a finite budget.
We have a finite risk limit that we shouldn't exceed.
So we're often asked to solve problems
where we're looking for the best solution or a maximum value
of some scalar function subject to a constraint.
And those constraints can take different forms.
They might be equalities.
They might be inequalities.
They might involve one or multiple variables.
So let's start at the beginning with the Lagrange multiplier
method for solving equality constraints
in multidimensional optimization problems.
Here's a picture to help visualize things.
This is a contour map of the neighborhood
of Mount Washington showing its hiking trails.
Mount Washington is the tallest point in New England.
And, if I asked you to leave MIT and to find the tallest point
and you had a functional description of this,
you could certainly find lots of local extrema,
but the global maximum would be at 6,288 feet
right here at the top of Mount Washington.
But you notice there are lots of hiking trails around the top
of Mount Washington.
And there's even an auto road here,
and there's a railroad that goes down the backside.
But, if you were looking for a tranquil way,
you might, say, be over here at the Appalachian Mountain Club
Lake of the Clouds Hut.
And you'd like to hike over here to Tuckerman Ravine, which
descends rather steeply.
And you'd like to do it without going
through the summit at all.
Well, a question you certainly could ask
is, along a trail of my choice, say
this one, what's the highest point that I would reach along
the trail?
So the trail represents your constraint.
You're not free to go anywhere in latitude and longitude
on this map.
That's your constraint.
But we can ask, as you go along the trail, at every point,
you're definitely at some elevation above sea level.
And we could think of that as being a function
h of x, y where x and y give your latitude
and longitude for example.
And we could ask a very reasonable question.
If there are no cliffs here, even
though it descends steeply, and if you don't
fall into a crevasse, we could ask,
what was the highest point along that trail?
One of the things that we can see immediately
is, whatever it is, wherever the highest point
is along this path, it has nothing
to do with the global maximum.
It doesn't go anywhere near the summit of Mount Washington.
OK, so it's not enough to just take a function
and find its extrema because the answer
that we're looking for may not be anywhere nearby.
The answer to doing this is also--
let's think about this a little bit geometrically.
Imagine that we're ascending.
Say we're climbing through Tuckerman Ravine.
And we're going to go along here.
What does it mean?
As long as we're ascending, we are crossing contour lines.
Contour lines, remember, are level sets
where the altitude is constant, where our scalar function
h is constant.
What it means to reach an extremum along the path
or to reach a maximum along the path
is that you're no longer crossing contour lines.
That is your direction of travel,
the tangent along the path that you're taking,
is parallel to the contour lines themselves.
The point at which you reach a maximum
is when the direction of your trail
is along the direction of a contour line, at least
instantaneously.
In either direction going forward or backward,
you would be going down at a critical point.
So the geometrical condition we have
is that the direction of the path
should be tangent to the level sets.
And that we can state as a condition on the gradients
of the two functions, one describing the constraint
along the path and the other describing
the shape of the level sets of the function h
without the constraints.
And, when we overlay the two, we say
they need to be in the same direction.
And that's what the Lagrange multiplier
method is going to give us.
So here is the Lagrange multiplier method.
What we're going to do is take our original unconstrained
function, h of x, y, and we're going
to construct a new function called the Lagrange function,
which is going to have one extra variable, which
is a variable called lambda.
And this extra variable lambda is known
as the Lagrange multiplier.
And the way I construct the function
is I take my original function, h of x, y,
and I subtract lambda--
it's linear lambda in this new variable--
times, in parentheses, I have my constraint.
So imagine that the constraint is given by some equation
in x and y, saying what they need to satisfy.
x and y is equal to some constant.
So all I've done is I've taken my original function
minus lambda times the constraint itself.
So the strategy here, in practical terms,
is to take a problem in two parts,
maximize the function subject to a constraint,
and turn it into a simpler problem in more variables.
So the problem in three variables,
with x, y, and lambda, is going to have no constraints.
So the idea is that we're going to take all three
partial derivatives now, set all three of them equal to 0.
That will impose the condition that the vectors--
that the direction of my constraint
is along the direction of the level sets.
And it's easy to solve.
So let's take a look at a couple of examples,
first in algebraic functions, and then we'll
see how this applies in finance, most notably, to the case
of portfolio optimization.
The general method is this.
If we have multiple constraints, we introduce one constant
called the Lagrange multiplier per constraint.
We define the Lagrange function, which
is linear in the constraints.
It's got extra variables, one per Lagrange multiplier,
but it has a simpler solution.
We take the derivatives with respect
to each of the original variables.
And, of course, that gives us the original partial
derivatives we would have had plus something that's
linear in lambda or the other Lagrange multipliers.
And, when we take the derivative with respect
to the Lagrange multipliers, the equations
we get when we set those derivatives to 0
are just the constraint equations themselves.
So that's it.
Then we find the critical points,
and we can substitute them in and make
sure they solve the problem.
We can check second derivatives to make sure that, in fact, we
have a maximum and not a minimum or a point of inflection.
And, usually, not always, but in many problems,
it doesn't even matter what the Lagrange function is.
What we care is the location of the extremal value, not
the value itself.
So that's worth keeping in mind because it can simplify things.
So, for example, if we want to pick
a different form of the Lagrange function
that's easier to solve, but where
we know it has the same critical points, that's OK.
We can do that.
And, in fact, when it comes to the constraint,
we have a lot of freedom as to how we could change it
because, at the critical points, the constraint function is
going to vanish.
So let's take a look at a couple of examples.
So here's a chance for you to do your own concept check.
And you can pause the video at this point.
And then we'll solve it together.
But here's the example.
Let's let h of x, y be the function x plus y.
And let's let the constraint be that the solutions,
the maximum, minimum, or extrema that we're looking for,
have to lie along a circle of radius r.
r here is just a radius.
It's not the risk-free rate.
So we construct our Lagrange function,
L of x, y, and lambda, to be our function h, x plus y,
minus lambda times the constraint.
So, if you'd like, pause the video.
See if you can solve it.
Find the critical points.
And then come back, and we'll take a look at this together.
OK, so let's compute some derivatives together.
What we find is we take the first partial of L
with respect to x.
We get 1 minus 2 lambda.
Notice it's we have lambda here.
We're always going to have something linear in lambda
because this is left over, and the partial derivatives
act on the constraint.
So that tells us that x is 1 over 2 lambda.
I take the partial with respect to y.
My function is symmetric in x and y.
So, no surprise, I get that y is 1 over 2 lambda.
And now, because x and y are both equal to 1 over 2 lambda,
I can eliminate lambda.
And I see that x is equal to y.
So I'm almost done.
x is equal to y, but they also have
to lie along the constraint, which
means that the sum of their squares
has to be equal to r squared.
So, if I substitute x equals y into this constraint equation--
and notice the constraint equation
I get just by differentiating with respect to lambda.
There's no lambda in the original function h.
And there's a linear in lambda before the constraint.
So differentiating with respect to lambda just
gives me back my constraint.
It's exactly what I would have had before,
but, whereas, without the Lagrange multiplier method,
you might have tried to solve for y in terms of x--
you could have written y as being
plus or minus the square root of r squared minus x squared,
substituted it back into h, and then tried
to solve for that extremum.
You'd have had a more complicated function and fewer
variables.
Here we're going to keep everything
where all the variables start on equal footing.
We substitute into the constraint.
We find there are two solutions.
x and y are each equal to plus or minus r
over square root of 2.
Either they're both plus signs, or they're both minus signs.
And it's easy to check that either,
at 45 degrees in the first quadrant
or in the third quadrant, we have
two points on the circle, which represent
the maximum and the minimum values of x plus y.
And, if we substitute in the values,
these are the values, square root of 2 times r
or minus square root of 2r, OK?
So that one you might have guessed just
from symmetry of the problem, but this is the method.
It's really very easy, very straightforward.
Let's do another example.
Here, again, pause the video.
Take a look at doing this.
And then, after you've checked your own concepts
and your own math, come back and compare.
A couple of things to note, our function in this case
is a general quadratic form with a cross term.
So it may not be obvious immediately where the extrema
or whether they're maxima or minima or saddle points.
And we're going to look at this quadratic form,
instead of linear on our previous example,
and we're going to have it lie along the unit circle.
So, subject to the constraint that points lie along the unit
circle, we want to ask where are the maxima and minima
of the function h of x, y.
We construct a Lagrangian by taking
the quadratic form minus lambda times the constraint.
Now, one thing to consider as you're
doing this, a couple of things that don't matter, one of them
is the sign of lambda.
If you change lambda to minus lambda,
if you change, in fact, the sign of the constraint to 1
minus x squared minus y squared, you'll
get exactly the same result. And you should check that.
If you carry through the signs consistently,
you'll find that, when you eliminate lambda,
everything goes through exactly the same.
But it's also true that there are different ways
to write the constraint, and any of them would work.
So, for example, if I want x squared
plus y squared to equal 1, I could
take x squared plus y squared to the fourth power equal to 1.
Or I could take x squared plus y squared minus 1
to the 12th power.
Anything that imposes the constraint is going to work.
The idea is the coefficient of lambda,
when we have found our constrained solution,
the coefficient of lambda will vanish.
It vanishes only-- it will vanish on the solution.
There might be other roots to the equation that might be off
somewhere in the complex plane.
We're not going to worry about this,
but it is the case that, if it's a solution,
then the coefficient of lambda will vanish.
So this is another easy algebraic equation.
We take derivatives.
We'll have some simple linear equations to solve.
Why don't you go ahead and try?
Pause the video here.
Come back, and we'll take a look together.
Last chance.
OK, let's take a look.
So we do partials.
So let's look at our partials of L. We have
16x plus 12y minus 2 lambda.
Notice that everything now, compared
to the previous example, is linear in x and y.
That last term is always linear in lambda.
I take the partial with respect to y.
And I have terms also in x and y--
12x plus 34y minus 2 lambda y equals 0.
And I have the constraint, which is
just x squared plus y squared has to be equal to 1.
So this has to be satisfied here.
So we've got these equations.
We can solve them for x and y and eliminate lambda.
We can eliminate lambda immediately
by taking the difference of these equations,
solve for x relative to y, and then get
the exact values for x and y in the unit circle
by solving this equation.
And what we find our two solutions, x and y,
are in the direction 1, 2--
and I've normalized this to be on the unit circle--
and in the direction minus 2, 1.
And, interestingly, those are, in normalized form,
the eigenvectors of the quadratic form that's
defined by the matrix, which we could have
written as Q is 8, 6, 6, 17.
So, if you compute the eigenvalues and eigenvectors
for this, you'll find 12 and 5 for the eigenvalues
and eigenvectors 1, 2 and minus 2, 5.
And, if we normalize the eigenvectors
to be of unit length, we get exactly the results shown here.