PROFESSOR: The results we've looked at
can be generalized in two ways.
One of them is by including more linear constraints of the kind
we had, and that's easy.
We add more Lagrange multipliers.
So we might have a rule that in addition
to a return constraint and a budget constraint,
we might want to limit certain risk exposures.
We might want to limit the portfolio
data, which is its sensitivity to the overall market.
We might want to target a particular industry exposure
or foreign country exposure, or we
might want to neutralize them.
If we're allowing a long-short portfolio,
we might say that our net exposure to a given country
should be equal to 0.
So in all those cases, we just had one more Lagrange
multiplier, and we solve the same thing.
It's just the algebra gets a little bit more complex.
Another kind of constraint that's
important in investment management
and many practical problems are inequality constraints,
and the Lagrange multiplayer method will not handle these.
In this case, we need to proceed with numerical solutions
and a technique called quadratic programming.
The idea of inequality constraint
is we might want, for example as I hinted before, we might have
a mandate where we're not allowed to short positions
and we need all our w's to be equal to 0.
The Lagrange multiplier method has no guarantee
that the solutions will end up with positive values of w.
They could be anywhere in the vector space
and not in half the vector space or a quadrant of the vector
space where all the w's are positive.
And we might have a constraint on an upper bound.
We might not be allowed to use leverage,
which would say that the individual weights all
need to be less than 1.
We might have more binding or tighter constraints,
where a typical investment manager isn't allowed
to put all of his or her eggs in one basket
or even a lot of them.
There might be a rule that says, the weight invested
in a particular asset or asset class can't exceed, say, 5%
or 10% or 1%.
So there might be some limit that's well inside the 0 and 1
range, and it could be applied at the level
of an individual weight or it could
be applied to a sum portfolio, which would correspond
to some linear combination of weights being constrained
with some upper or lower bound.
So when we have this kind of thing,
the Lagrange multiplier method might give us
a method where the constraints are satisfied,
these inequalities.
But it's not guaranteed to do so.
And in general, we need to use this technique called
quadratic programming.
The quadratic here comes from the fact
that our objective function is quadratic,
and our constraints being linear means that we can always
find solutions.
And we're not going to derive this.
We'll have some references for it,
and you can take a look if you're
interested in the algorithms.
But you'll find packages for doing this numerically,
and we'll take a look at some numerical examples as well.
Qualitatively, the important thing
is that we're always going to be by adding extra constraints.
The more constraints we have, the smaller
our efficient frontier becomes, the smaller
our feasible set of portfolios becomes.
The constraints in the best case are non-binding,
and then we have no change.
But the constraints can only make things worse.
They can only remove, if they are binding,
portfolios that otherwise would have been feasible
and have them not be feasible.
So we would expect the feasible space
to shrink when we solve for the inequality constraints,
and we'd expect the constrained optimization problem to give us
something that's smaller and that is not necessarily
the solution to the original constraint maximization.
Now, there are lots of other investment constraints
we could have--
position size, leverage size, factor exposure,
different balances for long-short neutrality.
We could be long-short in weights.
We could be equal beta, long and short.
We could have other factor exposures.
There are many other techniques.
There's a broad variety of them that
can be handled in quadratic programming.
There's a package in R called quadprog
and a function called solve.QP you can take a look at,
and you can take a look at our code examples as well.
What we find is typically something like this.
This is just an example of an asset allocation problem.
Suppose I start with eight assets,
and I've got their means and their covariances.
I have their mu vector, expected excess returns,
and I have their covariance matrix c.
And here are the individual assets
with their individual risk and return.
I haven't plotted what the correlations are among them,
but these are down here.
And if I compute from that mu and sigma what
the unconstrained efficient frontier is,
I find this hyperbola that's shown here on the black line.
So everything that's feasible is on that interior
of the black line.
When we include a long-only constraint
and a no-levergage constraint-- so we'll
have a budget constraint, and we'll
want to maximize our return or minimize the risk for a given
level of return.
And in addition, if we impose that the weights have
to be strictly between--
they have to be greater than or equal to 0 and less than
or equal to 1, they can't be negative,
they can't be greater than 1, they can't be short,
they can't be leverage positions,
then we find the blue line as being the set of solutions.
And this is the efficient frontier,
and the feasible portfolios are the interior region.
So these are the-- everything inside here
is a feasible portfolio, and the points that are optimal
are the points that are on the blue line.
Everything above and to the left on this graph is not reachable.
We cannot get returns that have lower risk for the same level
of return than the ones in our solution to our optimal
equation.
We cannot get returns that have--
portfolios that have higher return for given risk or that
have lower risk for a given return.
That excludes the region above and to the left
of the blue curve.
But we can see what we've lost in applying the constraints
and limiting the weights to be strictly between 0 and 1,
that we've lost the area that's the difference
between the black curve and the blue curve.
Those are portfolios that we might
have had that aren't here.
So it's always an interesting idea when to ask,
are constraints binding?
And if the constraints are binding,
what does it cost to have those constraints?
What would happen if we loosen the constraints?
The optimal solution would move.
Where would it move to?
Are we close?
Are we giving up a lot by imposing
these constraints or not?
So we do have these things that are set for constraints.
We typically think about solving and finding
an optimal portfolio, but there are
a couple of things that we might also keep in mind.
One of them is that if you're going
to optimize your portfolio, you're
highly dependent on the inputs.
You might want to know how sensitive your results are
to those inputs.
That is, if you were to change them a little bit,
if you had estimation errors in your returns
or in your covariance matrix, would you
move just a little bit all along the way?
Would you move along the efficient frontier?
Or would you end up somewhere else completely?
Conversely, even if you're not an optimizer,
you've just got some equal weighted portfolio,
or you're following an index--
you've got some country index--
it's of interest even if you haven't optimized
to ask where your portfolio would lie along this risk
and return plot.
Is it close to the efficient frontier?
And for example, that's an even--
an equal-weighted portfolio with even allocations of capital
to all of the assets.
That's an easy thing to explain to investors.
If you find that it's reasonably close to the frontier anyways,
then you're not sensitive to any of these estimation problems.
That would be good to know.
On the other hand, if you're far away,
now you can use this picture to make a compelling case for why
a careful analysis and constraint optimization
solution for an asset allocation or a general portfolio
optimization problem gives benefit for the investor
in terms of increasing the expected return,
decreasing the expected risk, or both.