PROFESSOR: We know that the accuracy of option valuations
on binomial trees will be improved
by increasing the number of steps on the tree,
all else equal.
We also know that as we take the number of steps to infinity,
the stock price tree will converge
to give a lognormal distribution of stock prices, which
is the assumption underlying the Black-Scholes-Merton model.
The same will be true for Monte Carlo simulations
where, for a fixed expiration date, decreasing the step size
and adding more steps causes price estimates to become
more accurate.
For the next few slides, our running example
will be based on a standard put and call
option priced using 10 steps.
We'll compare the results using Monte Carlo
and a binomial tree.
We'll also compare the results to
the Black-Scholes-Merton price, which
is expected to provide the most accurate result.
In these calculations then, the physical expected return
on the stock is set to 10%, its volatility to 30%,
the risk free rate is 2%, and the initial stock price
is $100.
The strike price is also $100.
And as I just mentioned, we're assuming 10 steps
over a horizon of one year.
Those inputs and the resulting outputs using the spreadsheet
program that you've already seen,
binomial.xls, produces the stock price tree here
and European call option tree here, set to value
a European call option, which has a value of 12.53
given these assumptions.
It's fairly straightforward to modify the Monte Carlo
simulations to incorporate multiple steps along each path.
For each successive step, a draw from the uniform distribution
from rand is compared to q star to determine if the next step
will be an up or a down.
If an up step is indicated, then the previous value of the stock
price is multiplied by u.
And if a down step is indicated, it's multiplied by d.
The parameters q star, u, and d are
calculated as they were for the binomial tree.
And they can be read off of the spreadsheet
on the previous slide.
Well, for example, this table shows the results
of the first 10 of 1,000 Monte Carlo simulations, all
starting at a stock price of 100 and taking
steps of 1/10 of a year all the way out to one year, so
10 steps in a year.
In this first simulation, the draws from rand
told us there was a down, another down, then an
up, and up, and so forth.
On this simulation path, the outcome
for the stock price at the end of the year is 146.151.
The call is then in the money at that time by 46.151
and the put is out of the money.
The discounted values of those option payoffs
are reported in the first column for the put
and in the second column for the call.
The results for nine more Monte Carlo simulation
runs are shown in these next nine rows.
The equally weighted average of the discounted payoffs
are then the Monte Carlo estimates of the option values.
The results for a 1,000 run Monte Carlo simulation
and the associated standard errors of the estimates
are summarized here on the top left.
The Monte Carlo option price estimates
are close to those from the binomial tree.
For comparison, let's look at the call estimates.
The spreadsheet reports the call prices
estimated from the binomial tree and also from the Black-Scholes
formula.
The Monte Carlo estimate of the call value is 12.637.
The binomial tree gives 12.53.
And Black-Scholes gives 12.82.
These are all pretty close.
Remember that the binomial estimate
will converge to the Black-Scholes-Merton estimate
as the number of steps gets very large in the tree.
It's also true that the Monte Carlo estimate
will converge the Black-Scholes-Merton estimate
both as the number of steps gets very large
and as the number of Monte Carlo simulations
also gets very large.
We can plot the stock values as a function of the time step
from these simulated values.
Each path is represented here by a different color.
And the results look like the distribution
of paths through the binomial tree but with missing branches.
The branches that are most likely to be missing
are those with the lowest probability,
which means having mostly all ups or mostly all downs.
A larger number of stimulation paths
will tend to fill out those tails of the distribution.
A useful observation then is that for derivatives
whose values are very sensitive to the extreme tails
of the stock price distribution, such as deep out of the money
puts and calls, it becomes very important to use a large number
of Monte Carlo simulations.