INSTRUCTOR: Now that we've gone over the most common types
of exotic options and some of the motivations
for trading them, we'll turn to the numerical methods that
are most frequently used for pricing.
We saw that for some of the exotic options
we looked at the formulas developed
to price them usually involve modifications
and extensions of the basic Black-Scholes-Merton model.
For the many exotics for which an analytical formula isn't
available, or when the underlying asset doesn't
satisfy the log normality and other assumptions needed,
numerical methods are used instead.
The two most common and related approaches
are binomial trees and Monte Carlo simulations.
With either method, we continue to rely on no arbitrage
logic that makes it possible to estimate the value of quite
complex derivative products with a good degree of confidence.
To understand the relation between risk neutral pricing
on binomial trees and Monte Carlo pricing on trees,
we'll start by reviewing the simple case of pricing
a standard call option on a non-dividend-paying stock
and a one-step tree.
Assume that the stock price is initially at $100.
The strike is out the money, also at $100.
The time to expiration is 1.
The risk-free rate is 2%.
And sigma, the volatility, is equal to 30%.
The tree is calibrated with an up calculated
and e to the sigma root T, which is
the usual way we find the up.
And the down is 1/u.
So the up turns out to be 1.35, and that gets us
from the initial stock price to the stock price in the upstate.
And multiplying by 1/u gets us 74.082 in the down state.
So in the usual way, the call is in the money in the upstate,
not in the downstate.
We take the expected value discounted back to time 0.
And we find that the value of the call is 15.73.
Note that we can price any European derivative
of the stock in the same way, calculating its expected
payoff at expiration, using the risk-neutral probabilities,
and discounting back at the risk-free rate
to get it's time 0 value.
An alternative way of computing the expected future payoff
is to simulate the up and down stock price movements.
For each simulation, the probability of an up
corresponds to the q star that was computed
based on the stock price tree.
To calculate whether a move is up or down,
we use a uniform random number generator.
In Excel, that built-in function is called RAND.
It generates a draw from a uniform distribution
that lies between 0 and 1.
We take a draw from the uniform distribution
N times, where each draw represents
the path taken on the tree, and N is
the number of simulated paths.
If the draw is less than q star, it represents an up move.
And the stock price outcome is S 1,u.
And if the draw is greater than q star,
it represents a down move.
And the stock price outcome is S 1, d.
Those values S 1,u you and S 1, d are the same as the ones we
computed for the tree.
Using many draws, this share of ups will approach q star.
For each simulation, we compute the payoffs
of the derivatives at time 1 based
on the outcomes of S. The value of the derivative security,
then, is the average of the present values of the payoffs
across the N simulations.
The procedure I just described is most easily
understood with an example.
Using the risk-neutral probability of 0.4587
that we calculated for the example shown
on the binomial tree, this table shows one set of outcomes
from running 10 Monte Carlo simulations.
Each row represents the outcome of one Monte Carlo run.
The draws from RAND determine whether a move is up or down.
For example, the first one results
in the up price because the draw of 0.4573
is less than the q star of 0.4587.
The corresponding option payoff is 34.986.
And that will be the same any time there's an up.
And the payoff will be 0 whenever there's a down.
Discounting the payoff to time 0 gives 34.293
as the present value of the payoff
whenever there's an up move.
Then averaging across our 10 Monte Carlo runs,
the average of 17.147 is the estimate
for the value of the call option.
It turns out that this outcome is rather far from the 15.731
that we found using the tree.
That discrepancy is due to the fact
that the average number of ups isn't very accurately estimated
with just 10 simulations.
As N gets large, the two values will converge.
Analysts relying on Monte Carlo simulation
need to assess how many simulation runs are necessary
in order to produce a sufficiently reliable estimate
of option value.
One's error tolerance can be expressed
in terms of an acceptable standard error on the estimated
option values.
The standard deviation of the estimates
is given by the formula here, assuming
that the random draws on each simulation path
are independent.
The important observation here is
that the standard deviation depends
on a factor of the square root of 1/N.
That means that the accuracy increases within N,
but as a decreasing rate as N gets large.
For example, the standard deviation
of 10 estimates in the previous example
was calculated to be 5.715.
A two-standard deviation confidence band
around the estimate, then, has a range of 5.7 to 28.6,
much too large to want to rely on that estimate.
In a rut of Monte Carlo simulations,
where I've increased N to 1,000, the sample estimate of 15.725
is much closer to the 15.731 that
was found with risk-neutral pricing on the binomial tree.
And the estimated two-standard deviation confidence band
is also much narrower with a range of 14.64 to 16.8.