PROFESSOR: In this video, I will introduce
a concept of expected return.
Suppose that, currently, Nikola Corporation
is traded at $32 a share.
We're given the probability distribution
of what will be a share price of Nikola next year.
Suppose, though, with probability 10%,
the share price will increase all the way to $150.
With 60% probability, the share price
is going to come down from $32 to $20.
And with the remaining 30% probability,
the share price will go all the way down to $2 a share.
The question is, what is the expected return on this stock
over the next year?
And here, by return, I would mean net return.
So first, let's compute what would
be the net return on Nikola stock price in each
of the corresponding cases, when the share price
goes up to $150, up to $20, or to $2.
So I will write down here net return, and I will compute it.
So in this first scenario, the net return on Nikola
is going to be $150 minus $32 divided by $32.
See, if you compute this, this gives us 368.75%.
So that is a very large return.
Now, in the second scenario, the net return
will be $20 minus $32 divided by $32.
And you could see that, in this case,
the share price declines, so the return's going to be negative.
So it's going to be negative 37.5%.
Now, in this last scenario, net return's
going to be $2 minus $32 divided by $32.
And that's going to be negative 93.75%.
So in this case, the share price goes almost to $0,
so we are losing most of our wealth.
Note that, by definition, net return can never
be less than negative 100%.
This would just mean that you're losing
all of your initial wealth that you invested into the stock.
Now let me define what expected return is.
Expected return, which I will denote as Er.
E stands for the expected, and this is the concept
from probability theory.
This would be the sum of all probabilities of each given
state, so state 1, 2, and 3, multiplied
by the net return in each of the corresponding states.
So p1 multiplied by the return that we'll
get on the stock in state 1, plus p2 times r2
plus p3 times r3.
If we have more states of nature,
we can write down the expected return
in a more compact way, as 1 all the way
to however many states of nature we have, let's say
n, p i times ri.
So the probability of each of these states of nature
multiplied by the net return in each
of the corresponding states.
So applied in our case, this would be 10% multiplied
by the return that we get in this first state, which
is 368.75%, plus 60%--
this is the probability of occurrence
of the second state--
multiplied by negative 37.50% return plus 30% multiplied
by negative 93.75% return.
If you compute this number, this would give us negative 13.75%.
So the expected net return on our investing
in this stock of Nikola Corporation is negative 13.75%.
Now let me also show you an alternative way
of solving this question.
What we can do is we can find the expected price of Nikola
stock in year one, and then use the current price
to find the net return.
So by definition, the expected price of a stock next year
will be the probability of each of the corresponding states
times the share price in that state of nature.
So in this case, it will be 10% multiplied
by $150 plus 60% multiplied by $20 plus 30% multiplied by $2.
If you compute the share price, we will get $27.60.
So right here, you already can see that, in expectation,
the share price of Nikola is going
to decline from the current price to what it
is going to be, or expected to be, next year.
Now to compute the net return, which
is taking the future price, the expected future price,
we'll divide it by the current price minus 1.
And so it will be $27.60 divided by $32 minus 1.
And this number will also be negative 13.75%.
So both approaches give us exactly the same final result,
which is the net return on the stock of negative 13.75%.
What it implies, this expected value or what we also
call mean return, is based on our assessment of probabilities
of different states and different prices
of share price of Nikola in each of those different states.
What is the most likely return on the share
over the next year?