PROFESSOR: In this segment, we'll
talk about trading mechanics.
Suppose you want to buy 100 shares of Uber.
There are two ways of doing it.
One, you can place what we call a limit order.
And the second way is you can place
what we call a market order.
Think of a limit order as placing
an advertising, which says how many shares and at what price
you want to buy.
And think of market order as responding to an advertising
posted by someone else.
So saying that you will be buying 100 shares of Uber
at the best price that is currently
available in the marketplace.
Let's consider a specific example.
On the slides, we see what we call a limit order book.
It shows us all available asking prices
right now of people or investors who are
willing to sell their shares.
In particular, the top part of the slide
shows four separate limit orders.
It says that someone is willing-- one
investor, at the very top, is willing to sell
their shares at $13.08.
And the number of shares they are willing to sell
at this price is 200 shares.
The investor right below is willing to sell also
200 shares, but at a price of $13.06.
Yet another investor is willing to sell 300 shares
at the price of $13.05.
And the last investor is willing to sell 100 shares
at a price of $13.04.
So this is the collection of all the offers of investors who are
willing to sell their shares.
And they indicate the price at which they're willing to sell
and the number of shares that they are willing to sell.
At the bottom, we have a collection of offers
by investors who are willing to buy shares.
The first investor is willing to buy 200 shares
at the price of $13.02.
The next investor is willing to buy 300 shares
at the price of $13.01.
And the other investor is willing to buy 200 shares
at the price of $12.99.
So this is the collection of what we call bids or quotes
from investors, limit orders from investors,
who are willing to buy shares or the specified number of shares
at these specified prices.
There is an important definition that we
will make based on this slide.
So the difference between the best ask,
which is, in our case, $13.04, and the best bid or the best
price at which somebody is willing to buy
a share, $13.02, this difference between $13.04 and $13.02
is called bid-ask spread, which is
the difference between, again, lowest ask and the highest bid.
Now let's try to understand what happens
when there is a market order that arrives to this limit
order book.
Suppose that there is a market order, comes in,
that wants to buy 200 shares.
Now, the best ask is only for 100 shares.
So somebody is willing to sell you 100 shares at $13.04.
The next best ask is 300 shares at $13.05.
So your order got to get executed in two batches.
You will buy the available 100 shares at $13.04.
And then you will buy the remaining 100 shares at $13.05.
Now after your order is executed,
let's look at how does the limit order book
look like after this order is executed.
So we see that because we just purchased 100 shares at $13.04,
there is no bottom line, which indicates that we actually
purchased this 100 shares at this price.
And the ask of $13.05 for 300 shares
right now indicates that there are only 200 shares available
at $13.05.
Which makes sense, because we purchased
100 of these 300 shares that were
available from the beginning.