PROFESSOR: In this video, we'll talk about returns.
I will define what is a gross return
and what is a net return.
Gross return, by definition, is the future value
of an asset divided by its current value.
And net return is the future value
of an asset divided by its current value minus 1.
In other words, net return will be just gross return minus 1.
And now let's consider a simple example.
So suppose that you bought an apartment with a current value
of $200,000.
And the future value of this apartment,
let's say in one year, is $300,000.
What is your gross and net return
on the purchase of this apartment?
By definition, gross return, in this case,
would be $300,000 divided by $200,000.
And if we expressed that ratio in percentages,
this would be 150%.
So when we talk about returns, we express them in percentages.
So the gross return on the purchase of this apartment
is 150%.
Now, the net return would be just gross return,
which is 150%, minus 1, or 100%, which would give us 50%.
So the net return on the purchase of this apartment
is 50%.
When we talk about returns, most frequently
we mean just net returns.
For example, if you hear someone is
saying that a stock had a 10% return, that 10%
is net return number.
For example, if the stock price was $100 and it had 10% return,
it means that its current value is $110.
Now, both gross and net return are random variables.
And the reason for that is because we
don't know what the future value of any of the asset is.
So in this particular example, if the current value
of the apartment is $200,000, its future value of $300,000
is just a guess.
And therefore, since this future value isn't known,
both gross and net return are random variables.