PROFESSOR: In this segment, we'll talk about bonds.
A bond is a promise to pay a fixed amount of money.
Let's consider the following example.
It's a bond issued by Ford, and it has a face value of $100.
The current price of this bond is $97.
The term is three years.
And this bond will pay an interest,
which we call a coupon.
We'll assume that the interest is paid annually on this bond.
Now, let's look at the timeline of cash outflow and cash inflow
that we get from investing into this bond.
In the year zero-- right now, when we purchase this bond--
we pay its price, $97.
This price buys us the ability to get our money, or the face
value of this bond of $100, back at the end of year three
plus the coupons or the interest that this bond pays.
In year one, we'll get the first coupon,
indicated as C1 on this chart.
The coupons are usually quoted as a percent
of the face value of the bond.
The face value of this bond is $100.
If the coupon is 1%, it would mean
that at the end of year one, we will
get 1% of $100, which is $1.
This will be our cash flow at the end of year one.
At the end of year two, we will get the same cash flow.
So it's the same coupon payment.
Well, we'll get 1% of $100, or $1.
That's our second cash inflow.
Finally, at the end of year three,
we will get our face value paid to us from the bond, which
is $100, plus the last coupon, which is another 1%
of $100, which is $1.
So the end of year three, we will get $101 paid to us.