INSTRUCTOR: So the second part of our class today,
we talked about depreciation and property, plant, and equipment.
Now we're going to talk about intangible assets
and amortization.
Remember, we just did the Hertz case.
Hertz has cars.
Cars are things you can touch.
So you can touch a car.
So tangible assets are things you can touch, inventory
in property, plant, and equipment.
Tangible assets have physical substance.
Intangible assets are things you can't touch,
such as patents, or brand value, or the value of your customers.
Intangible assets do not have physical substance.
So when you think about it, if we make an investment in R&D--
so we're developing some software,
as we develop that software and build that software out,
it's sort of similar conceptually
to investing in a building and building that building out.
However, the accounting is completely different.
So internally developed intangible assets
are expensed as opposed to property, plant, and equipment,
where you capitalize the value of property, plant,
and equipment and put it on the balance sheet as an asset.
The logic of this is what we talked
about in the very beginning of the course is,
for intangible assets, the future economic benefit
is thought not to be reliably measurable.
Whereas if we buy a car or if we buy a building,
the future economic benefits of those cars and buildings
are thought to be more reliably measurable.
So exceptions here-- and then we're going to talk about this
in the remainder of the class--
is certain software development expenditures.
And then in a later class when we talk about acquisitions,
we'll talk about how when you buy intangibles
from another company, those intangibles
will go on your balance sheet.
So as an example of the magnitude of intangible assets,
we're going to compute the value of Microsoft's
off-balance sheet assets as of their most recent fiscal year
end, as of June 30, 2019.
Now Microsoft is one of the biggest companies in the world,
so all these numbers are in billions.
So their balance sheet shows that their total liabilities
have a book value of $184 billion.
Their book value of stockholders' equity
is $103 billion.
And their total assets, which are
equal to total liabilities and stockholders' equity
are $287 billion.
So now let's figure out what the market value of these assets
and liabilities are.
So the one we can look up in the newspaper
is the market value of stockholder's equity.
So as of 6/30/2019, Microsoft had about $8 billion shares
outstanding, and its price was about $135.
If you multiply those two numbers together,
the market value of Microsoft stockholders' equity
was $1.037 trillion.
So we can estimate the market value
of Microsoft stockholders' equity.
Now let's estimate the market value
of Microsoft's total liabilities.
We'll see in a later class the total liabilities have
a market value often of approximately
the same as the book value.
So we're just going to estimate the market value of Microsoft's
liabilities are equal to their book value of $184 billion.
And then we'll add down, and notice
that Microsoft's total assets are worth $1.2 trillion,
but their book value is only $0.3 trillion.
So Microsoft is missing from its accounting statements
$934 billion worth of market value.
So again just summarizing, as of June 2019,
Microsoft had a market value of equity of $1 trillion,
while their book value of equity was only $100 billion.
So how is it that $934 billion worth of market value
is missing from their total assets
and from their book value?
Well, a large part of this is that they
have a lot of valuable intangible assets
that, by the rules of GAAP, do not
appear on their balance sheet.
These intangible assets include all
of Microsoft's intellectual property--
so their patents, their copyrights,
and their trademarks.
They may have licenses.
They may have franchise rights.
The Microsoft brand is worth something.
So we're missing the brand value off the balance sheet.
All the customers that they have-- they
have lists of all their customers.
That's valuable as well.
And goodwill, as we'll talk about later,
is also missing from their balance sheet.