PROFESSOR: We're going to now examine
intangible assets, particularly intangible assets held
by software companies.
So as noted above, under GAAP, internally
developed intangible assets are expensed.
The one exception is software development expenditures
and intangibles purchased from another company, which
we're going to talk about in a later class.
Now this is not on the exam, but just as background,
the US accounting system has some rules
for capitalizing software development costs.
So instead of just expensing software development costs,
we're going to capitalize some of those costs
and put them on our balance sheet.
So the rules are basically when you're doing research,
so like if you're developing an app
but you don't know whether the app is going to work or not,
you're going to expense the cost in the preliminary development
phase.
Once you've gotten the app to a point where it's likely
that you'll be able to complete it and sell it,
you're going to start capitalizing those development
costs.
After those development costs are capitalized,
they're going to be expensed just
like depreciation on a building, but now we're
going to amortize them over the useful life of the software.
And then we're going to look at some companies, some health
care companies, that develop software for internal use,
and then again this is not on the exam,
but apparently the rules for software development
for internal use is a little looser in the sense
that you can put more of the costs on your balance sheet.
And here there's a lot of variation in practice.
So Mulford and Roberts in 2006 do a nice study
and they find that almost 3/4 of US software companies,
71% of US software companies, don't
capitalize any of their software development costs.
So in some sense what they're saying is that by the time
the software is ready to come to market,
they've already had all the costs associated with it.
So they're not going to capitalize any cost.
But remember there's about 30% of software companies that
do capitalize costs.
And then more broadly, IFRS encourages capitalization
of development costs in addition to software costs,
but Mazzi et al., 2019, find that over 60%
of non-US companies that do research and development
don't capitalize any costs.
So the bottom line here is there's a lot of discretion
and judgment involved in whether and how much costs
are capitalized.
And the intuition of it again is I'm making my app.
When do I stop doing research on the app
and when do I sort of have a working model of the app?
And I'm developing the app and I can start capitalizing costs.
And I think a lot of companies just
think that maybe we just want to expense everything,
as that way we don't have to keep
track of what to capitalize.
So it's cheaper to just expense everything maybe.
And then investors don't seem to mind if companies write off
or expense everything rather than capitalizing some things.