PROFESSOR: Now we're going to talk about comparability.
And just as a reminder of what we
were doing earlier with depreciation,
let's suppose a company buys a computer server,
and it pays $100,000 for that server.
To keep things simple, let's assume
there's no residual value.
If the useful life is five years,
how much will depreciation expense be per year?
Well, $100,000 divided by 5 years is $20,000 a year.
Now let's assume the use life is two years, how much
depreciation expense per year?
So that's the same $100,000 investment,
now we're depreciating that over two years.
So depreciation expense is $50,000 a year.
Now with intangibles, it's exactly the same concept.
So we're going to capitalize $100,000 worth of the software
costs.
Again, we're assuming no residual value,
but with intangibles the word is amortization, not depreciation,
but it's the same concept.
So if we have $100,000 of costs, useful life
is five years, than 100,000 divided by 5 years is $20,000.
So we're going to amortize $20,000 of these software costs
a year.
Similarly, if the useful life is two years,
we're going to amortize 50,000 of these costs over two years.