PROFESSOR: So to understand the cash flow statement,
we're going to look at an interesting company, which
is Amazon.
So you've got the case materials in front of you.
And we're going to talk about Amazon's cash flow
statement and Amazon's performance, in general.
So thinking about Amazon's performance,
from 2014 to 2016, which is what's in the case materials,
we see big increases in net income.
We see big increases in cash.
And we see big increases in the stock price.
For the last 20 years or so, Amazon
hasn't been that profitable.
But we also see big increases in cash for the last 20 years
for Amazon and big increases in the stock price for Amazon.
And you can see this from the case in this picture
here where the orange line, which
is a flat line that goes across, is Amazon's net income.
It says that Amazon, in the last 10 years or so,
hasn't been all that profitable.
But if you look at the red line, you
see that cash flow has really accelerated.
So Amazon is doing something to generate
lots and lots of cash flow.
And when it generates that high amounts of cash flow,
it's generating large increases in the stock price,
as you can see from the blue line there.
And then, just putting some numbers to the case
so that we can talk about some numbers together--
so we'll look at a bunch of performance measures
here in the first column.
We're going to look at them in 2016, 2015, and 2014.
So you can see that sales in 2014 was about $90 million.
And sales has increased substantially
in the years up to 2016.
Net income has also increased substantially,
operating cash flow, or cash flow from operations,
and then you use the acronym CFO,
for Cash Flow from Operations.
We see that cash flow from operations from 2014 to 2016,
has almost-- has more than doubled.
And then we'll talk about, later,
what this investing cash flow means
and what this financing cash law means.
So let's look more formally at Amazon's cash flow statement.
So there are three sections to a cash flow statement.
At the top of the statement is operating cash flow
or cash flow from operations.
This is the cash that's generated
from our primary business activities.
Amazon sells goods over the internet.
Amazon has a web service as well.
So a lot of its cash flow from operations
comes from selling goods and rendering services.
Also, we record interest income and dividends
received in the statement in the operating section.
So if Amazon owns bonds and gets interest income
from those bonds, that will show up in the operating section.
If Amazon receives dividends because it owns stock,
that will also show up in the operating section.
Our second section, in the middle of the cash flow
statement, is the investing section.
So operating says, how do we do in our operations?
How much cash flow did we generate in our operations?
Investing is, what do we do with that cash flow?
Did we buy Property, Plant, and Equipment, PP&E?
Did we sell property, plant, and equipment?
Or did we buy securities in other firms?
Did we make investments in other firms' stock or debt?
So that's going to be in our investing section.
And then, finally, financing--
if we don't generate enough money from operating,
and we are spending lots of money on investing,
we have to come up with cash flow to finance the firms.
And the financing section of the cash flow statement
tells us where our financing is coming from.
So did we issue stock?
Did we issue debt?
Did we pay dividends?
That would be a financing use of cash flow.
Did we repurchase stock?
That would be a financing cash flow.
Did we repay or repurchase debt?
That also would've financing cash flow.
And the final point of the statement of cash flow
is operating, investing, and financing.
Those three activities are going to sum
to the actual change in cash and cash equivalents
during the year.
You can see that from the Amazon case.