PROFESSOR: To set this up, remember our discussion
about Zsa Zsa Company in our earlier class discussion
on depreciation expense.
When Zsa Zsa buys a $20,000 car, cash decreases and property,
plant, and equipment increases.
Recall that we set up the accumulated depreciation
contra-asset account to record depreciation.
Then, every year following the purchase of the car,
we're going to increase depreciation expense
and retained earnings, which reduces net income.
And we're going to balance the balance sheet
equation by increasing the accumulated depreciation
contra-asset.
But the key point is, after we buy the car for cash,
depreciation expense has no effect on cash.
Now let's look at Amazon's depreciation in 2016.
So how much did Amazon pay for property, plant, and equipment,
or PP&E, in 2016?
We're going to use the BSE to account for this transaction.
So we're going to acquire some assets.
If we look at the cash flow statement in the investing
section, we'll see that we invested $6.7 billion
in new property, plant, and equipment.
And that's a reduction in cash.
So that's the balance sheet equation entry--
similar to the one we just did for Delta.
Now, let's just make some assumptions here.
Let's make the assumption that, when
we buy this new property, plant, and equipment,
it has a five year useful life and it has no salvage value.
As intuition for this, remember that Amazon has web services
and that web services is growing a lot.
They're buying lots of servers.
You might imagine a server, which is a fancy computer,
is a short-lived asset.
So that server is not going to last very long.
So maybe it lasts five years and maybe that server
has no salvage value.
So if we compute depreciation for these new servers, say,
we're adding $6.7 billion of assets.
They have no salvage value.
So we're dividing $6.7 billion divided by 5.
And that's going to give us a depreciation
expense of $1.3 billion a year.
And this is all review, but this just sort of shows you
why increases in property, plant, and equipment
are going to lead to increases in depreciation expense.
And if you just look in Amazon's investing activity--
so this is, again, their cash flow statement from the case.
So I've just highlighted, here, Amazon, the last three years,
has bought $6.7 billion worth of equipment in 2016,
$4.6 billion equipment in the prior year,
and about $5 billion of equipment in 2014.
And so when we think, why is Amazon's depreciation expense
going up over time, Amazon is growing their property, plant,
and equipment.
And if you have more property, plant, and equipment,
at a gross level, that means more depreciation.
If you look at the balance sheet,
you can see that our property, plant, and equipment--
or Amazon's property, plant, and equipment net
grew by about $8 billion in 2016.
And then, as we just saw in the investing section,
over the last three years, Amazon
has purchased over $16 billion worth of property, plant,
and equipment.
And that's the sum of the $6.7 billion in 2016,
the $4.6 billion in 2015, and the $4.9 billion in 2014.
And it hasn't been selling any material
amounts of fixed assets.
If Amazon was selling fixed assets,
we would see those sales also on the investing section
of the property, plant, and equipment.
So again, in terms of why depreciation's going up
over time, more property, plant, and equipment
means more depreciation.
Why is Amazon growing its property, plant, and equipment?
Well, for one thing, as we've seen before,
its sales have grown at a very fast rate-- so 24%
annualized in the past three years ending 2016.
If you're selling more stuff, that
means you need more distribution centers.
You need more trucks and stuff like that.
So you have to buy more property, plant, and equipment
to support your sales.
Also, Amazon hasn't just grown fast in the past.
It expects to grow fast in the future.
And if we want to grow fast in the future,
we need to invest in property, plant, and equipment, or fixed
assets, to support this growth.
So there's an interesting article from The Wall Street
Journal from 2018 titled "Big Tech to Get Its Head Out
of Cloud Frenzy."
And it talks about these hyperscale networks
owned by Google, Amazon, Microsoft, and Facebook.
And what they're talking about are the cloud servers
or the web services, as Amazon calls it.
So these networks, the article says,
demand a staggering amount of capital expenditures.
So if you're going to serve companies and put
their data on your servers, you have
to buy lots and lots of servers.
And what's really fascinating here
is that these four companies spent $35 billion
in the first six months of 2018.
And that number's up 60% from the same period last year.
So even though these web businesses
sound like they're really profitable,
they also require lots of financing cash
flow and investing cash flow.
So you have to invest quite a bit
to build these web services.
So that concludes our discussion on depreciation.
It gives us some idea of why Amazon is increasing
the amount of depreciation expense
it has each year, partly because of its web services,
and it tells us that that depreciation
is a non-cash charge that reduces net income
but doesn't affect cash flow from operations.