PROFESSOR: Now we're going to talk
about a similar thing, which is stock-based compensation.
So Amazon, recall, gives its employees $3 billion
of stock, at least in the last year.
When Amazon gives its employees stock,
it gives them something that's not cash.
So it's an expense that reduces net income.
But it does not reduce cash flow from operations.
We're just going to work through a couple of examples
using the balance sheet equation here.
So as a review, if we pay an employee $1,000 in cash,
then cash is going to go down by $1,000.
So we reduce cash by $1,000.
And then we've got a wage expense of $1,000.
Now, what happens, as review again,
if we sell $1,000 worth of stock?
So if we sell $1,000 worth of stock,
contributed capital is going to go up by $1,000.
So that's the right-hand entry.
And we're going to get cash of $1,000.
And then finally, if we pay an employee $1,000 worth of stock,
well, we know there's going to be a wage expense.
So retained earnings is going to go down.
But what's the entry that's going to balance the balance
sheet equation?
So when we issue stock, we increase contributed capital.
So when we pay an employee in stock, wage expense of $1,000
is going to be offset by contributed capital of $1,000.
So the point of this is the third transaction.
When we pay somebody in stock, even
though we have a wage expense that reduces net income,
there's no cash effect so that nothing happens
to cash flow from operations.
So now we've talked about an example
of why depreciation expense is something
that we add back to net income.
We talked about an example of why stock compensation
expense is something we add back to net income.
We're going to now talk about Amazon's
third major adjustment, which is making adjustments for changes
in working capital.
And working capital is a term that's used a lot.
And I just want to define it, basically,
as working capital is the difference
between current assets and current liabilities.
So assets that are going to pay off
in the next year minus liabilities
that we have to pay in the next year--
that's called working capital because we have it
to work with in the next year.
Most people, when they're talking about working capital,
are actually talking about non-cash working capital, which
means current assets other than cash.
So we take current assets and subtract off cash
and then subtract off current liabilities.
And then we've talked a lot in the course
today about working capital accounts--
in particular, non-cash working capital accounts.
Accounts receivable is a current asset.
So instead of somebody paying us cash, they paid us credit.
Inventory is a current asset, prepaid assets.
Accounts payable is a current liability.
So instead of paying our suppliers in cash,
we pay them with paper, which is an accounts payable.
And then unearned revenues--
so we've got money.
But we haven't delivered the services.
So now we're going to talk about why changes in working capital
affect cash flow from operations.
And we're going to just do this in a sequence of examples.
So suppose that we buy $1,000 worth of inventory for cash,
we being Amazon, and we want to use the balance sheet
equation to account for this transaction.
So if we buy inventory for cash, cash
is going to go down by $1,000.
Inventory is going to go up by $1,000.
Does this affect cash?
Well, we see that cash went down.
So clearly, yes.
Does it affect net income?
We don't see any accounting for net income.
So clearly, no.
So because of the fact that this reduced cash,
but it did not reduce net income,
we need to subtract the $1,000 from net income
to get cash flow from operations.
So this was an example using a current asset.
Now we're going to do an example using a current liability.
So let's look at deferred revenue.
So suppose Amazon sells a gift card or sells services
and it gets $1,000 before it does
any providing of the services.
So let's use the balance sheet equation to account
for this transaction.
So as a review, we know that cash
is going to go up by $1,000.
And we know that unearned revenue
And this is not regular revenue.
It's unearned revenue because of the fact
that we haven't provided the service yet.
So does this transaction affect cash?
Clearly, yes.
We see that cash goes up.
Does it affect net income?
Again, we don't see an accounting for net income.
So there's no accounting for net income.
So because of the fact that we got this income
in cash ahead of time, we need to add $1,000 in net income
to get to cash flow from operations.
So those are two examples of why changes in working capital
accounts are going to be an adjustment
to cash flow from operations.
So our recipe to get to cash flow
from operations from net income, and you can see this, again,
illustrated in Amazon's cash flow from operations,
is-- remember that cash flow from operations
is equal to the net income minus accruals.
So we're going to start with net income.
And then we're going to add and subtract accruals
to get to cash flow from operations.
So we're going to start with net income.
So the top of our operating cash flow statement
is always going to be net income.
Then we're going to add non-cash expenses.
So these are expenses that lower net income,
but don't require cash.
We just worked through two examples of that.
Depreciation expense reduces net income,
but doesn't have any cash effect.
Similarly, stock compensation reduces net income,
but has no cash effect.
And then we didn't see any examples
of this in Amazon's case.
But remember when we were talking about property, plant,
and equipment in an earlier class, when
we sell property, plant, and equipment,
we may have a gain on sale.
That's going to be part of net income.
But that's an investing activity.
So we want to subtract that gain on sale
or subtract any loss on sales from property, plant,
and equipment sales.
So that's our second adjustment.
And then our third and final adjustment
is adding and subtracting changes
in non-cash working capital accounts.
And that'll give us cash flow from operations,
as we saw from Amazon's cash flow statement earlier.
So this chart is basically a summary
where we put things in buckets, showing Amazon's cash
flow from operations.
So in 2016, Amazon had net income of $2.3 billion.
It had depreciation of about $8 billion,
stock compensation of about $3 billion,
other adjustments of about a billion dollars,
and the $4 billion change in working capital.
And that gave operating cash flow.
So what you probably want to do at home now
is just look at Amazon's statement
and see how we've done these groupings here,
see how we've taken Amazon's net income to its cash flow
from operations.