PROFESSOR: In the remainder of this class,
we're going to have some fun and talk about some examples.
So one piece of lingo used in the US markets is the word
FAANG, F-A-A-N-G, referring to tech stocks Facebook, Amazon,
Apple, Netflix, and Google.
And you see that chart there from the Motley Fool
that shows that all of these stocks
have outperformed the S&P 500 index in the last 10 years
or so.
And these stocks or these tech stocks
are thought to drive the market.
So you'll often hear reference to the FAANG
stocks are driving the market.
So I want to talk a little bit about Netflix as a comparison
to Amazon.
So this is an article from Barron's, also from 2018.
And Barron's is an investment publication put out
by The Wall Street Journal.
And if you're interested in investing as a career,
I would encourage you to pick up Barron's, which is published
once every week on Saturday.
Read through that on Saturday morning.
There's lots of interesting stories about investments here.
So this story's about Netflix's earnings,
and it's entitled "Where Accounting Meets Showbiz."
And it talks about Netflix earnings are a creation
of accounting practices.
So Netflix, as you know, is always
making these original shows.
The original shows are quite costly.
So if you make House of Cards or something like that--
I'm not up on the most recent Netflix.
But if you make House of Cards, that thing
might cost, like, $100 million.
So you're investing a lot of money
into creating this original show.
And when you're making these investments,
your operating cash flows are quite negative.
But because of differences in US accounting standards,
Netflix has earnings on its income statements
even though cash flow is very negative because the accounting
rules allow what the article writer calls show business
companies to capitalize their production expenses.
And this sort of leads into two somewhat confusing things
if you don't know this accounting.
So a biotech company, if it develops a drug,
all of its development costs are going to be expensed.
And you would think that Netflix developing an original show
as a risk level comparable to a drug company developing
a new drug.
But Netflix-- because of show business accounting
rules, Netflix gets to capitalize those costs.
So those costs go on balance sheet.
The second accounting difference is that, these development
costs for these original shows, they're
not considered to be an investing cash
flow like property, plant, and equipment.
But they're considered to be an operating cash flow.
So what this all means is, when you look at Netflix
and compare it to Amazon--
this is 2016 numbers.
And here I have scaled net income and operating cash flow
by sales.
The reason I did that is because-- you can see
by the sales numbers there--
Netflix is a much smaller company than Amazon.
So by expressing net income as a percentage of sales and cash
flow as a percentage of sales, we're
sort of able to look at these two companies on a more apples
to apples basis.
So Netflix's net income is 2% of sales,
whereas Amazon's net income is 1.7% of sales.
So if you just are focused on the income number,
you think that Netflix is a much more profitable company
than Amazon.
But if you look at operating cash flow,
Netflix's operating cash flow is a minus 17%, basically,
whereas-- we talked about earlier--
Amazon has huge operating cash flow equal to 12% of sales.
So it shows you that it's worthwhile
looking at both income and operating cash flow.