[Professor:_] Back to Amazon for a second,
we can see from its cash flow statement what it's doing with
its cash flow from operations.
So in 2016 at the start of the year, Amazon had $16 billion
worth of cash on its balance sheet.
It generated another $16 billion in operating cash flow.
It used that operating cash flow. $10 billion
of that operating cash flow was used
to make investments to buy property, plant,
and equipment mainly.
And another $3 billion of that operating cash flow
was used to repay financing.
So we had a negative financing cash flow.
And that gives us ending cash of 19.--
$19 billion.
So in terms of investing, as we saw before,
Amazon is buying lots of property, plant, and equipment.
So it bought $7 billion of property, plant, and equipment
in 2014.
And if you look at the cash flow statement in the case,
you can see that Amazon is also buying some stock
and debt in other companies.
In terms of financing, even though Amazon
generates lots and lots of cash, it doesn't pay a dividend.
It does not repurchase stock.
It had made some repayments on debt.
And then puzzlingly, when they have lots and lots of cash,
they raised $6 billion in debt in 2014.
And maybe that was because they saw
themselves buying Whole Foods.
And the Whole Foods acquisition in 2017 was a $19 billion
acquisition.