PROFESSOR: And then just switching gears
a little bit to Tesla, which has historically
been a company with very negative free cash flow
as well, its earnings announcement the journal
says, "thanks largely to stretched accounts payable,
Tesla even generated record free cash flow of about $1 billion?"
What does stretched accounts payable mean?
So this just means that in this quarter
Tesla did not pay off its suppliers.
So its accounts payable became larger.
And as we talked about earlier, if you don't pay off
your suppliers that's a source of cash flow
so that it has the effect of increasing cash
flow from operations.
Why does this increase free cash flow?
Well, again, from our definition of free cash flow, which
is cash flow from operations minus capital expenditures,
anything that increases cash flow from operations
is going to increase free cash flow.