PROFESSOR: So wrapping up this class, which I
hope you have found enjoyable.
We talked about the statement of cash flow.
And the statement of cash flow tells us
where our cash comes from.
Does it come from operations?
Does it come from investing?
Does it come from financing?
And it's a useful statement.
Most people tend to look at the income statement only,
but it's a useful statement in telling us where the company's
growth comes from.
Is it financially healthy or not?
It's a way to evaluate financial company performance.
So if you take two companies, if they have the same amounts
of net income, you feel more confident in the company,
like Amazon, that's also generating lots of cash flow
from operations.
You need cash flow from operations.
You can't be like Netflix, where you continually
have negative cash flow from operations.
We can't pay bills with net income.
You can't pay bills without cash flow from operations.
It's important to be liquid.
So liquidity matters, and we need cash flow from operations.
Though my bottom line is black, I am flat on my back.
My cash flows out.
My customers pay slow.
A growth of my receivables, is almost unbelievable.
The result is certain, unremitting low.
And I hear the banker utter an ominous low mutter,
watch cash flow.