PROFESSOR: Models we study for applications in finance
are not just mathematical constructs,
they're tools that we use as approximations to reality
and that we use for interpreting data and understanding
the world around us.
Now in finance, the problem we have
is quite different from that we have in the physical sciences,
even though some of the mathematical tools
are quite similar.
Rutherford once said that if your experiment needs
statistics, you should have done a better experiment.
But in finance, we're really quite different from laboratory
sciences.
Most of our data is noisy.
We need statistics, we need tools
to get to the bottom of it.
Furthermore, we can't repeat an experiment,
not in a true laboratory sense.
Actually, we have an interesting dichotomy.
We've got on the one hand, that we often
deal with market data and historical market data.
And that is almost by definition reproducible.
If we plug-in the same numbers, we
should get exactly the same answer no matter
who does the calculation.
That's a good reason why it's interesting exercise
to pick up previously published papers
and work and reproduce their results.
Unlike a laboratory result, you should
be able to get exactly the same thing if you
can get your hands on the same historical market
data on which some empirical studies were based.
On the other hand, markets change.
We can't go back in time.
And all of our results are going to generally be provisional.
So this leads to a different perspective on modeling,
and often to the difficulty in settling questions.
And one that we'll take a look at
is going to be the role of the random walk
model and the so-called random walk hypothesis.
What does it say and can we test it?
More generally when we're looking at models,
we have a bunch of questions that we want to ask.
And I'll talk about a few of them now
and will develop more of them over the course of this lecture
and beyond.
We'd really like to know would be,
what's the model that generates the data that
determines how prices move, how variables evolve and so on.
But nobody tells us that there is such a thing.
There might not be such a thing.
If there is, it might change and we can't look it up in a book
exactly.
What we're typically faced with when it comes to real world
problems is data, and maybe a whole bunch of different models
and some candidate models.
So the questions we ask includes these, and not
necessarily in this order.
What's the model that best fits the data?
If we have a choice of models.
If the models have adjustable parameters,
how should we find the best values for those parameters?
How do we decide among the better of two models?
It might have a different number of adjustable parameters.
Do the models of a stationarity?
That is, do they describe the evolution
of our variables of interest in a way
that the models themselves don't change over time?
That is the probability distributions
are stationary over time, the so-called time's translation
invariance.
How should we be estimating our parameters?
How can we take a look at what's going on with data?
Before we build models and test them,
we might want to take a look at the data
and see if there's some general attributes that
suggest the kind of models that might or might not
be appropriate.
So we often do some initial exploration.
And sometimes we do this with the same statistical tools
that show up in other settings as well.
We often want to test hypotheses.
Is this model correct or is it not?
That's our simplest version.
Or if we have a bunch of models, which of the models
is the best?
And finally, we'll take a look when
we look at structured models of information propagation
in time series models as to how we can decide about what
the appropriate correlation links are,
what the distances are, what the order and class
of an appropriate model is.
There's not always an easy answer.
So let's review for a moment, just a couple of the basics.