PROFESSOR: You know from statistics
that a statistic is a function of the data.
It's a formula into which we can plug numbers and get out
another number.
And the classic examples in two of the most useful ones
in finance are the mean and the variance.
So the mean, we take a bunch of numbers,
compute their arithmetical average.
That's a function.
We could have taken other functions.
We could have taken their sum.
We could have taken different weighted averages.
This is a particular statistic that gives us a summary number
given a time series-- or a collection, actually,
not necessarily ordered--
values R sub t.
Same thing for the variance.
We can compute this.
Now, descriptive statistics don't require a model.
And one thing they do is they reduce
a large number of values down to a small number of values.
So these two numbers mu and sigma
can characterize a set of r's of arbitrary size.
So that obviously means that we're
throwing away information.
We're going from a large number of values down to two.
For these to be useful, we should in some sense
capture values that matter to us for what we're
doing in the sense that if we had two different collections
of r's, two different samples that were taken
and they had the same summary statistics,
we've got a good collection of summary statistics
if we feel about the same.
In this case, we often think of mu and sigma
as being the mean return and risk associated
with an investment or an asset.
And two assets that had similar mu and similar sigma might be
things that we would feel similarly about,
whereas if one had twice the return of the other for a given
level of risk we would differentiate them without
needing to dive into the details of the r's.
So that's a sign of well-chosen and well-behaved statistics.
But this is purely descriptive, and it
doesn't require any kind of model or anything further.
An estimator is a random variable.
And the formulas for estimators look quite familiar,
these formulas here.
For an estimate for the mean and for the variance
take a form that is mathematically
identical to what we saw on the previous page.
However, we think about them differently.
In this case, we don't yet have the data.
We think about them being a function
of future observations.
So they're random variables in the sense
that given a particular set of realizations,
particular set of draws from a distribution,
we'll get different values.
So mu hat and sigma squared hat may take different values based
on different observations.
So as a random variable, an estimator
has a distribution that's known as the sampling distribution.
And the first and second moments are easy to compute and derive.
And because of the central limit theorem,
if we've got well-behaved estimators,
then we run into the situation that we
might expect where the distribution,
the sampling distribution can approach
a Gaussian as the number of observations gets very large.
So that's one of the reasons we like large statistical samples.
We have good statistics, it gives us
not just the narrow distribution,
but it also gives us one that has a well-known shape
and approaches the Gaussian.
An estimate is a number that we get from the same formulas
by applying it to a particular set of realizations.