PROFESSOR: We use these to estimate parameters.
So for example.
In the random walk model that we wrote down,
we had two parameters.
The generalized random walk, we had two parameters--
mu and sigma.
When we did Monte Carlo simulation,
we picked values of mu and sigma and generated
a bunch of concrete numbers on the computer.
But suppose we start from data and we'd like to know.
What should we use for mu sigma if the data
were generated from, say, the random walk model.
What would be the right mu and sigma
that would correspondent that would have generated the data?
And the answer to that, we can find from usual statistics.
For maximum likelihood estimation, and in this case,
we find the mu from the average and the variance
from computing the sample variance
of our set of observations.
Now a quick aside on some things about doing financial returns
in particular, because that's the dominant case where we're
interested in finance where we're looking at time series
analysis.
The usual things that we would see in investment reporting
are going to involve simple returns--
simple returns, monthly returns, annual returns.
And variances or volatilities may be computed
using the simple returns.
But often, mathematically, it's better
to work with logarithmic returns,
continuously compounded returns, rather than simple returns.
Now it's easy-- they're one-to-one
connected because the simple return is
just so I can exponentiate the logarithmic return
and subtract 1 and get the value that I need there.
And for a lot of applications, numerically, the values
are really, really close.
For example, if I'm looking at the equity markets
and I'm looking at returns over a one day time scale,
the numbers, the typical size of the returns, is very small.
And mathematically, these will be quite similar.
But if we want to do things right,
we need to use the correct formula.
These have exactly the same information.
And we can compute the expectations
by changing variables in whichever form is
more natural for us to compute.
To show you the point I made just a moment ago,
if we look at a Taylor expansion of big R in terms
of little r, of simple returns, in terms of log returns,
or if we turn it around the other way,
we can see that the leading order, big R and little r,
they're the same.
However, there are two things we want to keep in mind.
One of them is, deviations can be economically significant.
So if we take a look at things like a typical 10% return
with 30% volatility on an annualized basis,
if we look at the formulas, we can
see that there are deviations depending
on which of the formulas we use to compute them.
The other thing to keep in mind is,
this is great when the values are small, which
they are most of the time.
But when they're not, they're not.
So when we have a day like the stock market crash in October
of 1987 where the market fell by a quarter in a single day,
whether you're using logarithmic returns or simple returns
makes a big deal, and the higher order terms
in the Taylor series matter.
So it's always better to do it right.
In practice, we can sometimes get away
by not taking a look at the difference
depending on what the applications are.
When we're thinking about volatility, though,
and we'll see this when we get to the Black-Scholes equation
when we think about option pricing,
one of the important parameters in the model
is the volatility of the underlying.
And that is something that we need to estimate from data.
So what should we use for our estimator?
Our idea is that we ultimately need to have a good model.
So there are a lot of different possible ways of estimating.
And what we really want the real test
is whether the procedure that we use
produces good applications of the model that ultimately
fit the data in the markets properly.
The typical approach, though, is to use logarithmic returns, not
simple returns, because they're consistent with the formulation
of the model.
That is, within the option pricing models, as we'll see,
there's an assumption that the returns are log
normally distributed, or, in other words,
that the log returns are normally distributed.
If we start from the parameters of the price process,
that if we think of the price as being
the price from the previous day times the exponential
of some logarithmic return, and then we
think about iterating that, that's
consistent with our random walk model here.
Now the drift coefficient cancels out
of the definition of the variance.
But it is required for our estimation of the volatility.
Remember that computing the volatility or computing
variance requires looking at the deviations around the mean.
And the only mean that we have, we're
going to need to estimate from the data.
There are in the literature lots of alternative estimates
that have different benefits.
They have improved efficiency and they take into account
some things we might not see simply from looking
at close-to-close returns.
And a couple of them, like the Parkinson and Garman-Klass
estimators, take into account additional information that
sort of interpolates between the discrete observations that are
usually made for computing returns from the close of one
market day to the next, including, did the price--
where did it achieve a high or a low during the day, intraday,
and do we take into account the open, close, high,
and low during the day.
And that additional information can be helpful.
So ultimately, these are modeling choices
we need to see, but the starting point usually
is the traditional estimator that we looked at before.
Now when we look at hypothesis testing,
the simplest case is taking a model, like the random walk
model, and asking whether it's right or wrong.
So hypothesis testing is the simplest case.
We start with two hypotheses, a null hypothesis
and a alternate, and we define a test statistic
to see if we can reject the null hypothesis.
This test statistic is a random variable.
So we often do this probabilistically.
In classical statistical inference,
we think about a p-value or we look at a z-statistic.
And we say if the null hypothesis were true,
what's the likelihood that we would observe a test
statistic like this or that's this extreme or more.
That is, we look to see how small the p-value is
for evidence to reject the null.
And we compare it to some significance level
that we've hopefully agreed at in advance.
Because the test statistic is a random variable,
it's drawn from a probability distribution.
And if we have a lot of observations to make,
we can re-scale things so that it
looks close to a normal distribution or a related
distribution.
Just to keep in mind, a simple example
before we turn to the random walk--
imagine that we're flipping a coin
to see if it's a fair coin.
So we take a coin, we flip it 10 times,
and we observe a bunch of heads.
And we ask, is the coin fair or biased.
If we don't know in advance whether it's fair or biased,
we might imagine that there's a particular probability
of observing heads.
And we could ask, what's the value of p
and what's the best estimate for p.
And if we do have an estimate for the bias,
how precise is it, how much confidence do we have.
But simple hypothesis testing starts with two hypotheses--
H0, the null hypothesis that the coin is fair,
that the probability is 1/2, the alternate hypothesis that it's
anything other than 1/2.
Question to think about in any of these cases--
what are the appropriate test statistics
that we might choose from.