PROFESSOR: Let's look at alternatives
to the random walk.
If we analyze market data for example for stock prices
in the style of Lo and McKinley doing a variance ratio test,
one of the ways that we can see that the random walk model is
not a good fit for the data is the presence
of serial correlation in returns.
That is, we see that the returns are not in fact independent.
If they were independent, the scaling behavior
as we add together more and more terms would grow.
The variance would grow linearly with time.
And if we observed departures from that,
that doesn't just mean that we reject the random walk.
It gives us a clue as to what we might
want to use to replace it.
So if we're constructing aggregating returns,
say q terms at a time, if they're not independent,
then when we compute the variance the cross terms don't
vanish when we take expectations.
And that's telling us something important.
That's telling us that information is propagating
from one step to the next.
So we want to think about autocovariance
and autocorrelations, which measure the relationship
of the time series with itself.
That's what the auto means.
And we just shift in time by k time steps.
So we want to do this in two ways.
One of them is an expectation for looking
at unrealized, unobserved variables in the future.
And the other is we'd like to look
at estimators for these properties based on past data.
And, of course, we'd expect these to be related.
So the definitions that we have are going to be--
and our notation will be gamma k for the covariance between two
r's of different lags.
When we have a stationary process,
the key thing is it should only depend on the difference
between the time indices.
So t minus t minus k is k.
And that's why I put the label over here.
Notice the gamma k doesn't depend on t.
It only depends on the time difference
on the number of steps between the two arguments,
in this case rt and rt minus k.
Gamma 0 is when I said k equals 0.
And that's the covariance of rt with itself.
And rho sub k is just a normalized version
divided by the variance.
In the same way that we usually compute the correlation of two
random variables by dividing by the square root of the product
of the variances, if it's the same variable,
if it's an autocovariance and we want
to get the autocorrelation, we divide
by the square root of the variance twice, variance times
variance, of the same series.
The series is stationary.
That's equivalent to just gamma k divided by gamma 0.
And this will be normalized.
This will be a pure number, whereas gamma
has units of r squared if r has dimensions.
So for instance, if we think about a sum of two
one-day returns, the variance, if they were uncorrelated,
would be twice the variance of the one day returns.
But if they are correlated there's an extra term.
So the variance of a two-day return, which is--
see if I can get my pointer back--
well, if not we'll use our pen.
The variance of a two-day return,
which is just the variance of two consecutive days,
is going to be twice the variance.
It's going to be the variance of rt
plus the variance of rt minus 1-- it's stationary,
so those are identical-- plus twice
the cross term in expectation.
And that's going to be the covariance r1 and r2.
So we can write that is twice the variance times 1
plus rho 1, where row 1 is the lag 1 autocorrelation function.
That is, it's the correlation of rt with rt minus 1.
So this is going to be bigger or smaller than twice the variance
of a single period return depending
on whether the autocorrelation is positive or negative,
depending on whether the return in one period
is more likely to have the same sign or the opposite sign
of the return in the previous period.
So in order to estimate and compute,
we use our usual formulas for computing covariances
of statistical data and for computing correlations
and statistical data with one caveat.
Normally, we take two time series of equal length.
And to compute their covariance, we subtract off
the mean of each one.
We compute their products and each time period,
and we sum over the time periods.
We have a little bit of an issue when
we look at finite length observations
from actual historical data.
And that suppose we have a series of 100 days.
If we shift by 1, they'll only have 99% days in common.
That will be one off the front and one off the back.
So we need to adjust.
And as we increase the lag s for a given dataset,
we're going to have shorter and shorter lengths in common.
So we need to be careful of that that we don't run out of data
and that we look at the common period.
Usually we make sure that we have a series that
are long enough that the end points won't matter,
that they'll just be small deviations.
But we do need to check that.
Alternatively, we can require that we
have data of a certain minimum length
by saying that we need to have a certain number
of common points.
And then we can account for the overhang for the lag.
So if we want to go up to lag 20, which we would rarely need,
we'd want to make sure that we have enough for 20 points
overhanging at the beginning and enough points in the middle
after we chop off those points.
So the formula we have really is just a--
very much like the formula for computing the covariance of two
random variables.
Subtract the mean, subtract the estimate of the mean.
These should be the same, but we usually
want to compute them appropriately for the length
of the series it enters.
So that because we're not using exactly the same data
series because of the offset because some points are
missing, we want to use the mean for each series.
So it's removed-- we subtract off
the sample mean for the dataset that's there and we compute.
Now, we expect in general to see convergence
depending on the details.
So as t goes to infinity, or as we take a very large number
of points, this estimate should converge to the true gamma k.
And the sampling distributions we can see convergence
in square root of t by choosing to resample things
like-- excuse me, to rescale things.
So that if we want we can think of the errors or the deviations
appropriately scaled by powers of t
so that they are drawn from a standard and 0, 1 distribution,
if we'd like to apply that in a hypothesis testing case,
and we want to take a look at usual confidence,
or significant levels like plus or minus 2.
Now, when we observe autocovariance
what we're looking for is the direction
and the magnitude of departures from a random walk.
And we'd like to know how large the correlation is
from one period to the next.
So serial correlation is a typical analytic and statistic
that we'll run when we get a time series of returns.
It's an important attribute.
After we've computed the mean and the variance,
one of the next things we'll almost always want
to take a look at to characterize what's going on
is the autocorrelation or autocovariance functions.
So in our example of two time steps for lag 1,
we compute this.
We have this expression.
And what we can do is we can compute a variance ratio where
we can compare our variance over two times steps
to what we would have expected had it been a random walk.
This would be 1 under the hypothesis
that it is a random walk.
And deviations from 1 means we have deviations
from random walk behavior.
If it's greater than 1 we have positive serial correlation.
If it's less than 1 we have negative serial correlation.
And we can generalize this to higher steps,
and we can get an expression we can
show with a little bit of algebra
that we can express things as a sum, weighted sum
of the different autocorrelation functions at different
lags all the way up to value q, if we're looking at aggregating
q steps at a time.
So we'll typically look at all lags.
Usually the first one is the one most of interest.
But in principle we can look at any lag at any separation.