PROFESSOR: Forecasts with time series models
are predictions about future observations,
future realizations of our random variables
that are conditioned on information that's known
at the time of the forecast.
Now, what is a forecast?
Well, the output could be one of a number of different things.
It could be a point forecast, for example,
the price of Tesla's stock in 30 days, the specific number.
It could be a probability forecast.
Probability of rain this weekend is 30%.
It could be a full distribution, that
is we might say the probability of stock XYZ,
its return distribution over the next year
is log normally distributed with a mu of 10% and a sigma of 30%.
So any of those could be the output
of a forecasting process.
And, of course, we'll want to evaluate
the quality of forecasts.
And in many ways it's less dramatic or mysterious
than it might seem.
One of the attributes of a forecast
is that it has a horizon or it may have multiple horizons.
That is, a forecast is framed in terms
of two points, the point at which we make the forecast--
and that we need to know so that we
know what information is available
on which to base the forecast--
and the future date when the realization will be known.
Clearly, we can't judge the quality of a forecast
until that date passes.
And then we can compare our predictions
with the subsequent observations.
So we usually think of a horizon.
And as time progresses between now and the horizon,
unless the horizon is five minutes from now
or the next day, if there are multiple steps in which we
could update our horizons based on new information evolving,
the forecast could change.
We may have rolling forecasts.
We may have forecast where we move both the current time
and the deadline, or very commonly, we
have forecasts for a particular date, an earnings release date,
and end of the fiscal year, or picnic weather for this Sunday.
Where as time evolves we may be interested in the same terminal
date which may be fixed on the calendar,
but we have new information that arises
and we can update our forecasts.
So if I said that our chance of rain for Sunday is 30%,
perhaps yesterday I made a forecast
based on what I knew at the time and I said it was 0,
it wasn't going to rain.
And tomorrow my forecast might change again.
Perhaps it goes to 50% as new information comes along.
In time series models we want to know what's available,
what's the information set.
And now we're going to use the same machinery that we
did in solving models in closed form unconditionally,
but now we're going to condition on information
that's available at a particular point in time.
And here's where the lag structure
of models such AR and MA models, and RM models more
generally come in.
So let's take a look at an example.
Let's look at AR1 model.
So here for convenience, I've simplified our usual AR1 model
by defining a new variable y which is
Rt minus mu divided by sigma.
So I've taken our usual defining equation
and I just divided it through by sigma.
Now, this looks like a normalized random variable.
But, remember, that's not necessarily the case.
Sigma is not the standard deviation of R,
it's just the coefficient we put in front of Z in our model.
So this is scaled to be dimensionless.
It certainly looks like it might have 0 mean and some unit 1
size variance, but that's something
that we would need to compute.
We can't just infer that from here.
The reason I defined it this way was
to clean up and reduce some of the parameters
so that we really only have one parameter left
in our model, lambda.
And we can put the others back by re-substituting for y
using this expression.
So in terms of these variables, the AR1 model
takes a simple form.
Y sub t is a new random term.
Z sub t which would be all we'd have if it were random walk.
And if it's autoregressive of order 1,
we have a coefficient which here is
called minus lambda times the previous observation
Y of t minus 1.
If we're forecasting, it's helpful to shift our thinking
from looking backward to looking forward.
So let's just add 1 to t and write it
in this way, which is more a little bit more suggestive
if not more informative.
Let's say that Yt plus 1, the next observation we're
going to have is the next realization
of the random variable Z minus lambda times
the last known observation Y sub t.
Now, suppose we were to compute the conditional expectation
based on the information set available
at time t, which I'm going to denote
just I sub t for the information set.
In this case, it only consists of the past realizations of Y,
because those are the only variables in our problem.
But it might exist of a bunch of auxiliary financial or other
econometric variables.
So, in this case, what I wanted to do
is take an expected value assuming
that I know all of the realizations up through time t
so that Y sub t no longer a random variable.
But everything, Yt plus 1, Yt plus 2, Yt plus 3,
and so on into the future, those have not yet been observed
and they are random variables.
So exactly how I denote this is a matter of convention,
but and these are my conventions.
So hopefully the idea is clear.
Let's take a look at what the consequences are.
When I take expectations of both sides of the equation,
on the left-hand side I have the expectation of Y,
condition on the information set I sub t.
On the right-hand side the expectation of Z
is 0 because it's the standardized random variable.
Its value, its expectation is always 0.
And this term now is a constant because it's already
been observed.
So it's expectation is just equal to itself.
So it's minus lambda times Y sub t.
How do we find the forecast or an expectation two steps
in the future?
We iterate.
So Y sub t plus 2 from the defining equation
for AR1 process, I can just take the previous equation
and write t--
the same way I replace by t plus 1, I'll replace t plus 1
by t plus 2.
So I have this defining equation Y of t plus 2 is Zt plus 2
minus lambda Yt plus 1.
Now, I'm going to substitute my previous equation
for Yt plus 1.
And I can-- just by substitution I can now express Yt plus 2
as Z of t plus 2 which is in the future, minus lambda of Zt
plus 1 which is also in the future,
plus lambda squared times Yt, which is a known quantity.
And now I'll stop.
Take expectations of both sides.
The first two terms vanish because they're Z's.
They have mean 0.
And the expectation for two steps ahead in our process
conditioned on the information available at time t
is equals a lambda squared Y sub t.