PROFESSOR: When we look at forecasting,
there are a number of different elements that come into play.
And I would just like to lay them out for you.
But we're only going to take a look at a small subset of them.
Forecasting is a very big subject.
We're just going to touch on it in the context of time series
modeling applications, so that we
can see how we take the structure of our time series
model and construct specific forecasts based
on given information sets.
So what are the elements of forecasting generally?
Well first, we'd like to know the nature of the process.
Is it something deterministic?
If it's given by a known curve, a sine wave or parabola,
we can predict exactly where something is going to be.
We can tell exactly when the next eclipse of the sun
is going to be.
We know exactly when the next eclipse of the moon
We can even send spaceships to land very precisely,
or send them through the solar system,
because we have deterministic processes that we can solve.
If we have random processes, we don't expect
to get that kind of precision.
We're going to have necessarily probabilistic forecasts.
The processes could be stationary,
they could be non-stationary.
We're going to have very different tools for predicting
them in those cases.
And are they laws of nature or are they human behavior?
They're laws of nature, at least we
know that the process itself doesn't depend
on circumstances around it--
human behavior could change at any time.
How much do we know about the process?
Do we know the process, or do we not know
what the underlying process is?
Perhaps we know the process.
We know what it is, let's say, an AR(1) process,
or an ARMA(1,2) process, but we don't know what the parameters
are.
So in one case, we have to figure out
what model to work with.
In the other case, we may have uncertain estimates
of the parameters which we'd like to apply.
And that will be an additional source
of uncertainty in our forecasts compared to the case where
we know the parameters.
And is this a theoretical model that's
based on some financial or economic ideas?
Or is it an empirical model that's just fit to the data,
and it seems to work.
Or is it a theoretical model that should work?
We have the sort of normative and positive views of things.
And although the approach is going
to be the same, in the way in which we'll
think about evaluating the model quality will be different,
because to the extent that we observe deviations,
it will tell us something about our assumptions
and what we would need to revisit,
and how we would then refine things.
If it's an empirical model, we may
need to get more data or a better data set,
or we might need to find a better model to fit it.
If we have a mismatch with a theoretical model,
perhaps we need new ideas.
Perhaps the ideas that we thought controlled
the processes to produce the variables
were just wrong or in need of some extension
and generalization.
How complex is the model?
The examples we're doing are mostly
going to be univariate models or bivariate models.
So we could have a very large number of variables.
And they could be coupled.
Typically, when we think about multivariate models,
we look for ways that we can simplify them and reduce them
to previous cases.
So it's often possible by taking linear combinations,
to take a multivariate process, particularly if it's
a linear model, and reduce it to a series
of uncoupled separate linear models that then we can solve.
But the techniques will depend.
And linear is usually a fairly straightforward category
with some reliable tools that we can regularly deploy.
Non-linear is kind of an open category where there's
no guarantee of success, and there's not necessarily
a general approach.
Those are not the most common models
that we'll see in finance.
And those will not be among the things
we'll be looking at in our future discussions
or in any of the problems and applications.
We do want to think about what the horizon is.
Do we need one step ahead?
Do we need multiple steps ahead?
That is, would we like to produce
at every possible future horizon?
Does it go off to infinity?
Do we need asymptotic results as t goes to infinity?
Or perhaps, as many financial applications,
we have a finite date.
We have the maturity date for a bond.
We have the ending period for a loan.
We have the expiration date for an option.
And in those cases, we might be interested in forecasts
over only a multiple steps, but maybe only
over a particular horizon, which decreases as time evolves.
What are the forecast criteria?
Are we actually forecasting observable variables or not?
That might seem strange.
You might think, of course we forecast observable variables.
But keep in mind, that one of the things we've already seen
is models where we introduce volatility as a parameter.
We have sigma.
And if we take a model of time varying volatility,
we need to keep in mind that volatility--
while it can be a parameter in a model--
is not an observable quantity.
We can ask what the price of an asset is.
We can't ask what it's instantaneous volatility is.
To know it's volatility, we need to observe it
over a period of time.
We measure the random fluctuations.
And that quantifies what the volatility is.
But if we have a model of dynamic volatility,
where the volatility changes over time--
there are many such models, they're
very important in finance--
but we can't directly observe the volatility.
So we need to do some extra work to be
able to connect the predictions of the model with things
that we can observe so that we can compare predictions
to outcomes, so that we can compare forecasts
to observations.
We'll want to think about measures of forecast accuracy.
How close is close enough?
If we insist on a point forecast being exactly right,
most of our predictions are going to be exactly wrong.
But usually, we'd like to have some measure.
And one of the important things to keep in mind in finance
compared to other areas where we use statistical methods,
and we make predictions, and we make forecasts,
is that we often have a very real cost associated
with error.
So the usual things in literature,
like mean squared forecast error,
are convenient mathematically.
They're somewhat intuitive.
But in finance, we often have other numbers in mind,
like the loss in a particular scenario--
the financial loss, which might not be the same easy
to use mathematical expression.
But we do want to keep track of the fact that the economic cost
of an error, or a deviation, or the benefit--
if it's deviations on the upside--
is something that we can directly
measure and is directly related to issues of valuation.
So we'll often want to think about forecast accuracy--
weighting things by their financial importance,
not just taking an equal weighted average
across all possible kinds of errors.
We might want to weight more heavily the kinds of errors
that we're most interested in avoiding.
Models don't stay the same.
Models change.
Models need to be replaced.
So we want to think about what kind of model evolution
we might expect.
We can have static parameters that stay fixed,
or we might think about having adjustable parameters
that maybe we change over time.
We might think about models where, when we see errors,
we update our parameters, so that we
can make gradual changes to our model as our dataset increases.
As we make more observations, we can improve
our estimates of parameters.
And we may need to think also about identifying situations
where we would declare our model to be broken.
There's some fundamental change in the market,
sometimes called a regime shift or a break
in time series, that's telling us,
hey, that model is not working.
There's something new generating the data.
Someone swapped out one roulette wheel for us,
and they put in another one.
So those are kind of things we want to be aware of.
There's a question, is the model completely static?
Is it somewhat dynamic where the parameters get updated?
And if so, how and when?
And then, when is it time to go shopping for a new model?
How do we set up forecasts?
Well, typically we start with observations up
to some particular time t.
Now, we can't really go for the infinite past.
And hopefully, none of our results
would depend on the series existing in the infinite past.
But what we usually think about for forecasting
is there is some amount of history
up to a particular point.
And maybe we have some set of observations x0, x1, x2, x3,
up to the time xt.
And my convention for forecasting
will be t will be the time at which we're
making our forecast about future values for t
plus 1, t plus 2, all the way up through t plus h, where
h stands for the horizon.
And we assume, that we have the information set
available of everything that happened before and possibly
including the current observation.
And we want to know what happens next.
The probabilities that we're interested in computing
are going to be conditional probabilities.
But it's really the same thing we've already seen.
We're taking expectations.
The only difference is, we need to look at the time index
and not apply stationarity directly.
We can apply stationarity for things
that are random variables.
That is, we can say that the probability
distributions of future realizations are the same.
But that does not mean the past draws from the distribution
are the same.
Even though a head and a tail are equally likely,
or one of the six sides of a die are equally likely,
on our next five random occurrences,
the last five are fixed, because they are what they are.
So that's our distinction between past and future.
We can look at making point forecasts,
and we can think about whether we can have enough information
to generate a full probability distribution for future events,
or perhaps somewhere in between.
Not just a number, but perhaps moments
of the future distribution.
What's the mean?
What's the variance?
And that could tell us something about what our confidence is
and what a confidence interval is around
a forecast for future values.
We can sometimes include subjective information
as well in a Bayesian approach, where
we take information about what our prior beliefs are
as a starting point.
And then, we iteratively update our forecasts
as new information becomes available.
And we do it in a way that's consistent with the laws
of probability.
The optimal forecast we can think
of from a result of Granger as simply
being the forecast at horizon, h,
is the conditional mean of the forecast.
That's our best forecast, provided that the cost function
is symmetric and convex.
So this says that the forecast for a future variable
is, we take its expectation based on what we know now.
We can also compute other moments around it.
But for the point forecast, this is the best forecast
that we can do in terms of minimizing different error
criteria.
So for a given model, we can use the optimal forecast.
And for a given set of data, we're
tasked with finding what the optimal model is.
If we think of a typical kind of random walk-- in this case,
an arithmetic random walk--
where I have a price, and each time
is the previous price plus some new innovation, some new event
that comes along, something with step
size sigma where z is a normalized random variable.
Sigma is the scale of the volatility.
And we ask, what's my forecast h steps
ahead for the value of the price that follows this forecast?
What I do is, I iterate this out to solve for p t plus h
in terms of the previous t's.
I take expectations.
And because all I'm going to do is add together
more z's, and those all have 0 mean,
the expectation of p of t plus h-- given
the information I have available--
is the current price.
That is, the forecast for the price h steps in the future
Now, for a symmetric random walk, that makes sense.
We're equally likely to have disease go up or down.
They will in general diffuse.
They will move around.
They're very unlikely to be exactly back where
we started at p.
Nevertheless, that is the optimal forecast.