PROFESSOR: Let's look at another setting for random walks--
the binomial tree model that's used in option pricing.
In the binomial model, in each discrete time step
a stock price, let's say an asset price,
can move only up or down to a particular fixed value.
This sounds crazy, far away from reality.
Stock prices can move anything, up or down in very small
increments.
But in this model, we say there's only one thing
it can do going up or down.
In typically in the model, we allow the movements
to be by the same percentage increase,
to have the same return in each time step,
so it's a stationary series.
So here's the structure of the model-- time goes to the right.
And in each column, so I start from this point here
and I've labeled all these nodes and I go either
to node 1 or node 2.
And then from each of these other nodes,
I have two choices as time evolves.
Here, I can go to either 4 or 5.
I can go up or down.
If I'm from 5, I can go to 8 or 9.
If I end up a terminal node 8, though, there
are a lot of ways I could have gotten there.
I could have gone 0, 1, 4, 8.
I could have gone 0, 2, 5, 8.
I could go 0, 2, 4, 8.
So if I want to know what the likelihood is to end up
at a terminal node of a particular value,
I can just add up all the possible ways
to get there, multiply times the probability of seeing
that particular path realized.
And that turns out to be essential for doing option
pricing and for managing risk.
But in terms of the basic model, we
recognize right away that's a random walk.
After all, we're taking steps, discrete steps,
in each time period.
And we're looking at the aggregate behavior
of those steps.
And we know that some of the large time properties
are related to the statistical distribution
of the sum of random steps.
So we do this in two steps, no pun intended.
We build the tree, we have a structure
for what the up and down moves represent.
Usually, we have a fixed return associated with up and down.
And that gives us a recombining tree,
where you notice there are two different ways to get, say,
to node 4.
Going up and down is the same as going down and up.
There are trees that don't necessarily recombine,
but in this case we'll keep the recombining tree.
And there are trees also that have multiple branches.
There are trinomial trees and multinomial trees.
But we'll do a look in the binomial tree.
So first we have the tree structure.
We assign to each branch a magnitude
by which the return changes, if we go up or if we go down,
and a probability of that happening.
Once we set up the tree structure,
we're ready to do some analytics and to price derivatives
on this tree, and also to take a look at in this structure
some very interesting possibilities
for exotic options and for different boundary conditions.
So the random walk process is the basis
of one approach to option pricing.
And it's obviously an extreme simplification of the dynamics.
But in the limit we actually end up
getting exactly the same result that we
do through continuous time approaches.
So in each time step the underlying
can either go up or down and we have uncertain payoffs.
Usually in this model, we think of having two assets--
one risky asset and a risk-free asset whose return
doesn't depend on where we are on the tree.
But one of the things we also need
to do to match this to reality is
take our abstract random walk and put some parameters on it.
We need to find out what the appropriate scales are.
And so we need to set the scales.
We need to decide on the returns.
We need to decide on the probabilities.
And that's going to tell us how this can map over
into the real world.
So here's an example of how we set up the structure.
We have a recursive behavior for a random walk where we say,
at each time step the new price, one step ahead,
is going to be the previous price, either times a number
I'll call u for an up move with probability p,
or a down move with probability 1 minus p.
That's one reason why I sometimes use
S instead of p for probability.
S we'll think of as stock price.
So the structure has this tree structure
here where, as I build things up,
I started this node with price S0.
With probability p I can go up and realize the price S0u.
If I go up again, the probability of going up and up
is p squared is my cumulative probability
to get to this point.
If I do so, the asset price with probability p squared
is going to be S0u squared.
Now I could end up if I have an up and down move,
I have two different ways of doing that.
Each of those ways has probability p times 1 minus p,
and I get this value, and similarly
for the downside of the tree.
And I can go at an arbitrary number of steps.
So what's the structure we expect?
Well, it's a binomial tree.
No surprise-- we find a binomial distribution.
The probability of observing a particular stock price
is equal to the probability of our binomial distribution
of the corresponding set of up and down moves.
So in this case if I have t time steps
and I need there to be k up moves,
I have t choose k ways of doing it.
They have probability p to the k, 1 minus p to the t minus k.
It's our old friend the binomial distribution.
Let's look at a concrete example.
Suppose u is equal to 2.
This is rather extreme.
Suppose in each time step the value of the stock doubles.
Suppose if I go down the value of the stock is cut in half.
Suppose the probability of an up move is 1/3,
the probability of a down move is 1/3.
Excuse me, probability of up is 2/3, probability of down move
is 1/3.
And let's suppose we have a starting price of 16.
So the tree looks like this.
16 with probability 2/3 doubles at time 1 to value 32.
And it can double again to value 64.
The probability of getting there at the end of two times steps
is 4/9.
The other terminal values at t equals 2 are 64, 16, and 4.
And that's it, it can't be anything else.
All right, so this is a very rigid model
of how stock prices could evolve and what
their terminal values are.
We can do some of the usual analytics.
For example, we could ask about the distribution
of stock prices at time t.
And here we have it.
So these are probability 4/9 to get a 64, probability 4/9
to get a 16.
Probability 1/9 to get a 4.
And that's it.
Now where it really gets interesting
is when we apply this to option pricing.
Now option pricing-- options are kind of a derivative.
And a derivative is a security whose value
depends on another security.
So you may be familiar with stock options,
and in particular call options that give you the right--
but not the obligation--
to buy security at a fixed price k for a call option,
but you would only exercise that if the market price is above k.
So if I tell you you have the right to buy a stock at $10,
you would not exercise that if the stock were $3.
You'd only exercise it if the price were more.
And then you could realize an immediate profit.
So if you have an option to buy a stock at a strike price
k equals $10, and at the time when the option is
about to expire if the stock price is $64, that means
you could buy it for 10 sell it for 64,
and have a profit of $54.
So no arbitrage tells us that if you
could make that $54 by doing that transaction,
then the value of the option should be $54.
So put options work similarly.
They give you the right but not the obligation
to sell at a fixed price.
You're not going to sell if you could get more money by selling
at the market price.
So put options are valuable if the price goes down.
Call options are valuable if the price goes up.
But in both cases, their value depends
quite asymmetrically on the value of the underlying,
on the value of the stock.
So a common structure that we see
in binomial trees as part of our approach to option pricing
is that first we set up the binomial random walks that
correspond to the stock price movement.
And then we look on the terminal nodes
out here in this example at t equals 2,
and assuming my option expires at t equals 2.
I look at the terminal nodes and I
say, what are the values of the options on the terminal nodes.
And they're determined by the value of the stock
on the terminal nodes.
So if the stock has value 64, 16, and 4,
then the value of a call option C at that point in time
could be 54 in the upper position with probability 4/9.
It could be 6 with probability 4/9,
because there are two ways of reaching it.
Or it could be 0, because we're not
going to buy a stock for $10 if we could buy it
by exercising our option--
if we could just throw away the option, it's valueless,
and we were to buy the stock on the market for $4.
Put options work in a complementary way.
And there's a property called put-call parity, which
you can see here in action.
Where when the risk-free rate is 0,
the value of a call minus the value of a put
is the value of the security minus the strike price.
So here we have the put is worthless
up here, because the stock is worth more than $10.
Here it's worthless stock is worth more than $10.
And down here it's worth $6, because we
could sell for $10 something that we could buy for $4.
The tree becomes useful for more general kinds of problems,
and especially if we have different kinds
of boundary conditions.
So typically we're thinking for a vanilla
option that only expires at a particular point in time.
We go out and we look at the terminal nodes in the tree.
But we might have dividends that occur
at some intermediate point.
We might want to know at intermediate points
on interior nodes of the tree should we exercise the option.
Is it advantageous to do so?
There might be exotic options that if we
hit a particular node, if we go down too
far before we're going up, the option might become valueless.
Those are known as knock-out options.
And there are knock-in options that start valueless.
But if we hit a particular node, then they come to life.
And that splits.
It differentiates among the different paths.
We don't just group them together
and count the total number of combinatorics.
We need to separate those that might pass for a particular
node from those that don't.
So usual, it reduces to problems that we've already
seen in probability where we need
to classify different kinds of trajectories,
compute the probability of each, and then sum up
the ones that are of interest for the particular application.
Now to be able to connect with our previous model, what
we need to do is calibrate the tree.
We need to be able to connect parameters
on the tree with parameters of real-world stock prices.
So if we think of our stock price
as having a random walk with a logarithmic return
variable that takes binomial steps, in this notation,
if we think of r as being defined
as a logarithmic return, then in the binomial model
r would take two values, either the logarithm of u
so that e to the r multiplies St minus 1 by u,
or logarithm of D. So that's straightforward.
If we want to know how to implement our model
and we have a given u and D, this is how we do it
And we can also do it in terms of a typical Bernoulli-type
variable.
If we let x be 1 or 0, we can construct a variable.
Because it only has two states, it doesn't really
matter how we do it.
We can rewrite things for linear transformations
as long as there are two different states.
Here, if I have a 1 and a 0, I can multiply something
and add something else.
And I can relate it to the log u and log D formulation.
So we can use different kinds of formulation.
The basic point is, it's a two-state model at each node.
So to connect this to real world asset values
and their returns and their volatilities,
we calibrate the model by taking expectations.
So we would calibrate mu to be the expectation
of r from the formulas that we had before.
And we compute sigma squared as the variance
by applying the definition and using
our usual results for things that
are constructed out of basic z.
So we put in the distribution of our binomial variables.
We have some extra parameters.
We compute.
And then what we're going to do is we have expressions now
for mu and sigma squared, which are things that we can estimate
and think about in terms of real-world asset
prices, their mean and their variance,
and we can connect them to model parameters
in the random walk, things that are the step size a and b,
the coefficients of the step formulation
in the Bernoulli form I just showed you and p
the probability.
So we can solve for a, p, and b in terms
of the up and down factors, for example.
And we can do that this over here to have a and b
in terms of those with mu and sigma.
And then we can express log u and log D
also in terms of mu and sigma so that if we
have particular real world values of mu and sigma, that
can tell us what u and D we can use on the model that
will give us something that will be
a discrete representation of the real-world drift and volatility
that we want.
Notice that the specification actually matches
different numbers and parameters, that in this case
we have two real world parameters, mu and sigma,
in terms of three model parameters, three unknowns.