PROFESSOR: There's a problem in the classical probability
literature known as Gambler's Ruin that's
a discrete time stochastic process that's
solved in a different way.
And it would be interesting for us to take a look at it.
So here's the idea.
The idea is, suppose that you and I are gambling.
And we begin with the total amount of wealth,
total amount of assets.
Let's call it a.
And in this example on the right hand side,
imagine that there's $10 that we have between us.
And we start with you have $5 and I have $5.
And the idea is, we play a sequence of games.
At each step, if you win, you get $1-- if I win,
I get $1, the total amount of wealth is conserved.
And we play until one of us is ruined--
that is, until either your capital goes to 0 or mine does.
So from your perspective, either you get all the wealth,
or your wealth goes to 0, at which point it stops.
Now, I've shown on the right a picture
that illustrates some possible ways this game might come out
with these starting conditions.
And each color represents a different path.
You'll notice that of the five paths that are shown here,
three of them finish with the player winning--
that is, capturing all $10 that are available.
One of them finishes with ruin--
that is at $0.
And then, it stays there.
Once you're ruined, you're not allowed to make any more bets.
And in the green path, one of them
has not yet hit either end.
It hasn't yet hit 0 or $10.
And we might even wonder if it could just
keep going indefinitely.
So in this kind of game, we have a repeated set of gambles.
And to keep it general, we're going
to allow the probability of success or failure--
our Bernoulli trials-- be asymmetric.
So let's let p represent the probability of success.
q is 1 minus p is the probability of failure.
You start with some initial capital, x greater than 0.
And we have these two classic stopping points,
which are either when you're capital x is equal to 0,
or x is equal to a.
Now, there are two kinds of things that this typifies--
two classes of problems, known as stopping
problems and boundary problems.
The boundary case is pretty obvious.
We have these two cases where our wealth either hits 0
or it hits a, at which point we stop.
So we can ask, unlike us unlike our previous case where
we looked at time series and just said,
you give initial conditions.
What happens in the future?
Here, we have boundary conditions
that specify something specific that occurs
if and when we hit them.
And of course, there are obvious financial applications.
These are things that represent bankruptcy, that's
the classic definition of ruin.
But they might be other events.
For example, hitting a capital reserve requirement,
hitting a credit default trigger, hitting your stop loss
limit.
And we could think of things on the upper limit as well.
We might have a strategy where we terminate an investment
once we reach a desired goal.
The stopping problems are a little bit different.
Those are cases where we want to know,
does a given process stop?
Does it ever reach the condition?
And if it does reach the condition, what
would be an expected time or what
would be the distribution of stopping times?
We might also think about this strategically.
We could have a question where we
ask, what would be the optimal way to say, run a business,
if we wanted to minimize its default probability
or its bankruptcy probability.
So let's look at the math and see how we can do this.
What we'll see is, we have a recursion relation.
But this recursion is not in time.
This recursion is in money.
So here's what we do.
Let's let q sub x denote the probability of ruin--
that is, the probability that we'll eventually hit 0
before x equals a, starting from an initial capital level x.
Now, the interesting thing here is
it does have a Markov structure, because it doesn't matter
what's happened in the past.
All the matters for our probability of surviving
is how much capital we have at the present time.
Probability is obviously conserved.
So the probability of ruin now we
can relate to what happens after our next game.
After the next game, we could win
with probability p, in which case
our capital would be x plus 1.
And that would give us p times qx plus 1.
Or we could lose and end up with capital
x minus 1, in which case, this would
be our probability of ruin.
And adding together these two mutually
exclusive possibilities gives us our original probability.
Now, you can see that this is a recursion relationship in x.
This kind of difference equation where
we have a relation between x minus 1, x, and x plus 1
is similar to differential equations
that are second order.
This is a second order difference equation.
Like the differential equation case,
there are two independent solutions.
And we fix the boundary conditions
by imposing-- we fix the final solution by imposing boundary
conditions on the general linear combination of the two
solutions.
So there's a special case when the probabilities are equal.
Let's do the general case.
In the general case, where p is not equal to q,
you can check by substitution that these
are two different solutions.
One of them is the trivial solution,
that q sub x equals 1.
And that's not an interesting solution to our problem,
saying the probability of ruin is equal to 1,
because we start out not being ruined.
But mathematically, leaving aside the boundary conditions,
it does solve this equation, because p plus q is equal to 1.
The other one is this form here, q over p to the x.
And remember, q is equal to 1 minus p.
And if you substitute this into the equation,
you can check that it works.
Now therefore, the most general solution
is a linear combination of these two special solutions.
So we have two constants.
Let's call them a and b.
So our general solution is of the form
constant plus another constant, times q over p to the x power.
And we fix a and b by imposing boundary conditions--
two obvious boundary conditions.
When x equals 0, we are ruined.
If we have no money, the probability of ruin
is 1, because we're already ruined.
And similarly, if we have all the money,
if our capital is equal to a, our probability of ruin
is 0, because the game is already ended.
So if we impose these, we can solve for a and b,
and we get this result for the probability of ruin--
this expression in the box down here.
This tells us, as a function of a, x, and p
what our probability of ruin is starting from any given
level of capital x.
Now, we can ask a variety of questions
about what happens under these absorbing boundary conditions.
For example, we could ask, can the sequence
continue without terminating?
That is, does the probability of reaching neither x equals a
or x equals 0 in an arbitrary amount of time,
is that some positive number?
Is it equal to 0, which would mean
that we do hit one of the other two boundaries.
We could ask with the expected time is to hit.
If we allowed ourselves to stop differently,
what kind of strategy might we employ, and could we
do something better?
How do we take advantage of unequal odds?
For the case where the odds are equal,
we can do it in one of two ways.
We can either check that 1 and x over a
are special solutions to the equation.
Or we can take the limit, where q approaches p,
using L'Hopital's rule and just taking our general solution.
What do we see about actual numerical values
to get some intuition about what's going on?
Well, one interesting fact about this,
is that if we start very close to taking all the money,
we have a good chance of winning.
Which isn't surprising.
For example, suppose that there's $100 between us,
and we start with $99, and we're playing the house.
And suppose the odds are equal, then
you can check by the previous formula,
we have a 99% chance of winning one more dollar
before we lose all 99% that we have.
Not surprising.
We're close to owning all of the money.
But what's less obvious, is that if the odds are against us,
we still have a very good chance of winning all the money
before we lose what we have.
That is, even when the odds are stacked against us,
if we have sufficient capital reserves, the odds
of attaining a finite goal--
and in this case, a relatively modest goal--
can look very attractive even when the odds are against us.
So the odds are against us, we typically
think it's a game that we shouldn't play.
The expected value's negative, stay away.
We want to look for opportunities
where we have positive expected value in a gamble.
And furthermore, where we give adequate compensation for risk.
If the expected return is negative,
normally we would say, let's leave it alone,
provided there are some other better opportunities available.
But all that changes when we limit our objective,
and we say, suppose I only want a fixed amount of money,
and I'm not going to play the game indefinitely.
In fact, we can go a bit further.
Not only does this sometimes give us
a positive chance for achieving a goal before we get ruined,
but it says, that when the odds are against us, sometimes
we should take even more risk.
What if we change the stakes?
Suppose we increase the bet size from 1 to b,
and let's suppose that b evenly divides a and x,
just for simplicity.
So if we change our bet size, then we update our recursion.
The problem has the same structure,
it's just the individual steps are chunkier.
When we substitute in--
we play the same game as before.
We solve for our formula, we get a new result. And what we find
is, that when the stakes are increased, that if the odds are
against us, we have a lower ruin probability-- that
is, a greater chance of winning all the money
and hitting the upper boundary, than we did before.
So if the odds are against you it
can be advantageous to swing for the fences, so to speak.
That is, you can think of this intuitively
as being kind of a complement to the law of large numbers.
In a game where we play indefinitely,
we know that our expected return is going to be negative.
We of course need to worry about the fluctuations.
But this says, that if there's a definite stopping point,
the fluctuations can be to our advantage
if we stop when we get a fluctuation that's
sufficient for us to hit our upper boundary.
That is, the longer we play, the more likely
we are to grind down and end up ruined.
But if we take larger bets, we're
more likely to have an instance where
we hit our upper boundary.
So lower ruin probability means greater overall chance
of success.
What if our appetite for risk is unbounded.
That is, suppose that a is infinite,
and we want to keep playing, and just
see how much money we could get.
Well, it's pretty clear that if the odds are unfavorable,
that we're never going to get all the money.
We've set ourselves an impossible task.
And in fact, our probability of ruin goes to 1.
In the case where the odds are in our favor,
we can compute what the ruin probability is
and get something potentially that's less than 1.
How long does the game last?
Well, we could ask about its expected duration
in the same way.
But now, things are slightly different,
because now we have a generalization
of our previous equation.
But now we have an inhomogeneous equation.
So let d be the duration of the game.
Then d of x plus 1 is the duration of the game,
starting from x plus $1.
And d x minus 1 is the duration of the game starting
from x minus $1.
And we need to find out d of x is,
that is, what's the expected return as a function of x.
So in our recursion, before we equated this to what's
on the left hand side.
But now, we know that these are related
to one more play of the game, so we add 1
on the right hand side.
So instead of the previous homogeneous equation
where every term involved the d, here we have this plus 1,
where you can check that this gives
a solution to the equation.
Here it's a slightly more complicated formula for p
not equal to q, for p equals q.
This simplifies it to a nice quadratic form.
a x minus x squared for p equals q.
So that tells us, that for example,
in a fair game, if you and I each start with $100--
$200 total, the expected duration of the game
is 10,000--
100 times 100.
And it grows as the square when the stakes are equal.
So let's summarize.
Gambler's Ruin is a problem which
has a recursive structure.
It's a discrete time process in money rather than in time.
And it's subject to boundary conditions.
The boundary conditions tell us when the process terminates.
It's got applications to gambling, obviously,
to insurance where the ruin problem in the insurance
literature is finding the probability that you have
adequate capital to never get ruined
by random processes which represent
the arrival of insurable claims or losses.
It has applications to thinking about bankruptcy likelihood,
credit default, and to bet sizing in investment strategies
or in gambling strategies.
The stopping problems that we consider
are things that could be defined by economic conditions,
such as a company in distress, beating
a particular term in a covenant, or a bank loan being called
subject to certain terms.
We can think about optimal stopping problems, where
we might have different kinds of objective functions
rather than maximizing expected return,
rather than thinking of maximizing Sharpe ratio,
we might think of a business venture
where what we'd like to do as business owners, and investors,
and entrepreneurs is, sure, we might
like to maximize our profit.
But maybe what we'd really like to do
would be to maximize the lifetime of our business
or minimize the probability that we go bankrupt.
And those will not be exactly the same calculation.