JOHN CORE: So in this little segment,
we're going to talk about finding US companies'
financial statements.
So for example, we're going to use Dell's financial statements
later on in this class.
So finding US companies' financial statements.
There are basically two ways to do this.
One is the SEC, which is the US Securities and Exchange
Commission.
It requires that all public companies
file their financial statements with the SEC.
So one thing you could do is pick a company
that interests you, maybe it's Dell technology, maybe somebody
else, go to SEC EDGAR, Google that, and then find the 10K.
But I encourage you very strongly, don't print the 10K,
because often these documents are several hundred pages long.
So nowadays, with Adobe Acrobat, you
can just search the 10K electronically.
The other way you can get a 10K or a company's annual report
is go to the company's investor relations website.
So you might Google, for example, Tesla investor
relations, if you're interested in Tesla.
So here's what it looks like if we search for Dell Technologies
10K on SEC EDGAR.
So we search EDGAR, we put in Dell Technologies,
we put in filing type as 10K, and then
it'll give a list of all the 10Ks that we want,
and then we can click through to get the document that we want.
Alternatively, you can go to a company's investor relations
website.
Here, for example, is Tesla's investor relations website.
And it'll also give you SEC filings.
You can pick out their 10K.
And that 10K comes in Acrobat formats, so PDF,
or it comes as a Word document, and sometimes
what's really handy is you can get it in an Excel spreadsheet
so you can pick up all the numbers in an Excel
spreadsheet.