JOHN CORE: Now let's do a famous example, Hewlett-Packard
company, HP, bought Autonomy, which is a UK software company.
And it paid $11 billion for it in 2011.
A year later, HP wrote down the value of Autonomy,
and it valued at $2 billion.
So in a year on that investment, HP lost 80% of its money.
Now think about your own investing activities.
Think about how many times have you lost 80% in one year?
It hurts.
And this was an $11 billion investment.
So HP has sued Autonomy and said that Autonomy overstated
its revenues, and because revenues were too high,
earnings were too high, and therefore, Autonomy's stock
price was too high.
Because Hewlett-Packard did not recognize these overstatements,
it overpaid for Autonomy.
HP alleges that Autonomy overstated its revenues
by turning software service deals into software licensing
deals.
Why does it matter if software is a license or a service?
So if I sell you a license, I've given you
everything up front so I can recognize most of my revenue
and earnings up front.
If it's a service, I'm promising to give you software over time,
and revenue is going to be recognized,
and earnings are going to be recognized over time
as the services are provided.
And this sort of dribbled out, but one nice story about this
is The Insider Reveals Creative Autonomy Accounting,
where Autonomy did a four year software as a service deal,
so this is something that we should recognize revenue
on over a four year period.
It morphed it into a software licensing contract, and one
of the ways they did that was structure it
so that most of the fees were deemed to be for licensing,
and by doing this, Autonomy was able to book
most of the revenue up front, and by booking the revenue up
front, it makes it look like Autonomy
was growing a lot faster than it really was.
Now one way you can maybe see this
in published financial statements,
this is Autonomy's revenue for the year 2008, 2009, 2010.
So 2010 was the year before they got bought by Hewlett-Packard.
Notice how fast revenue's growing.
Revenue grows from $503 million to $870 million.
I also gathered from the balance sheet
the deferred revenue account, and what
we're interested in here is the change in deferred revenue.
So how much revenue was classified during the year
as deferred revenue?
That's what the change is.
And notice that in 2009, we had change
in deferred revenue, or new deferred revenue, was about 10%
of total revenue, whereas in 2010, that number
drops to less than 1%.
So it suggests that maybe Autonomy, at least in 2010,
was not deferring as much revenue as it had in the past.
So this gives you a way to look at financial statement analysis
to give you some insight into what companies are doing.