PROFESSOR: So now we're going to do
some examples of the new revenue recognition standard,
and we're going to base them on the Spartan case that
was assigned reading.
So let's think about what Spartan does.
So it runs the Spartan Races.
So one product it sells is race entry.
It may sell a parking space.
It may sell a commemorative jacket.
It sells annual race passes.
So instead of a single entry, you can buy a full year entry.
It sells advertising and sponsorship, training classes,
and certification.
So we're going to just look at a couple of these products
and talk about revenue recognition for these products.
So first example, say, on January 1st,
Spartan sells me an annual raise pass for $1,000.
So these things truly do cost this amount.
Does everybody knows what a Spartan Race is?
This is where you just go climb over logs in obstacle courses,
takes like six hours.
You're all muddy.
You feel awful at the end.
There's a high injury rate.
But people pay money to do this.
So if Spartan sells me an annual pass for $1,000,
how does this affect Spartan's financial statements?
Looking at the balance sheet equation--
so one way we could do the accounting
for this is count all the revenue at the time of sale--
so take in cash of 1,000, increase retained earnings
by revenue 1,000.
The second thing we could do is--
when Spartan sells me this pass, it
hasn't provided me any services.
I get to race in the future.
So that accounting, which turns out
to be the correct accounting, is Spartan gets some cash
and it recognizes a liability for deferred revenue
because it's going to provide me the ability to do these races
in the future.
Then, either as time passes or as the race
has occurred but by the end of the year,
we're going to gradually amortize the deferred revenue
and take it into regular revenue.
So which is correct?
As we already talked about, deferring it and then
recognizing it as time passing is a correct way to do it.
Now let's do a second example which is a little bit more
complicated.
And this brings to mind the iPhone example we just did.
So for $800, Spartan sells me a season pass and a jacket
as a package.
So I get the season pass.
I also get a jacket.
Let's pretend that the jacket costs Spartan $50 to make,
and Spartan can sell the jacket in the outside market for $200.
It's going to send me the jacket immediately.
And let's assume that the season package, contrary to what
we just did-- in this example, let's
assume that the season package retails for $750.
Now, to allocate the price here, we're
going to use the relative retail value of each component.
So the jacket's worth $200.
The season pass is worth $750.
So the performance obligation is the pass and the coat.
The pass has a retail value of $750, which
is 79% of the total value.
And then we're going to allocate that
to the bundle price at $800, and that gives us our sales price
allocation of $632.
Now, on this part of it, we're not
going to recognize the revenue now.
We're going to defer the revenue and recognize it
over the course of the next year.
The coat, on the other hand, it has a retail value of $200.
That's 21% of the total retail sales price,
or $168 of the bundle sales price,
and we're going to recognize that revenue now.
So again, continuing on with this example,
then, we're going to get cash of $800, deferred revenue, which
is the season pass-- we're going to defer
the revenue on the season pass, and we're going to recognize
regular revenue or merchandise revenue on the jacket
because we're delivering the jacket right away.
And then we'll recognize the cost of goods sold
associated with the jacket.
So essentially what we're doing here
is we're allocating the transaction
price, which is step 4 of our new revenue recognition rules.
And then we're recognizing revenue
when we satisfy the performance obligation.
So here, the jacket--
the performance obligation-- we satisfy when we deliver it.
The season pass, we're going to satisfy that performance
obligation over time.