JOHN CORE: So now we've wrapped up, for the time being,
revenue recognition.
Now we want to do is talk about estimates.
In particular, estimates for bad debt expense and
estimates or returns.
So remember, in Shrek 2, we talked about product returns
and Dreamworks' failure to correctly estimate
these returns.
Now we're going to look at accounts receivable
and think about why do firm give credit--
if customers are not going to pay, why do firms give credit?
Well, the answer to this is to generate revenue.
So if you make it easier for people
to buy stuff by giving them credit,
maybe they'll buy even more stuff.
If they don't pay, this is a bad debt expense
that we need to match the revenues,
but by giving them credit, we've encouraged
them to buy even more, so even after they
don't pay for all of it, we're still ahead
of where we would be if we were in a cash business.
So for the remainder of this class,
we're going to talk about when we generate revenues--
in particular, credit revenues--
when a customer gives me an accounts receivable,
how do I estimate how much of that
accounts receivable is going to be bad debt,
and how do I allow for that bad debt
so that I can match my expenses to my revenues?
And we're going to look at it in the context of Dell.
So Dell's business model, what's the business?
So we all know Dell is a computer company.
Who are Dell's customers and how do they pay?
Well, they're retail people, like you and me,
and they're wholesale people like corporate businesses.
Some of them pay in cash, and some of them pay in credit.
And again, why do we give them credit?
Because we want to give them the opportunity
to buy more stuff from us, and therefore,
generate more revenues.
Does Dell appear to be successful?
We've got high revenue growth and our stock price
has done very well.
So Dell is a big and successful company.
Here's an example of a Dell product.
So this is their fold over laptop, which, if you buy it,
you get 12 months no interest financing.
So they're allowing you to buy it and not
pay for it for whole year.
So they're allowing you to buy it
with a year's worth of credit.
So again, why do they do that?
Because people are more likely to buy this computer
if they don't have to pay for it right now.
Now let's remember our revenue transactions
from earlier in the class, and we're focused now
on we sell a computer costing $500,
and we sell it for $1,000 on accounts receivable.
So here's our balance sheet equation for it.
The question for this part of the class
is we give somebody credit of $1,000, what happens
if that somebody doesn't pay?
So Dell, in this case, is going to have
some kind of bad debt expense.
And we're going to talk about two ways of accounting
for the bad debt expense.
The first method is called the direct method
and the second method is called the allowance method.
I may just show you the direct method
to give you some intuition for what's going on,
and also, the direct method is required
for income tax purposes.
And then we're going to then discuss two allowance methods.
One is the percentage of sales method,
and the second is the aging method.