PROFESSOR: So in the prior slide,
we saw our gross accounts receivable was $12,456,
and our allowance for doubtful accounts was $85.
So that's just summarizing from the prior slide.
We began with $12,456, and we had an allowance
for doubtful accounts of $85.
Now, what would happen if our write-offs
were much bigger than expected?
So imagine that our write offs were $185 million.
So we record that there.
What that means is we had a beginning allowance
for doubtful accounts of $85.
Now, we have to write off $185 million,
and we don't have enough in the balance of allowance
for doubtful accounts to take care of those write-offs.
So what we do then is have our accountants look
at our accounts receivable, figure out
how much our balance should be after the write-off.
Let's imagine they say the balance should be $100 million
after the write-off.
So after this write-off, we should
have a balance of $100 million, and then we
can back into or solve for the additional bad debt accrual.
So because we've underestimated it in the past, at this point,
we have to add an additional $200 million.
And that'll always keep our allowance
for doubtful accounts with a positive balance.