PROFESSOR: All right, as a quick aside--
and this is looking ahead to our class on income taxes.
Remember, the direct method that we just
illustrated a few minutes ago is required
for income tax returns.
For GAAP, you have to use either percentage of sales or aging
of accounts receivable.
So imagine that Dell uses percentage of sales
for its financial statements.
So think about it.
In general, will our bad debt expense under the direct method
equal our bad debt expense on our income statement?
So clearly not.
So as we've done in the examples above,
at any one point in time, our write-offs
can be more or less than our bad debt expense.
And this just shows you that there's
a different set of accounting for financial accounting
purposes and a different set of accounting for tax accounting
purposes.
So because of these differences, in general, how much we
expense for tax purposes is going
to be different than how much we expense for financial reporting
purposes.
And assuming the revenues are the same, our cash taxes--
our taxable income is going to be
greater or less than our financial reporting
income, which means that taxes paid are
going to be, in general, different than tax expense.
So when you're thinking, if I deduct
this expense for financial reporting purposes,
it's going to lower my taxes, that's, in general, not correct
because just because something's an expense
for financial reporting purposes does not mean it
is an expense for tax purposes.
And we'll come back to this.