PROFESSOR: Now for the BASE equation.
so BASE means Beginning plus Additions plus Subtractions
equals Ending Balances.
So every balance sheet account is
going to evolve using the same BASE equation.
So we've got a beginning balance.
So for example, right now it's the allowance
for doubtful account.
We add stuff to it.
So in our example here we're adding bad debt expense to it.
We subtract things from it, so our example here we're
subtracting write-offs from the allowance
for doubtful accounts.
That gives us our ending balance.
So the BASE equation beginning plus editions
minus subtractions equals ending balance,
we're going to keep using this throughout the course.
And in our example now that helps us
because the percentage of sales method
gives us bad debt expense, which is an addition,
and that allows us to compute the ending balance because we
know what write-offs are.
Alternatively in a minute we're going
to talk about the aging analysis, which will give us
the ending balance.
We still know what the subtractions are,
and then we can back into the amount of the additions, which
is bad debt expense.
Another way to see this is on this slide here
looking to the right on our contra
asset, which again is an asset account, which
is used to record reductions in the value of an asset.
So we're looking at allowance for doubtful accounts.
It has a beginning balance.
We add bad debt expense to that.
We subtract write-offs.
That gives us our ending balance.
At the time that we subtract those write offs
from the allowance for doubtful accounts,
we're going to reduce accounts receivable,
and accounts receivable evolves based on we
have a beginning balance.
We add some credit sales.
We collect cash on some of that.
We write some of it off, and then that
gives us our ending balance.
So this is the BASE equation for allowance for doubtful accounts
and for allows for accounts receivable.
And then companies give you information
in this BASE format.
So for example Dell keeps track of trade receivables, which
is the first panel in the slide here
and customer financing receivables, which is
the second panel of the slide.
And you can find this in the 10K in scheduled two.
And so again, notice, the words here.
Balance at the beginning of a period, that's
basically beginning allowance for doubtful accounts.
Provision charge to the income statement,
that's what we've been calling bad debt expense.
Bad debt write offs, we could call
that amount deemed uncollectable,
and then the balance at the end of the period is ending ADA.
Same thing with a customer financing receivables,
they've got different words but it essentially
is the same concept.
We begin with an allowance for doubtful accounts.
We add bad debt expense.
We reduce it by write offs, and then that
gives us an ending allowance for doubtful accounts.