PROFESSOR: Now let's do a little bit of financial statement
analysis, and I want to introduce a concept here called
accounts receivable turnover, which
is defined as how much revenue we
have divided by average accounts receivable net.
So this ratio of measures how quickly we
collect cash on credit sales.
So if we have lots of credit revenue but low receivables,
we'll collect cash quickly.
So on this accounts receivable turnover,
we want a bigger number.
That means that we are collecting faster.
That means that we don't have so much capital tied up
in accounts receivable.
I think a more intuitive way to do
it is just do the inverse of accounts receivable.
So divide accounts receivable turnover into one.
Multiply it by day's receivable--
multiply it by 365.
That gives us days receivable.
All we've done is invert accounts receivable turnover
calculation, but this gives us an intuition
of how many days of sales it takes us to collect payment
after a sale.
So here a smaller number is better
because it indicates faster collections.
Now looking back at our friends Bausch and Lomb.
In this chart, the first line is the year.
So we're looking at 1990 to 1993.
Remember, 1993 was the year of the fraud.
We look at their net sales over that four year period.
We look at their net accounts receivable
over that four year period.
We average the accounts receivable.
So for example, in '91 I'm taking the average of 203
and 205 to get average net accounts receivable of 204.
And then having calculated average net accounts
receivable, I can compute accounts receivable turnover as
shown in the fifth row there.
And then we can infer that and multiply it by 365
and come up with days receivable.
So this is not a red flag, but what you see going on
there is accounts receivable turnover is about 7
in '91 and '91, and then it slows way down
and goes below 6 in '93.
Or similar intuition, days receivable is about 50
in '91 and '92, and then it shoots up to 65 in '93.
So this is telling you that the company is doing something
different with its accounts receivable,
and it may bare use for you as an analysis
to look into this more deeply just with some simple accounts
receivable turnover numbers.