PROFESSOR: | we just talked about the allowance
for doubtful accounts or the allowance for bad debt.
Now we want to talk about a second related thing, which
is the allowance for returns.
So when you buy something from Amazon, as I'm sure many of you
have, many of you also return some of that stuff to Amazon,
and the correct accounting for that is we
don't record revenues on everything that we sell.
We record revenues on stuff that we
sell less some kind of expectation
for how much returns we're going to get.
So the liability for return allowances
is analogous to the allowance for doubtful accounts.
The only thing that's different here
is that we've taken the contra-asset, which
is a negative asset, and moved it over and made
it a liability.
But we do the accounting for this on the liability side.
And when the return happens, because we've
allowed for the return ahead of time
when the return actually happens it's not
going to reduce revenues and it's not
going to reduce net income.
So returning to Shrek and Dreamworks, remember,
let's suppose that Dreamworks ships 100 million
of Shrek DVDS in November of 2004.
And the time it ships them, it expects 50% of them
to be returned.
For this example, we're just going
to ignore cost of goods sold.
So our accounting is going to be, we ship out $100 million
worth of stuff.
So we get accounts receivable of $100 million.
We got revenue of $100 million, but we're
going to recognize this liability
for returns of $50 million.
And we're going to reduce revenue by $50 million.
So we shipped out $100 million worth of stuff,
but we expect to get 50 million of it back.
So we've really only gotten 50 million worth of revenue.
And then in December, some of these DVDS are returned.
So 30 million of them are returned.
Accounts receivable is going to go down by $30 million
at that time.
Allowance or returns are going to go down by $30 million.
So if we ship no more DVDS in 2004,
our revenues are going to be $50 million,
which is the 50 million worth of revenue
minus the allowance for returns of $50 million.
Our accounts receivable will be $70 million.
So $100 million in gross accounts receivable
minus the accounts receivable that were returned for us
and then our net liability for return allowances at the end
of 2004 is $20 million.
And so that's a stylized example.
So notice the difference here with the bad debt expense
is the allowance for returns reduces revenue,
whereas bad debt expense increases expense.
But both of them have the same effect on net income.
So that's a stylized example of the liability return analysis.
Now let's look at Amazon's note on return allowances to get us
a sense for what this looks like in the real world, OK.
So Amazon has a liability for return allowances, which
reduce revenue and cost of sales or cost of goods sold,
and they estimate that using historical experience.
So based on Amazon in historical experience
when they ship a billion worth of stuff out,
they expect to get like 10 million of it back.
So the balance of their liabilities or return
allowances in the second line there, they
include that in accrued expenses and others
so as a current liability.
So this is how much their liabilities for the return
allowances are in 2018, $623 million.
Then they tell you how much they added
to the allowance along with sales,
and they tell you how much they had just
deducted from the allowance when things were sent back to them.
Now what we didn't have in the Shrek example
a minute ago was when Amazon gets
something returned so if you buy a DVD from Amazon
and then return it to Amazon, Amazon
gets that DVD back and at least in theory
puts it back into inventory.
So what Amazon is telling you in the final couple of lines
there is that included in inventories
are goods that they expect to be returned.
So they've actually shipped these goods out,
but because they expect them to be returned
they keep those in inventory.
So Amazon's inventories includes items
that Amazon owns right now and also items that Amazon expects
their customers to return.