PROFESSOR: In this lecture, we explore relation of options.
Option relation is one of the central topics in this course
and in the modern theory of finance.
One reason for that is the tremendous economic importance
of the options market.
Options are highly versatile financial instruments.
Well-developed options markets help market participants
implement sophisticated trading strategies for both risk
management and speculation.
Another important reason for our focus on options
is that many financial instruments
and financial decision problems include embedded options.
To handle such problems, we need to develop methods
for option valuation and risk management.
Just like futures and forwards, some options trade on exchanges
and follow common standards and some trade over the counter
and have more variety.
We begin our discussion with the most common types
of options, so-called plain vanilla options,
which trade both on exchanges and over-the-counter.
Later in the class, we will consider
more complex types of options.
The most common and the simplest types of options
are calls and puts.
The call option gives its owner the right
to buy the underlying asset at the given
price on or before the expiration date.
We call the purchase price the strike price.
The put option gives its holder the right
to sell the underlying asset at the strike price
on or before the expiration date.
We distinguish two types of options
based on their exercise rules.
European options allow their owner
to exercise the option only on the expiration date.
The holder of an American option can
exercise at any time on or prior to the expiration date.
To summarize, the key elements in defining an option
are the underlying asset and its price;
the exercise price of the option or what we call the strike
price; the expiration date, also called the maturity date;
and the option type, European or American.