We now establish an important result,
known as the Put-call parity for European options.
This result is based on the straightforward arbitrage
argument and is a highly robust relation between option prices
in the data.
We maintain the assumption that the underlying asset,
the stock, does not pay dividends.
Consider two portfolios.
Portfolio 1 includes a call and the bond with a par value
equal to the strike.
Portfolio 2 includes a put option
with the same strike as the call and one share of the stock.
Compare the payoffs of the two portfolios at maturity.
These are identical.
The Law of One Price implies that the initial value
of the two portfolios must be the same.
This relation is known as the put-call parity.
It connects prices of the European put
and call options with the same strike price.