PROFESSOR: Let's first look at bonds at a discount.
Here, coupon rate is lower than the market rate.
Suppose the face value of the discount bond is $10,000.
Coupon rate is 6%, and market rate is 8%.
Maturity is 3 years.
Looking at the actual cash flow at the present value
of each cash flow, in years 1 and 2,
the cash outflow is $600, reflecting the coupon rate.
And in year 3, cash outflow is $10,600,
because the firm needs to pay back the principal.
It's the sum of year 3's interest payment
and the principal amount due at maturity.
In order to account for the schedule of payments,
we need to first calculate the present value of the bonds
each year.
To calculate the present value, the cash flows
can be seen as $600 annually for three years at 8% market
rate for the coupon payments and $10,000 single sum in three
years at a market rate, for the principal repayment.
To calculate the present value, we
can refer to the present value tables.
For the coupon payments, or the annuity,
we multiply $600 by 2.577, which is the present value
multiplier for 8% interest with a maturity of 3 years,
and obtain a present value of $1,546.
For the lump sum payment at year 3, we multiply 0.794 by $10,000
and obtain a present value of $7,938.
Adding these to, annuity and single sum, the total NPV
of cash flows is $9,484.
Now on to the balance sheet equation.
First, at the time of issuance, the present value
of the bond, $9,484, is added as cash.
Bond payable increases by $10,000, which
is the phase value of the bond.
Simultaneously, to balance the equation out,
a cash liability account, which is called a bond discount,
decreases by $516.
So the net bond payable at this point
is the present value of the bond, $9,484,
and the discount balance is $516.
In year one cash decreases by $600
because interest is paid by the coupon rate.
But one thing that's tricky here is that the interest expense
is not simply $600.
Rather, it is the previous year's bond payable
times the market rate.
In this case, interest expense is the net bond
payable for year 0, $9,484, times 8%, which equals $759.
Therefore, retained earnings decreased by $759.
To balance the equation out, bond discount
decreases by the remaining amount, $159.
Now the net bond payable is last year's net bond payable
plus the decrease bond discount amount, which
is $9,484 plus $159, $9,643.
Interest payments four years two and three
proceed using the same method.
In year two, interest expense is $9,643 times 8%, so $771.
In year three, interest expense is $786.
At maturity date, three years after the bond issuance,
the net bond payable, should be $10,000.
Finally, accounting for the principal repayment at maturity
a simple.
Cash decreases by $10,000, the face value,
and bond payable decreases by $10,000.
Now let's take a look at bonds at premium.
Again, the face value is $10,000,
and maturity is 3 years.
But this time, the coupon rate is 8%,
and the market rate is 6%.
Using the same present value calculation method,
the present value at the time of issuance is $10,535.
Accounting for premium bonds is similar to accounting
for discount bonds.
At issuance, cash increases by the present value
of the bond, $10,535.
Bond payable increases by the face value amount, $10,000.
Instead of bond discount, bond premium account,
which is liabilities, increases by the difference
between cash received and the face value of the bond.
Net bond payable is now $10,535, and the premium balance
is $535.
In year 1, cash decreases by $800,
due to the interest payment.
Again, interest expense decreases
by the net bond payable amount in the last year
times the market rate, which is $632 in this case.
Bond premium decreases by the difference between cash
and the interest expense.
Years 2 and 3 followed the same routine.
Finally, at the end of maturity, cash decreases by $10,000,
and bond payable also decreases by $10,000,
once the firm repays the principal.
Another possible scenario to look for
is when firms retire debt earlier than its maturity.
When firms retire debt early, the market value of debt
can be different from the book value, due to the firm's
economic conditions, which determines the credit quality,
and due to macroeconomic conditions, which determines
the market interest rates.
A rule of thumb to remember what is actually
when market value is higher than the book
value, early retirement results in a loss, and in a gain
when market value is lower than the book value.
Let's go over an example.
Suppose we have a zero coupon bond
on our books with the following balances,
bond payable of $11,500 and bond discount of $1,500.
So the net book value is $10,000.
Now let's say we repurchased the bond
at the market value of $8,500.
The market rate increased.
So the value of that decreased, essentially.
To account for this, let's first look at cash.
Cash decreased by $8,500, because we repurchased the bond
at that amount.
Since we retired the entire amount of debt,
payable decreases by $11,500, and bond discount
is also decreased by $1,500.
To balance the equation how, we record an increase of $1,500 in
retained earnings as a gain.