PROFESSOR: Question 2 uses the footnotes from Dollar General.
Part A-- using the BSE, show the transaction
for dollar general's issuance of 11.875%
senior subordinated notes here after senior subordinated notes
in 2007.
For this question, ignore the issuance of the senior notes
and only focus on the senior subordinated notes.
Refer to the footnotes below.
On July 6, 2007, Dollar General issued $725 million face value
bonds, with a maturity of 10 years.
It received proceeds of $718 million
after deducting issuance costs of $7 million.
To reflect this on the balance sheet equation,
cash increases by $718 million.
Deferred insurance costs increases by $7 million,
and bonds payable increases by $725 million.
Part B-- use the balance sheet equation
to identify the transactions Dollar General records
to reflect the issuance of the zero coupon bond.
The face value of this bond is $800,000,
and this bond is a zero coupon bond
with the maturity of 20 years and a 6% interest rate.
After discounting the 20 years, the present value
of the $800,000 bond is $249,444.
Thus cash increases by $249,444.
Bonds payable increases by $100,000.
And bond discount, which is a contra liability account,
increases by $550,556, which is the difference
between the bonds payable and cash increased.
Part C-- use the balance sheet equation
to record the annual amortization related
to the zero coupon bond issued in question 2b
for the fiscal year ending February 3, 2012 and 2013.
Recall that the net bond payable at issuance is to $49,444.
To obtain the amortization, or the decrease in bond discount,
you take the net bond payable from last year
and multiply that by the interest
rate, which is to $49,444 times 6%, which equals $14,967.
In 2012, therefore, bond discount increases by $14,967,
and retained earnings also decrease by the same amount,
as interest expense.
Similarly, for year 2013, the interest expense
is net bond payable of $249,444 plus $14,967 times 6%, which
is $15,860.
Bond discount and shareholders' equity
both decrease by $15,864.