PROFESSOR: Question 1-- referred to the following footnotes
for Transocean Limited on debt.
Part A-- as of December 31, 2010,
has Transocean redeemed any of the 7.45% nodes?
If yes, how much?
The answer is no, since the principal amount on December
31, 2010 is same as the issuing amount, which is $100 billion.
You can find this in the second paragraph of the Footnotes
section.
Part B-- as of December 31, 2010,
how much is the discount on the 7.45% nodes?
Is the yearly amortization of the discount
likely to be a material amount?
Hint, note 11 reports annual debt totals,
net of unamortized discounts.
The discount on the 7.45% nodes is $4 million,
which is $100 million of principal minus $96 million
on the net balance.
You can find in this section of the footnotes.
The yearly amortization is unlikely to be material.
The rounded value of the net obligation
didn't change, indicating that the change was less than $1
million.
Part C-- were the 7.375% 10 year notes issued at a premium,
at a discount, or at par?
They were issued at a premium.
The balance of the loan, including
the unamortized premium, is $247 million,
which is greater than the principal amount, which
is to $246 million.
The second row of the table in the footnotes
shows the amount of the balance of the loan.
And the second paragraph indicates
$247 million principle amount.