PROFESSOR: Question 3, capitalizing
off balance sheet items--
refer to Zoltan Corp's off balance sheet obligations.
For this question, assumes 0% tax rate.
Describe how Zoltan's assets and liabilities on December 31,
2011 would change if off balance sheet
obligations are capitalized.
Use the BSE to record this transaction.
For this question, assume that the discount rate is 6%,
and assume that Zoltan pays the payments
at the end of the fiscal year.
Also, assume that Zoltan makes equal payments over a nine year
period.
Off balance sheet obligations are $600,000 per year,
and we use discount rate of 6%.
As you can see in the table on the right,
after summing up the discount values,
the present value of the off balance sheet
is approximately $4.081 million.
The easy way to calculate this is to use the annuity table.
To do the balance sheet equation,
we increase assets by $4.081 million
and liabilities by the same amount.