INSTRUCTOR: The concept of risk-neutral probabilities
is closely related to the concept of state prices.
Consider a primitive state contingent claim.
It's basically a digital option.
It pays off $1.00 only in a given future state and nothing
otherwise.
For example, a digital option that pays $1.00 at time 2 only
if the price of the stock goes up in both periods defines
a state contingent claim on the highest node of the tree
at time 2.
Denote the price of our digital option by phi.
This is the state price of the highest
state on the tree at time 2 or the Arrow-Debreu state price.
We can define state prices for all other states
in a similar manner.
Each state price is simply the market price of a financial
claim paying $1.00 only in a particular future state
and nothing otherwise.
Using the risk-neutral probabilities,
we know how to compute the market prices of such state
contingent claims.
Their prices are given by the expectation of the payoff
and the q probabilities discounted
at the risk-free interest rate.
Note that the payoff of a primitive state contingent
claim is concentrated in a single state.
Then the risk-neutral expected value of the payoff
is equal to the q probability of the corresponding state.
We have derived a relation between state price
and the risk-neutral probability.
State prices are proportional to the risk-neutral probabilities.
In addition to the later, they also
reflect the time value of money, or the risk-free rate.
Once we know the state prices, we
can value any state contingent payoff
as a portfolio of state contingent claims.
This is mathematical equivalent to the risk-neutral valuation
formula.