PROFESSOR: In this segment, we'll
go into the details of the argument we discussed
during the recent webinar.
This is an idea due to Fischer Black, who
suggested that if some investors in the market
prefer high beta stocks to low beta stocks,
this results in a violation of the CAPM,
where the security market line is relatively flat.
Firms can take advantage of this violation
and increase their market value by levering up.
The result is that even though the CAPM fails
to hold in the capital market, it
is still very useful for corporate financial decisions.
This argument provides an interesting connection
between the CAPM and the M&M theorem
that we discussed later in the course.
Eventually this brought us back to the APT.
And for full details, I will refer you to the webinar video.