PROFESSOR: The focus this week is
on the pricing of options on fixed income securities
and interest rates.
As in week three, when we discussed forward
future and swap contracts related to the fixed income
market, the fundamental driver of risk
is the volatility of interest rates.
I encourage you to review the week three material together
with what's covered in the lecture today
to see the connections and develop
a more complete understanding of fixed income derivatives.
The pricing models we'll look at fall
into two broad categories--
models of stochastic bond prices and models
of stochastic interest rates.
The first category falls under the heading of Black-Scholes
Merton style models.
We'll see why the BSM model doesn't work well
for pricing bond options and discuss why Black's model is
sometimes used instead.
Most options pricing models in the fixed income world
actually start with models of stochastic short-term interest
rates, and those will be our main focus.
The models are used to infer stochastic bond
prices, stochastic yield curves, and the value
of associated options and other derivatives.
We'll start with binomial models of short-term rates, which
are a very versatile tool for valuation
and especially practical for American-style options.
Then we'll briefly turn to continuous time interest rate
models and how they're implemented to price options.