JOHN CORE: This is our first class.
What we're going to do in this class
is briefly introduce the course, and then
introduce accrual accounting.
My name is John Core.
I'm a professor at MIT Sloan School of Management.
In terms of our course objectives,
we're training you to be leaders.
We want you to understand accounting at a big picture
level, and this will help you reach your career
goals, either as a finance professional, or more broadly,
as an executive as you move out of the finance arena.
We want you to understand the big picture of how accounting
information is prepared.
We're not training you how to prepare accounting information,
we want you to have that big picture knowledge
so that you can make informed decisions using accounting
information.
And in order to do that, we're going
to introduce you to some of the rules, some of the language,
and some of the techniques.
We're going to try to help you recognize when managers using
accounting are using judgment, and then finally,
and most importantly, we're going
to help you apply accounting insights to real world
situations, again, as you would as a finance professional, more
generally as a business professional.
Briefly, MIT Sloan School's mission,
and when you come to MIT, when you come to the Sloan School,
you'll see this mission statement chiseled
in the wall of our main building.
Our mission is to develop principled, innovative leaders
who improve the world.
Many times in this course, we're going
to discuss examples in which firms or people are
manipulating accounting numbers.
The purpose of these examples is to help
you understand the role of judgment in accounting systems,
and that accounting systems give people leeway in which they can
manipulate numbers inappropriately,
or they can use that leeway to make better communication
decisions.
None of this, however, is to suggest
that the example behavior that we're looking at
is appropriate.
So please remember this as we go through the class.