JOHN CORE: Now we're going to do an introductory case
on Dreamworks.
It made a movie called Shrek 2, and then made a DVD about it.
Dreamworks is special because it only makes two movies a year.
So the revenues from this movie are
a big part of Dreamworks' operations for the year.
Notice the green guy, this is the DVD box,
that's Shrek 2, if you don't know who he is.
We're going to look at the economic consequences
of accounting through the Shrek 2 case.
This is based on a Wall Street Journal article
from May 31, 2005.
The Shrek 2 DVD, says the reporter,
made a killing over the 2004/2005 holiday season.
Here's a timeline below.
So you see, over the holiday season,
so from Thanksgiving to early January,
Shrek 2 made a killing.
Second case fact is at the beginning of 2005,
Jeff Katzenberg, who is the Dreamworks CEO,
was bragging a lot about all the records
that Shrek 2 had set in the DVD market,
or broken in the DVD market.
So there's our timeline again.
In early January, they put out the statement bragging
about their records.
But as the first quarter ended, so Dreamworks,
like many American companies, has a fiscal year
that ends on December 31.
That means its first quarter ends on March 31,
and as this first quarter was ending,
Dreamworks started seeing retailers
returning millions of copies of the unsold copies of the DVD.
So notice that this means that they're not
going to be selling these, because they're coming back
to them.
And then finally, on May 10, 2005,
Dreamworks issued its earnings announcement, and at that time,
it dropped a bombshell because its earnings fell short
of earnings forecast by 25%.
So you see again in the timeline,
we made a killing back in late December,
we bragged about it in January, we saw the DVDs
coming back to us in late March, and it wasn't until May
when we made our earnings announcement
that we told our stockholders exactly what was going on.