PROFESSOR: So this obviously, again,
has been done in PowerPoint.
A better way to do these transactions
is on an Excel spreadsheet.
So you can imagine what we're going
to do now is add all these columns down.
And you see that line there called
EB, which is Ending Balance.
So when we add all these columns down,
what are we going to have?
We're going to have our balance sheet as
of the end of year one.
So let's add all the columns down.
And then, if you're like me, you want
to check that these columns actually add up to each other.
So that Total Assets in the Assets column is 46.
Liabilities is 20.
Stockholders' equity is 26.
Often, when you're doing this, you can make small mistakes,
and this is the double entry feature of the accounting
system is that when you form your balance sheet,
you will discover whether or not you have
any small mistakes in there.
And then you can look up above and correct them.
So just arranging this information now.
So EB, again, is our Ending Balance sheet.
And then, arranging this information,
this is the way that US companies
present their balance sheet, which
is Cash, which is the most liquid asset,
goes at the top-left.
Then you've got Accounts Receivable, less liquid assets.
In terms of liabilities, Accounts Payable,
which is your most liquid liabilities,
goes up at the top.
You compute Total Liabilities, compute Stockholders' Equity.
Now, other countries-- and this is just a convention--
they sometimes will put the least liquid asset up on top.
So in this example, another country
might put Inventory on top and then
sort of cascade it down to Cash.
But clearly, the presentation is just a point of emphasis,
but it doesn't change any of the substance.
Having done Peter's company and having created a balance sheet,
now we're going to create the income statement and the cash
flow statement.