PROFESSOR: Now here is an integral formula
that tells us how to use the special function
p0 to get a general solution to the differential equation that
satisfies arbitrary initial conditions.
So imagine that at time t equals 0, we want our function p of z
and t that satisfies the diffusion
equation to have some particular functional form f of z.
It could be something like f of z equals z squared.
It could be a cosine.
So you pick a function f of z, and the question
is, can we find a time dependent function that
satisfies the diffusion equation such that when t is equal to 0,
it takes the particular form that we want.
If we can do that, getting the solution
to the Black-Scholes equation is going to be a piece of cake.
And here's how it works.
We put in our function p0 where we take
a difference of the variable.
That is, we're going to have an integration variable.
We're going to integrate over all possible z
primes of our special function for our initial conditions
f of z prime.
And then we're going to multiply that against a kernel function
against what's known as a Green's function
our special p0 where we're substituting
for z the difference between z and z
prime where z is the outside variable
and z prime is the variable of integration.
So if we were to differentiate this with respect to z,
the only z appears here, and it's not integrated over.
So we can bring a derivative inside the equation.
Similarly, if we want to integrate with respect to time,
this integral is not over time.
z prime is a dummy variable for integration.
If we want to differentiate this with respect to time,
this is the only place where time appears.
So let's take a look at a couple examples,
and you can check that this actually works.
If we substitute in our particular expression for p0,
here's our rule.
We've got 1 over square root of 2 pi t, which
I put in front because it doesn't depend
on z prime, exponential of minus z minus z
prime quantity squared over 2t times f of z prime dz prime.