PROFESSOR: Here's a warm-up exercise.
For each of these sets of equations,
how many solutions are there?
I don't care what they are.
I just want you to find out how many there are.
Now, this is a typical problem in linear algebra,
and it has a close connection to what we looked at in lectures
this week in asset pricing, where we're
looking at market structure.
And we ask, are markets complete?
How many different kinds of coverage
can we get to describe risks that
might happen in different possible states of the world,
to describe rewards and payoffs that
might happen in different states of the world?
We want to know, is it possible to cover everything?
And if it is possible to cover everything,
is our a solution unique?
If it's not possible to cover everything, what's missing?
What are the constraints?
What can we do?
If there are additional things that we
could do to complete a market, are those completions unique?
And we invert solutions.
We're given an answer.
We go back to the original problem.
These are all things that you've actually
seen in other guises for a long time,
solving equations as simple as this.
But what I'm going to do is go through the basics
of linear algebra as a review.
And I hope you've seen the lectures,
but if you're coming here first for linear algebra review,
you go back to the lectures, come back here again--
either way you do it, I hope you make
the connection between the two.
And certainly, feel free to skip parts, or speed it up
to 1 and 1/2 or twice speed if it helps it go by faster.
Vectors are elements in something called a vector
space.
And the key idea is not that they're columns of numbers.
The key idea is that they're objects
that can be added to get other objects of the same type.
And of course, we've been dealing
with that throughout the entire course,
not as columns of numbers, but we've
been looking at functions, where we add two functions,
for example, and we get another function.
If it obeys rules of addition and scalar multiplication,
and it's closed under those operations,
then we can think about this as a vector space.
There are properties of vector addition.
And this is not just for little arrows pointing in the plane.
This is true for any mathematical objects
that obey these properties.
We can call it a vector space.
It's commutative.
V plus w is the same thing as w plus v. It's associative.
You can do the addition in any order you'd like.
It has an identity, in this case, an additive identity
that we call 0.
And importantly, it has an additive inverse
that we can have a negative, and we can go the other way.
Now, one of the things that we saw in our example
during the lecture is that we can represent portfolio space
as being a set of vectors.
But do they form a vector space?
One of the requirements is that there be, for example, a 0.
Is there?
Well, yeah.
You could have an empty portfolio.
You would add it to a portfolio, you would get nothing.
What about v plus w and w plus v?
Sure.
If you've got 100 shares of Coca-Cola stock
and 100 shares of Caterpillar, it
doesn't matter which way you add them.
They add up either way.
You can commute.
What about the additive inverse?
That's a bit tricky.
How do we have the opposite of a portfolio?
Well, the way we usually think about it is a simple answer.
And this is approximation to reality,
but definitely not the way real-world trading
exactly works.
We can think about short positions in a security
as being like owning a negative quantity of that security.
That says that if we have short positions,
we think that a short portfolio is identified
with a long portfolio because the long portfolio are
the stocks you would need to buy to cover a short position.
A short position, just as a reminder,
is when you borrow stock and you sell it,
but you have an obligation to replace the stock to the owner.
So there's a natural fit.
We can pick it out the additive inverse and the vector
as saying, what's the vector we need to add to get back to 0?
In the case of a financial portfolio of securities,
say that it is held short, we could
say, what's the portfolio that we would need to cover
a set of short positions?
That would be a minus of a minus v. That
would be v. We could say, what are the trades that we
need to do in order to liquidate a portfolio?
That might be a signed portfolio with negative signs
for responding to required sales.
And that would say that, if we have a portfolio,
the additive inverse is the portfolio
that you would need to sell.
You would need to take a negative relative position
in order to get to 0.
Those all have correspondences.
That's what we saw for portfolios in portfolio space
during the lecture this week.
Now, the scalars form a field--
and here, we use real numbers, not complex numbers.
And why is that important?
Well, first of all, there are properties that we have.
The a times b, we can associate it either way,
so we can multiply by a scalar--
with two scalars first or the vector first.
We have a distributive law for either multiplication
by scalars or multiplication--
so a scalar times a sum of vectors or a sum
of scalars times the vector.
Either way, we have these simple laws.
And there's a scalar identity, as well, which is the number 1.
So that's fine.
But where we run into an issue is that,
if we're thinking about portfolio space--
and there are lots of other vector spaces
that we use in finance.
But if we think specifically of a portfolio space,
and we think about our typical example of a set of stocks,
stocks can only be held in integer quantities.
And that doesn't form a field.
There are lots of these buzzwords that are here.
And we'll get to touch on some of them,
but certainly not all of them.
Let's look at some notions from linear algebra,
like linear dependence, basis, dimension,
different kinds of linear accommodation,
and have a direct application of what
we saw in the structure of financial markets.
A linear combination of vectors is
a sum of the vectors where we can multiply each vector
by an arbitrary scalar.
We saw an example of that in building a portfolio.
If you have a portfolio with 100 shares of stock a
and 200 shares of stock b, that's
the same as a single portfolio with components, say,
100 and 200.
Or it could be 100 times a portfolio with a single share
of stock plus 200 times the portfolio
with a single share of stock b.
So we can multiply things by constants.
We can add them together.
And that's a linear combination.
And that's an action that we can take on portfolios.
Very natural.
Now, a set of vectors is said to be linearly dependent if there
are a set of non-zero constants so that we
can write an equation like this where
we can set this equal to 0.
And of course, what that really means
is that we can solve for one of the vectors
in terms of the other vectors in the set.
That's what we mean by a redundant security.
We mean that its payoff could be reproduced by some combination
of other securities.
Simple example in the introduction I think I gave
was a trivial example, not even with column vectors
in a high-dimensional space.
If you have a $5 bill, a $10 bill, and a of $20 bills,
you can trade them off for one another.
You can replicate the payoff of one with the others.
However, we do need to be careful about the divisibility.
Assuming that we have constants, we
can show, though, that there are relationships.
For example, we could say that 4 $5 bills minus
& $20 bill is equal to 0.
And that would show that those are--
that's sufficient to show that those are linearly dependent.
And it's a pretty obvious notion.
This is the formal notion.
And then, if we can't do that, we
say that the vectors are linearly independent.
And this is really important.
It means that they describe different kinds of things.
An example in our portfolios would
be, in terms of our basic portfolio space,
if we have two different stocks--
they describe different things, that they describe
completely different payoffs--
they are independent of each other.
Linear dependence means that we can write one of the vectors
in terms of the others.
And in the case of our payoff matrix,
that means that we can write the payoff of one kind of security
in terms of another set of securities.
And that means that we could build a portfolio that
has exactly the same payoff.
And that means, in a certain sense,
you don't really need the first one.
Now, we might have it for lots of reasons, in the same way
that the existence of $1 bills doesn't mean that we
don't find $50 and $100 bills.
Of course we do.
They're there for lots of different reasons.
And the same thing is true in financial markets.
In fact, when it comes to derivative pricing,
there's an entire, enormous market of securities
that arguably are all redundant.
And yet there's an enormous demand for them,
and enormous trading activity, and they
perform very important functions in the economy.
When it comes just back to independence,
we have a very simple question, though, which is not,
how useful is it?
It's just, can you do this?
Can you write this equation?
And if you can, great.
Now, it says we really have one less degree of freedom.
In this example, it says v1 can be expressed
in terms of the others.
Now, there is a technical point here to make,
which is that we're dividing by a1,
and we do need to make sure that actually
leads to closure within our chosen field of scalars.
And if they're integers, the answer is actually no.
You can find a lot of things where this is not necessarily
going to work for different financial securities.
But it turns out that, in usual quantities that are done,
this tends to be pretty small.
And this is actually a good approximation,
but you do have to check.
Because either things are linearly independent
or they're not.
You can't be a little bit dependent.
From a mathematical point of view, there's a bright line.
From an applications point of view,
it requires judgment of the modeler.
And that's you.
That's why this is a course in mathematical methods
that are used.
We're going through the mathematical rules.
But how they get applied will depend.
Because in most real-world financial settings,
the assumptions the pure mathematics
are almost never satisfied, which means,
technically, we can't use any of the results.
And you'll need to use your judgment
to see when it might nevertheless be OK to do so.
There's an infinite number of factors
we can multiply by all of these constants,
but does that really mean that everything is infinite?
No, it doesn't.
If we start with a finite set of vectors,
we can use them to generate a vector
space just by taking all possible linear combinations
of them.
Then it's pretty clear that, even though we
could multiply times an infinite number of scalars
and get an infinite number of vectors,
everything is generated by a finite set.
We say that set spans the vector space.
And we call the vector-- we can say
that the vector space is the span of this set of vectors.
So it's true, by construction, that it's
closed under addition and scalar multiplication.
Now if, in addition to spanning the vector space,
the vectors are linearly independent,
then we say they form a basis for V. The basis isn't unique,
but it does mean it's the smallest number of vectors
that we have to have in order to describe everything
in the vector space.
And we call that number the dimension of the vector space.
Given a basis, we have a way to describe every vector
in the vector space.
It's a linear combination in terms of the basis vectors.
And this expression is unique.
And this leads us to our usual coordinate system.
Because we think of our column vectors
as being coordinates with respect to a basis.
If I have basis vectors u1, u2, u3,
and I take all possible linear combinations,
well I could write that-- so I have c1 times u1, c2 times u2,
and so on for any set of c's.
Our usual notation is we have these unit
vectors, these unit basis vectors,
1, 0, 0, 0, 0, 1, 0, 0, 0, and so on.
And we see that if we apply this rule,
we get our usual notation-- that we
get a column vector of numbers.
In the case of our classic payoff matrix,
we're looking at this in terms of columns,
we can think of the basis vectors as corresponding
to the arrow to our securities.
That is, they are the unit payoffs
in state 1 of the world, state 2 of the world,
state 3 of the world.
And we can take linear combinations.
If you want to end up with a vector that pays off 1, 2, 3,
it's 1 times the vector 1, 0, 0 plus twice
the vector 0, 1, 0, plus 3 times the vector 0, 0, 1.
So that gives us our usual notation.
Subspace of a vector space is a vector space
that's a subset of V. Now, that means
it has to be a vector space on its own.
And the span of a subset of basic factors of V
defines the subspace of V. If we take
a set of linearly independent vectors
that's smaller than the dimension of the space, then
we--
span is going to define a subspace.
We can always define something smaller.
You can think of a plane as a subspace
of three-dimensional space.
You can take a group of independent assets
less than everything and talk about what they span.
Because we're looking at everything generated
by a particular subset of basis vectors,
it has to be a vector space.
And we can take a look at the consequences.