PROFESSOR: Now, linear transformations are functions,
sometimes called mappings, that go from one vector space
to another.
And they can be completely different dimensions.
The key property is one we've been using since the beginning.
It's linearity.
And here it is.
So we've been doing linear transformations all along,
without calling them that.
So if I have a mapping which says that T takes me
from vector space V to vector space W,
then that means that something of the form T acting on V
is a vector in the space W. Linearity
means that when the operator acts on this sum,
it's the sum of the operator acting
on the individual elements.
And when we take the transformation acting
on scalar times our vector, we can bring the scalar out
in front.
It's a scalar times the operation acting on the vector.
So this simple property of linearity,
for example, that we've been using with expectations
is described by the actions on the vectors of the vector
space.
So if we know how it behaves on the basis vector,
by using linearity we know how it behaves on anything.
So consider a transformation acting on an arbitrary vector.
And we can express it as a linear combination.
So T is acting on V. V we could write
in terms of the basis vectors.
Applying linearity, we can write this
as the constants times T acting on each of the basis vectors.
And if we know how T acts on each basis vector,
then we know how it would act on any vector.
And we just recombine the results.
So in our payoff analogy, the payoff on a portfolio
is the sum of the payoffs of the individual securities.
And in fact, it doesn't matter how big your portfolio is.
The only thing we need to know are the individual payoffs.
And then we know how the payoff works
for anything more general.
And what this says is we really just
add up multiples of the columns that
correspond to the individual things
that we're interested in.
So that brings us to matrix notation.
If we combine these columns, we can form them
into something that looks like a matrix.
So we construct the columns to be the output
of T acting on something.
And I've written T as an abstract linear transformation.
And M is the matrix, a concrete set of numbers
that we can write down.
And that's important when we're thinking
about bases and change of basis from one to another,
and things more abstractly.
That's not going to be very important for what we're
doing now, so we can closely identify the matrix
with the transformation itself.
But they are two separate things.
It requires a particular bases to write down a matrix
with respect to that basis.
To change basis, your transformation
is the same transformation, but it gets a different matrix.
So the matrix M depends on the choice that we have.
And then when M acts on a column vector of the original space,
the result is going to be a linear combination
of the columns of M.
And we've seen this.
If we have a portfolio that consisted
of the stock and a bond, and we multiplied it by the matrix A,
what did we get?
We just got the sum of the first two columns,
which intuitively is what we'd expect.
It's the sum of the payoffs of the security--
individual securities.
So this does for us the rules of matrix multiplication
that might seem kind of weird when you first run into them.
They correspond to a very natural way
of adding up payoffs, adding up securities, and adding up
money.
So in component notation, if we write M acting on--
so I've got this complicated matrix M with elements mij.
I act on a column vector.
And the rules of matrix multiplication
tell me that I get a column--
excuse me, that I get a column vector over here, which
is of different dimension.
And we write-- in matrix notation,
we can write this with summation convention.
It would be sum over j of mij hold
at the i-th component of the result, which
is, say, the second one here, could be i.
We hold i fixed, and we sum over the second column,
which is everything that we have here for the matching j's.
So if we take i to be a particular number 1 through s,
where s is the number of rows that we have,
and we ask about the i-th one-- say, how do I get, for example,
the second row over here--
I get it by taking--
by holding the I fixed.
So that would be corresponding to this second row.
And I take each element of the second row times each element
of this vector.
You notice they have the same number,
and that's what gives me this formula here.
But really, the simple thing that's going on
is when we do matrix multiplication,
we're just taking linear combinations of the columns.
These rules simplify if we're in the case of two dimensions.
And in particular, if we have square matrices,
we can think of this as transformations in the plane.
We can look at what happens if we iterate transformations
on the same space.
More generally, we can define matrix multiplication
where I go from one vector space V to another space W
to yet another vector space.
And we get that the action of successive linear
transformations is itself a linear transformation.
The product of two matrices is itself a matrix.
And we have these rules that are complicated to write down.
But in principle, it's just telling us
that if we want to get from V to W to X,
we could go straight from V to X by looking at this combined
matrix.
Now, the important among the properties of matrix
multiplication are that they're associative,
they're distributive.
But famously, they are not commutative.
You can't change the order.
And in particular, not only if you get a number,
but if the vector spaces have different dimension,
this doesn't even make any sense.
In our example, we're really going to be looking typically
at two vector spaces--
one in the world of security markets, where we've
got a set of securities that we identify we
have a basis vector for each traded security,
and on the other hand we have state space
that has to do with states of the world,
possibly in the future, without regard
to what finance people are doing and constructing securities.
We're going from one to the other and then back.
But if we wanted to do multiple hops across multiple spaces,
this is the way in which we would do it.
And there are two very important spaces
that we're going to use extensively.
And these are subspaces of a linear transformation.
They're called the image and the kernel.
And so the image of a linear transformation
is the set of everything that you can
reach by acting on it with--
by acting with t on all of the possible vectors in the vector
space.
So in our example, we said, what are all the possible payoffs
we could generate with a given set of securities?
Can I get everything?
Do I get less than everything?
Whatever it is, the span of the image that we have
generates everything.
So what we say is, specifically, the image
are all the vectors W that are T acting on something
in our vector space.
So this would be the payoff of all possible portfolios,
because these V's are linear combinations of our basis
assets.
And this says that the image of a linear transformation
are all the payoffs that can possibly be generated.
So it could be the entire target space W.
But often, it's going to be less.
So this tells us what we can reach,
what's reachable with a linear transformation,
when it acts on everything in our original space.
The kernel of a linear transformation
is a subset not of the target space W,
it's a subset of our original space V.
And it's all the vectors that get mapped
into the zero vector.
And sometimes, we say that it's annihilated
by the linear transformation T.
So the kernel of a linear transformation
is the set of all vectors that are taken into 0.
This is going to be-- and this we've seen in lecture--
essential to defining one kind of arbitrage.
Because this would mean that the payoff on an--
obviously, this is a special case.
Zero always gets taken into zero.
But what does this mean in a financial context?
What's a concrete financial example?
It's an arbitrage portfolio, where
we have redundant securities.
That is, if I can construct a set of securities--
not just an empty portfolio, but actual securities,
long and short positions-- and if it
had zero payoff, that's an example of something that's
in the kernel.
It's a non-zero vector, it has zero payoff.
So one more concept that's very important
is the rank of a linear transformation.
And that's the dimension of the image.
And that tells us how many linearly independent columns
are in the matrix.
That's why we inspect our payoff matrices,
see how many columns are there.
we can know by inspection or by more sophisticated techniques,
how many columns are there that are linearly independent.
That tells us how many dimensions there
have to be in the target space.
So the rank of a linear transformation
is very important.
And we've seen the rank of the payoff matrix
is essential for telling us whether markets
are complete or incomplete, and in certain cases,
about the number of redundant securities
they may have to be present.
The fundamental theorem of linear transformations
is a rule about the dimensions of these important spaces.
It says that the dimension of our original space
is equal to the dimension of the image plus the dimension
of the kernel.
So what that says is the dimension of the image,
remember, is the number of independent securities
that we have that have payoffs that can't
be replicated from each other.
And the dimension of the kernel is
going to be the number of redundant assets that we have--
the number of assets that are left over that
aren't giving us genuinely new payoff.
The division between them is not unique,
but this fundamental theorem is an important rule,
and it holds no matter how we choose to divide things up.
It's really a property of the relationship between these two
spaces under the action of a particular linear
transformation.
Of course, there are some special cases.
So if the kernel's empty, if everything
gets taken into a new vector, then the rank
of the transformation is equal to the dimension of the space
V. And if V and W have the same dimension,
and we say the matrix is of full rank,
then the linear transformation is inevitable.
It's a one-to-one mapping from space V to space W.
Everything--
we can reach every point in W by some vector in V.
And from any point, we can always
find the vector V that got us there.
Now, it's easy to do operations with matrices on a computer.
For two-by-two matrices, you can and should
be able to do them in your head.
But for anything bigger than two by two,
you probably should use a computer,
because the rules for doing matrix multiplication
are very complicated, rules for doing things
like determinants which apply if you have square matrices
are even more complicated, and the rules
for doing inversions of matrices are even more complicated,
and the rules for solving for linear independence
of a bunch of sets if you have non-square matrices
are even more complicated than that.
So it's a good idea to try things out.
You can do this in R, which we've been using,
or you can pick a programming environment of your choice.
But we want to distinguish operations of linear algebra
from those that are commonly done in lots of computing
environments, including R, where the typical thing is
if you have two lists, two things that would look
like vectors, and if you multiply them together,
or two matrices, what it does by default
is it multiplies them pointwise.
And that's not even an operation of linear algebra in general.
So what we do is we need a different notation.
But that's OK.
And it's going to depend on the different languages.
So in R, A times B, instead of the star operator,
it's sandwiched between percent signs.
Very easy and obvious to remember.
Percent start percent, A times B,
that's the notation for matrix multiplication of A times B.
If you want the square, you can take, say, A times A.
But what you don't do is A times B that's not a matrix product.
That just takes A and B, If they're the same size, not even
if they're square, and multiplies
them element by element.
And things-- there are operations
we can define, like exponentials of matrices
if the matrices are square.
But most of the functions by default don't do that.
In this case in R, the exponential of the matrix
is going to be the matrix of the exponential
of the individual matrix element.
So in addition to that, you need to be aware
of a whole bunch of limitations, because they're in computers.
So it's easy to get nonsense coming out.
And what you have to do this you have
to check your answers to make sure they're OK.
Remember that we're dealing with real numbers computers.
Can't do real numbers.
They do discrete approximations.
So there can be rounding issues.
There could be issues of stability.
A determinant that's close to 0 is not the same as one
that is 0.
But for the computer, it might not be able to tell.
And we might have two vectors that are either linearly
dependent or they're not, they're parallel
or they're not, but the computer might not
be able to tell to within machine precision.
So you need to go back and forth between the computational tool
and checking that things actually work and make sense.
So here's an example of what we could do.
Suppose we have a linear system of equations.
So here's a system of equations like the one I wrote down
at the beginning-- three equations, three unknowns.
We can write this in matrix form.
Using the rules of matrix multiplication,
I can write this as M times v equal to b, where I define v
to be the vector x, y, z--
those are three coordinates.
I define b to be a constant.
This would be like our payoff vector is B.
So here it's 3, 6, 9.
And I have a bunch of coefficients in front
that are all the coefficients in these equations.
And by organizing them in this way--
1, 2, 3, show up here as 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6 get multiplied times x, y, z to give us this expression,
we can encapsulate this set of equations.
In this matrix notation.
How do we solve it?
Well, M times v equals b, we'd like
to write v as b divided by M. We can't quite do that.
We can't just divide by a matrix.
But we can do the next best thing if M is invertible.
We'd like to have something that we could
write as v is M inverse b.
Can we do it?
So we can define a matrix in R as saying a matrix,
here's the list of numbers.
We tell it that we want there to be three rows.
And it will organize things like this--
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
The command to invert a matrix in R
is called solve, because it thinks
we want to solve this system of linear equations.
And if we say solve, we get a problem.
Here is an error message--
computationally singular reciprocal condition
10 to the minus 18, which sounds awfully close to 0.
And the problem is that's the number we get--
something of that order-- if we look at the determinant.
The determinant is actually really close to 0.
And the reason for it should be pretty obvious now
if we take a look at it.
The determinant is 0, that would arise if the rows or columns
were linearly dependent.
Notice that the middle column is the average of the first
and the third column.
So this column plus this column add up
to twice the middle column.
That means the determinant is 0.
That means that an inverse doesn't exist.
Suppose I tweak it.
And suppose I change this number from a 9 to a 10.
Now, actually, we're golden.
So now we have something that is invertible.
All three columns are independent.
And we can invert it.
So what we'd like to do is find the v such
that when we act with M on the left, we get this vector.
If we do that in R, I've got M defined here,
I have b defined here.
The determinant is minus 3.
That's safely away from 0.
And if I define M inverse to be the inverse matrix,
I get a bunch of numbers.
And you might suspect that these could
be done as fractions, not as decimals,
and you would be right.
And then we can take M inverse multiplied times b,
and we get this vector here, which
looks like minus 1, 2, 1.776 times 10 to the minus 15.
Hmm.
Looks to me kind of like minus 1, 2, 0.
And if we check, we find out, actually,
that that's also the equation.
You can see that here, because minus 1, 2, 0,
it says take twice the second column
and subtract the first column.
So 4 minus 1 is 3.
10 minus 4 is 6.
And 16 minus 7 gives us 9.
So we're good.