PROFESSOR: So let's look systematically
at systems of linear equations and see
how we can classify them.
And what you'll see is that this matches closely
with the kind of classification we
looked at in the structure of financial markets.
Are they complete?
Or are they incomplete?
What's the rank of the payoff matrix?
Are there unique solutions?
Are there redundant securities?
So in general, there are different kinds
of systems of linear equations.
And we have cases where we have either homogeneous
or inhomogeneous equations.
So in the first case, we have an inhomogeneous equation
of the form that we looked at when
we tried to solve a matrix times a vector equals
a fixed constant, b.
And the question to solve is, can we find a solution v such
that when acted on by M, we get the particular target--
actually, the payoff vector-- b.
Now, there's special case when b is equal to 0.
We have what's called a homogeneous equation,
because every term in it has a v. 0 is
0 times v. And in this case, we're asking,
is v in the kernel?
And the reason that that's important
is that if we have a solution to the second equation,
and acting on b is equal to 0, then
we can add any multiple of that to the solution
in the first equation, and get another equation.
So in general, we've got s equations wit n unknowns,
and we want to know when we have a solution.
And roughly what we expect to find
is that it depends on whether we have
the same number of equations as unknowns,
whether we have more unknowns, or whether we have fewer.
So what we'd roughly expect it that if s and n are equal,
if we have as many equations as unknowns,
that there should be a unique solution.
And if we've got more equations than we do variables,
then we're not going to find any solutions at all.
Or generally, that system would be overdetermined
and overconstrained.
And if we have fewer equations than variables,
we'd expect there to be infinitely many solutions.
So that intuition is correct, but it's not
enough to count the variables.
We need to look at the rank.
We need to ask about the number of independent equations,
and the number of independent rows and columns
in our linear transformation.
So the exact situation depends on the dimension
of the image of the kernel.
And remember, those are related through the Fundamental Theorem
of Linear Transformations.
So let's go through some cases.
First of all, suppose that s is equal to n.
So we have the same number of equations as unknowns.
The matrix M is square.
And then there are two subcases.
We saw that the matrix might be invertible.
Or even if it's square, it might not be invertible.
Invertible means that all the rows and columns
are linearly independent.
In a securities market, it means that there
are as many securities as there are states with payoffs
in the world, and that none of the securities
is redundant, that none can be written in terms of the others.
In that case, we have a unique way to replicate the payoff.
Not only can we find a solution, that solution is unique
and we get it by inverting the matrix.
So it's invertible, easy, multiplying left and right here
by an inverse, we get a solution.
Now, the determinant of M is 0, if the matrix is not
invertible, if there is a linear dependence among the rows
or columns, then we don't have a unique solution.
But what we do have is a nonzero kernel.
So there's going to be some nontrivial vector that's
taken in to 0 by the action of the matrix.
Now, if we look at that in terms of the Fundamental Theorem
of Linear Transformations, we can
see that this tells us that the dimension of the image of M
has to be the rank, and that's going to be n--
the dimension of our security space or our original space--
minus the dimension of the kernel.
And that's going to be smaller, because our assumption is
that this number is bigger than 0.
So subtracting a number bigger than 0 leads
to a number smaller than n.
And that's going to be equal to s.
So we end up with the case where in effect, n, the rank,
is going to be less than s.
So what that means is that we've got some vectors b for which
there won't be a solution.
There's some vectors that we can reach.
There's certain cases where we can solve the equation.
But we can't solve it for every possible vector,
only for a subset of the vectors.
And the size of the subset depends
on the size of the kernel of M. The bigger the kernel of M is,
the smaller the image of M is.
So let's look at how to do this in R.
And I'll let you run these commands.
These are just simple things that you
can run in the command line.
It's mostly about the case where we have a nonsingular
matrix that we just looked at.
So here's a system of linear equations.
These are three equations, three unknowns.
The matrix is nonsingular.
The function solve(M) inverts the matrix.
If we say solve(M,b), it gives us the unique solution.
And it's set up in R. I've constructed a matrix.
I've written down a vector, b.
I asked to solve for v. And here I get my answer
in decimal form, or in happier notation,
we can just say v is minus 1/3, 2/3, 0.
And you can check that that satisfies the equations above.
What we also found, though, of course,
is it's a unique solution.
So we know that there are no others,
because of our properties of M.
Now, what about the case where we have a square matrix
but it's singular?
So this is the other system we looked at earlier.
So in this case, I have the nine down here.
Rows and columns are linearly dependent.
And there's a technique for solving these equations,
as well, numerically.
So we can use this function qr to get a particular solution,
if it exists.
So what we do is, I construct a new matrix.
This is M1, in this case.
b is going to be the same vector that we had before,
and we'd like to solve it.
So if we try to solve using our previous method,
we get an error message.
And it tells us, guess what?
Matrix is probably singular, determinant's probably 0.
But if we use qr.solve, then we get a warning message
that the matrix is singular, but we nevertheless
can get a solution.
So the solution that we have, the particular solution
that we have, depends on how we do it.
Because remember, if we have a particular solution,
if there's a b, it does hit the particular b in question,
it's not uniquely determined, because we could
add any element of the kernel.
So you can check the kernel of z is this factor.
As I said, the central column is the sum
of the first and third columns.
So that's what z tells us.
And v, here's my particular choice, 0, 0, 1/3.
You can check that that satisfies the equation
that we need.
When I look in R, it found a different solution.
So this one is not as pretty as mine is,
but it's equally valid.
How do we know that?
Two different ways.
Number one, we can act on it with M
and verify that it satisfies the equation.
Or, number two, we can take the difference between the results
and find out if they differ by an element of the kernel.
Now, suppose that we've got more equations than unknowns.
Then in general, there aren't going to be any solutions,
or there won't be solutions for at least some values of b.
But again, we need to be careful about not just counting
variables, we need n equations, we need
to ask if they're independent.
After all, if I've got two more equations than unknowns,
but those equations are the same equation
or they're multiples of the same equation, that doesn't really
count.
So we get at that through looking at the rank.
So what's going on in this case is
we've got a smaller space going into a bigger one.
So we can't hit everything.
If we start with a three dimensional space
and we map it into a four dimensional space,
the most we can hope to hit is a three dimensional subspace.
There's always going to be something left over.
If we look at this in terms of our Fundamental Theorem
of Linear Transformations and we write this out,
we can see that the dimension of the image
has to be less than the entire size of the space.
But intuitively, it's because we're taking a small space
and putting it into a bigger one.
So there's no general solution.
That means that there's at least a lot--
an infinite number of factors that we can't solve for.
But we might happen to find a specific one, depending
on the particular b that we have.
If it's within the image, then we can find a solution.
So here's an example in R. Let's take a look
at four equations and two unknowns.
So in this case, qr.solve will give us a particular solution,
if it exists.
But we need to check, because it will sometimes output
things that aren't solutions.
So we need to check by substitution.
And in this case, there is a solution
for this particular set of coefficients,
this b on the right hand side, there is a solution.
And you can check that it's 3, minus 2.
But we do need to check that, because it's possible
that we could get something different.
And I have an example of that over here,
where we have a good answer.
And then a case where if I change this 5 into a 6, which
I've done over here numerically, I
get R also gives me an answer.
And if you substituted it and you find guess what,
it doesn't solve the equation.
So there's a specific algorithm in qr.solve which does generate
an output, even when it shouldn't.
So it's on you to check and make sure that it actually works.
Finally, let's take a look at case 3.
When there are more unknowns than equations,
than there are multiple solutions.
This time, we've got a big space going into a smaller one.
So think about our first example.
We've got four securities going into a three dimensional space.
Maybe I've got 10 going into a three dimensional space.
So if the space is genuinely larger,
we have a really big space going into a smaller one,
then some vectors have to get mapped to 0.
If we again look at our dimension formula
from the Fundamental Theorem of Linear Transformations, what
we can see is that the dimension of the kernel
has to be bigger than 0.
Now, if the dimension of the kernel is bigger than 0,
that means that any solutions that we do find are not unique.
It means there's an infinite number of them.
So what it means is if we can find a set of basis factors
for the kernel, say it's one dimensional,
say it's three dimensional, we can
add any linear combination of basis vectors in the kernel
to any particular solution and get another solution.
So it's a particular kind of infinity.
We have an infinite number of solutions
because we can add a finite dimensional vector
space to it, which is equal to the dimension of the kernel.
So if the kernel is one dimensional,
we have an infinite number of solutions,
but we have a one parameter family for that solutions.
If the kernel is two dimensional,
we have a two parameter family of solutions.
So there are two independent parameters, each of which
could take an infinity of values,
but it's not just anything goes.
Here's an example in R. Let's take
a look at the transpose of the previous matrix, why not?
In this case, we've got two equations and four unknowns.
Before, we had four equations and two unknowns.
So here's the system of linear equations we'd like to solve.
The qr.solve function does give us a particular solution
that we can work with.
But now we also need to solve the kernel.
Now if we do that and we solve for the kernel numerically,
again, there's not a unique way to write it down.
There are all kinds of different choices
you can make for basis factors.
And when we do it by hand, we tend to take easy things.
These are the ones that I found.
And I like them, because they've got integer entries
and they've got a bunch of zeros.
That makes it easy to check, and they look nice.
However, if you do it in R, you can get something like this.
Which, it turns out, there's a zero entry.
It's equally valid, but it looks a little bit messier.
However, they span the same space.
And given any particular solution,
such as this one, whether we find it
by I, which is easier to do for this set of equations,
or if we find it numerically by applying qr.solve,
once we have that particular solution,
we have a two parameter family general solution.
We can add some constant times this basis factor
plus the other constants this basis factor.
Or, if you prefer to use these two vectors as a basis,
we get the same thing.
This kernel function is not built into R.
There's an example of it I can show you.
We can take a look with the definition of kernel
by taking a look at adapting the eigenvalue function.
This turns out to give us a nice view of the kernel, because we
transfer this into a problem where we can think
of the kernel being related to the eigenvectors
of a different linear transformation.
So the basis might be inconvenient,
but if they're not 2 by 2 matrices or 2 by 4 or 4
by 2 matrices, where you can look at it,
squint a little bit, and guess what the kernel is,
you may need to resort to numerical methods
or to other algorithms, and that's completely fine
in larger case.
It's really except for small cases,
you wouldn't want to do that.
But conceptually, the idea is exactly the same.
So what we've done is we've classified different kinds,
different categories of systems of linear equations,
and their solutions.
And we've seen that these correspond
to the different cases that we want that,
when we examined questions of market completeness--
is s bigger or smaller than n?
What's the rank the payoff matrix?
When we looked at whether there are solutions--
what's the image of the payoff matrix?
What's the kernel of the payoff matrix?
Are there redundant securities?
These are all encompassed by the same questions
that we asked whenever we want to solve any simple system
of linear equations.