PROFESSOR: What about equity investments?
In this section, we'll go over the equity
method, a common method to account for equity securities.
In one of the previous slides, I mentioned
that equity method is used for equity securities
with 20% to 50% ownership.
When accounting using the equity method,
changes in market prices do not affect the balance sheet
or the income statement unless the loss or gain
has been realized.
This is similar to the treatment for available for sale
securities.
Dividends received affect the investment account directly
but not retained earnings.
Also, the company's earnings affect both the investment
account and retained earnings.