PROFESSOR: Hi, everyone.
Welcome to fifth recitation of the Financial Accounting course.
In this recitation, we'll cover acquisitions
and goodwill and investments.
What is mergers and acquisitions?
Companies often engage in business combinations
or acquire other firms to enhance their business.
This is informally referred to as M&A activity.
For example, Facebook acquiring Instagram or Heinz merging with
Kraft Foods are some good instances of M&As.
We will often use the term net assets.
Net assets equals assets minus liability.
Remember from the BSE that assets minus liabilities
equals equity.
The question I hope to go through in this recitation
is, how do we account for acquisitions?
Under purchase accounting, the entire acquisition payment
is added to the acquirer's balance sheet and distributed.
We do this in three steps.
One, account for fair value of tangible assets
and liabilities, such as PPE, financial assets,
and other assets and liabilities.
Two, account for identifiable intangible assets,
such as customer relationships, trade names, and patents.
And three, put everything else under goodwill,
which is an intangible asset that
is not separately identifiable.
This essentially is a plug-in account,
where you classify everything else from the two items listed
above.
This procedure as a whole is called
allocating the purchase price.
Let's dig a little deeper on goodwill and intangibles.
If you see goodwill on the balance sheet,
it represents purchase goodwill.
Goodwill will occur on firm A's balance sheet
only of firm A acquired firm B and purchased at a higher price
the firm B's book value.
Firms cannot estimate and report their own goodwill.
Similarly, identifiable intangibles
on the balance sheet, such as patents,
are the result of a purchase from another company.
The only exception is certain software development costs.
Identifiable intangibles are subject to amortization, which
we assume zero salvage value.