PROFESSOR: Let's solve an example.
Trek Company purchases 100 shares
of Stark Company for $10 each.
This is a 30% stake.
Report the transaction in BSE.
Cash decreases by $1,000, and investment increases by $1,000.
A year later, Stark Company shares rise to $15 each.
Trek Company does not sell any of their shares.
Record the BSE.
There's no effect on the balance sheet,
because equity method does not record unrealized gains.
The following year, Stark Company
issues a dividend of $1 a share.
Cash increases by $100, 1 times $100.
Investment, on the other hand, decreases by $100
to account for the dividend.
And recall that dividends affect the investment account, but not
the retained earnings account.
The following day, Stark Company announces earnings of $1,000.
Trek Company sells all of their shares for cash at $13 each.
There are two transactions here.
First, we need to account for the earnings of $1,000.
Equity method requires us to multiply earnings
times the percentage stake the company is holding,
which is 30%.
Therefore investment increases by $300
and retained earnings increase by $300.
The second transaction we need to realize
is that Trek Company should record
the selling of the securities.
Since we received $1,300 in cash by selling equity securities,
cash increases by $1,300.
On the other hand, investment decreases by 1,200.
This is after accounting minus $100
from dividends and plus $300 from earnings.
Retained earnings increases by $100
to account for the realized gain.