PROFESSOR: Let's solve an example.
AT&T acquired 100% of DirecTV stake,
and AT&T needs to make adjustments,
using the consolidation method.
The following table is AT&T and DirecTV's balance sheet post
acquisition, and both, unconsolidated,
reported in fair values.
How does AT&T's consolidate a balance sheet look
like post acquisition?
After consolidation, AT&T increases
assets and liabilities by the fair value amount.
For example, cash increases by $5,061, which
is DirecTV's cash holdings.
Other tangible assets increased by $14,943, and so on.
However, we need to adjust for the original investments
in DirecTV.
Here, in AT&T's unconsolidated balance sheet post acquisition,
reports the book value of net assets of DirecTV,
which is $47,763 under investment
in DirecTV in the fourth row of this table.
The consolidation method requires to adjust this amount,
because we already incorporated all other assets
and liabilities into the consolidated AT&T balance
sheet.
Therefore, we subtract $47,763 from AT&T's balance sheet,
which used to be recorded under AT&T's unconsolidated balance
sheet.
The final value of total assets of AT&T's consolidated balance
sheet is $402,737, and the book value of net assets
is $120,886.