PROFESSOR: Question 3 deals with debt securities
classified as trading.
Let's say Trek Company now purchased 100 par bonds,
with a face value of $10, with 10% stake, as before.
Trek classifies the bonds as trading.
Record the B.
This transaction is the same as held for maturity securities.
Cash decreases by $1,000, and investment
increases by the same amount.
A year later, bonds are trading at $15 each.
Trek Company does not sell.
Record the BSE.
In this case, since the bonds are classified as trading,
we need to record the gains and increase in market value,
although the company did not sell.
To reflect the increases in market value for trading
securities, investment increases by $500
because the market value per bond increased to $15 from $10.
On the other hand, retained earnings increases by $500
and is recorded as an increase in unrealized gains.
Later, the bonds issue a coupon payment totaling $100.
As before, cash increases by $100,
and retained earnings increase by $100, which is
classified as interest income.
The following day, bonds are trading at $13 each.
And Trek Company sells all of their bonds for cash.
Record the BSE.
Since trucks sold all of their bonds at $13,
cash increases by $1,300.
Investments decreased by $1,500, because the book
value of the bonds was recorded at $1,500.
Finally, to balance the equation out, we record negative $200
in retained earnings and classify this as realized loss.