PROFESSOR: Question is on held to maturity debt securities.
Let's say Trek Company purchases 100 par bonds with a face value
of $10, which is a 10% stake.
Trek intends to hold the bonds until maturity.
What is the balance sheet equation for this transaction?
Cash decreases by $1,000, and investment increases by $1,000.
A year later, bonds are trading at $15 each.
Trek Company does not sell.
What is the BSE?
Before we go to the BSE equation,
we need to know what kind of security
this should be classified as.
As mentioned in the question, Trek
intends to hold the bonds until maturity
and they have 10% stake.
Therefore, this would be classified as held to maturity
securities.
Knowing this, I mentioned held to maturity securities
does not have any effect on balance sheet,
despite any changes in market value.
Therefore, there is no change in the balance sheet equation.
The following year, the bonds issue a coupon payment of $100.
Record this under the BSE equation.
Cash increases by $100 because Trek
received $100 of interest income,
and retained earnings increase by $100.
At maturity, the bonds are trading at $10.
Trek Company receives back principle in cash.
Trek Company received the cash at maturity,
so cash increases by the principal amount, which
is $1,000, and investment decreases by the same amount,
$1,000.