PROFESSOR: In this question, we'll
cover available for sale, or AFS, securities.
Trek Company purchased 100 bonds with a face value
of $10, same 10% stake.
But instead, they classified the bonds as available for sale.
Record the balance sheet equation.
Again, cash decreases by $1,000 and investment increases
by $1,000.
A year later, bonds are trading at $15 each.
Trek Company does not sell.
Since this is available for sale securities,
the unrealized gains are reflected
on the balance sheet equation, but not on income statement.
Investment increases by $500, and other comprehensive income,
or OCI, increases by $500.
This OCI account does not affect income statement.
The following year, the bonds issue a coupon payment
totaling $100.
Record the B. Again, cash increases by $100,
and retained earnings increased by $100
to reflect the interest income.
The following day, bonds are trading at $13 each.
Trek Company sells all of their bonds for cash.
Again, cash increases by $1,300.
Investment, on the other hand, decreases by $1,500.
OCI also decreases by $500, because the $500 increase was
reflected on the OCI account.
In contrast to trading securities,
retained earnings increased by $300.
Why is this?
This is because OCI does not affect income statement.
And for AFS securities, you record only
realized gains or losses on the income statement.
In reality, Trek bought the bonds at $10
and sold them at $13 each.
So the realized gain itself is $300.