PROFESSOR: Question one-- acquisition.
Suppose Big Company buys Little Company for $2,000.
The following is Little Company's balance sheet.
What is the balance sheet equation
to account for this acquisition?
In order to solve this question, we
need to know more information.
First, we need to know what the fair value of tangible assets
and liabilities are.
Fair value means what the acquirer valued or paid
for these assets and liabilities as opposed to the book value.
We first know that the Big Company paid $2,000
to acquire Little Company.
The market value of net assets of the Little Company
therefore is $2,000.
In this problem, let's assume Little Company's land
is valued at $800 although the book value is $300.
All other tangible assets and liabilities
have not changed in value.
Therefore, the market value of tangible assets
after the merger becomes $1,150 rather than $650.
This is because all other assets remain the same value,
but land was valued at $800 instead of $300.
This $800 is the market value after the merger.
Total liabilities stayed the same at $450.
We have the market value of liabilities and equity--
$450 and $2,000 respectively.
We can also obtain the market value of total assets
of Little Company.
This is $2,450.
For our second step, we need to know
what the identifiable intangible assets are valued at.
Let's assume Big Company identified intangible assets
valued at $100.
Our final step requires solving for goodwill.
We subtract tangible assets and intangible assets,
which we identified previously from the total assets.
Solving for goodwill gives us $1,200 on goodwill.
Again, goodwill works like a plug-in value
after considering the market values
of tangible assets, liabilities, and intangible assets.
We now have to identify the balance sheet equation.
The balance sheet equation to record
the acquisition of Little Company
becomes cash decreases by $1,900.
Accounts receivable increase by $200.
Inventory increases by $50.
Land increases by $800.
Intangibles or intangible assets increases by $100.
Goodwill increases by $1,200, accounts payable by $50.
And long-term debt increases by $400.
Here, note that cash decreases by $1,900 instead of $2,000
because Big Company paid $2,000 in cash
but Little Company had $100 in cash so net $1,900 decrease.
Suppose Big Company previously had $1,000 of goodwill
on their balance sheet.
What is the new amount of goodwill on the balance sheet?
If Big Company had $1,000 goodwill,
and acquiring Little Company adds $1,200,
so the final goodwill amount for Big Company is $2,200.