PROFESSOR: Having established the basic concepts of what
balance sheet equation is about, let's
talk about a special example.
Recall in transaction two Tom borrowed $100,000
from the bank.
Cash increased by $100,000, and loans payable also
increased by $100,000.
Now let's assume that on December 31st of 2009 and one
year passes since Tom borrowed the loan,
Tom records interest expenses that day but no cash payment
is made.
What do you record?
First, you need to record interest expenses.
Interest expenses are recorded as expense,
and shareholders' equity decreases by $6,000.
What will balance the decreases in shareholders' equity.
Since Tom didn't make any cash payments yet,
liabilities would increase because interest
is what Tom owes to the bank.
The item accrued interests under liabilities
increases by $6,000.