PROFESSOR: In this section, we'll
cover some practice problems to familiarize yourself
with the BSC.
We'll focus on the transactions made by a hypothetical company,
Brady's Lawn Care.
Brady's Lawn Care was founded on January 1, 2009.
The company's founder, Tom, provides ongoing maintenance
and gardening services for his clients
in the summer and snow removal in the winter.
During the first fiscal year of operations,
Tom engaged in the transactions listed on the following pages.
The first transaction, on January 1, 2009,
Tom issued 100,000 shares of common stocks
to friends and family for $15 each,
in order to raise money to start his business.
What actually transaction be?
Remember the basic balance sheet equations.
Assets equals liabilities plus shareholders' equity.
In this transaction, Tom raised cash, which is assets.
So in this transaction, since cash increased,
cash item increases by $15 times 100,000 shares,
which equals $1.5 million.
Since Tom raised cash by issuing common stock,
the corresponding $1.5 million increases in the shareholders'
equity side.
Common stock is a form of shareholders' equity.
You can see the BSC holds, since assets go up by $1.5 million.
And shareholders' equity correspondingly
increases by $1.5 million.