PROFESSOR: Let's sum up the five transactions together.
The final cash number after the five transactions
is $800,000, accounts receivable, $300,000,
inventory, $225,000, equipment, $500,000.
As for the liabilities, Tom has a loan
payable of $100,000, which he received from Independent Bank.
In shareholders' equity, the common stock he issued
didn't go away.
So $1.5 million remained intact.
Tom made $300,000 in revenue with a cost of $75,000.
So net he increased retained earnings by $225,000.
Notice that the numbers at the bottom in the blue box
are basically the numbers used to create the balance sheet.
On the other hand, the red box represents
transactions or items that are used for the income statement.
Let's discuss a little bit further
how exactly we should build the financial statements
for these transactions.
For the income statement, we begin with the top line
revenue.
Recall that Tom made $300,000 in revenue
and used $75,000 to incur that revenue.
In other words, he used $75,000 as Cost of Goods Sold or COGS.
Netting COGS from revenue leaves him with $225,000.
The profit after subtracting COGS from revenue
is called gross profit.
In this scenario, Tom did not incur any other expenses.
Therefore, there is no other expenses
incurred in this example.
Therefore, the final net income equals the gross profit,
which is $225,000.
Now let's look at the balance sheet.
Again, assets are what a company owns,
liabilities are what a company owes,
and equity is the share of what the shareholders have.
Under assets, there is a list of what the company owns,
cash of $800,000, inventory of $225,000,
accounts receivables of $300,000,
and equipment of $500,000.
Its total assets is $1.825 million.
These assets are composed of liabilities and equity.
Total liabilities is $100,000 from the loan
Tom borrowed from the bank, and the rest
is shareholders' equity.
Within shareholders' equity, common stock
is $1.5 dollars million and retained earnings $225,000.
So the total equity is $1.725 million.
Let's see if the BSE holds.
Assets equals liabilities plus shareholders' equity.
Total assets is $1.825 million, and liabilities plus equity
is $1.825 million as well.
BSE holds.