PROFESSOR: Transaction five, on April 21st,
Tom billed his clients for the spring planning services
totaling $300,000.
Tom had used $75,000 worth of plants and other supplies
for these services.
It looks like Tom made a revenue.
He delivered his spring planning services in cash.
Collectability is reasonable since he builded his clients.
Because Tom didn't receive cash yet,
accounts receivable increases by $300,000.
Correspondingly because revenue increases
retained earnings, which is a shareholders' equity account,
retained earnings increases by $300,000.
During the course of generating his revenue,
Tom used $75,000 worth of plants and supplies for his service.
As per the matching principle, this cost
is incurred as revenue is recognized.
Inventory decreases by $75,000 and retained
earnings decreases by $75,000, because cost of goods sold
increased by that amount.