PROFESSOR: Related to the previous problem, problem 5
ask how much Tesla's interest expense was in 2019.
First of all, how much was the interest expense?
And we can see from the income statement, it was $685 million.
By contrast, how much interest did Tesla pay in cash in 2019?
That was only $455 million.
We can pick that up from the bottom of the cash flow
statement.
The question is, why is the difference?
And then as we saw in the prior problem,
they have a lot of convertible debt
that's treated as discount bonds.
And for that convertible debt, the interest expense
is much greater than the cash coupon or the cash interest.
This table shows cash coupon and interest expense
for Tesla's convertible bonds.
In 2019, we see that cash interest, which
is the top row there, is much smaller than total interest
expense, which is the bottom row.