JOHN CORE: Problem 7, we're starting
to look more deeply in the cash flow statement now,
asked how much cash does Tesla need for debt principal in 2020
and 2021.
So one thing we want to know is how much
Tesla debt matures in 2020, how much Tesla debt matures
in 2021.
And then recognizing that some of this debt
is convertible debt, it asked in 2020, how much of the debt
will turn into stock or convert into stock if the stock
price is greater than $300.
And then similarly, in 2021, how much of the debt
will convert into stock if the stock
price is greater than 360?
One place that we talked about looking for this information
is the contractual obligations table.
So on page 58 of the 10K, Tesla presents
their contractual obligations.
And it shows total amount of principal and interest,
so schedule interest, for 2020 and 2021.
But we're looking for just principle amount, not interest.
Fortunately, there's another table in note 12
which shows recourse debt and non-recourse debt, and then
total principal amounts coming due in 2020 and 2021.
And here we have the answers that we want,
which is about $1.4 billion in 2022, $2.3 billion in 2021.
Just as an aside, we haven't seen this concept
of recourse debt before, but non-recourse debt
is like your car loan.
So if you do not pay your car loan,
the bank will come and take your car,
but they can't take other assets from you.
So that's non-recourse debt.
Recourse debt is what you don't want to have,
is that the lender can take your car.
And then if you still owe money on the debt,
they can take your other personal assets.
So recourse debt for corporations
and for individuals is dangerous.
In terms of cash needed for debt,
this is answering the question of how much converts we have.
So at the top of the table, we see that there's
the 1.25% notes due in 2021.
And we know that they have a conversion
price of $360 a share.
So in 2021, if these notes come due
and the stock price is greater than $360,
these things will turn into stock
and we won't have to pay cash for them.
Similarly, the zero coupon convertible notes due in 2020
have a conversion price of $300 a share.
So if these notes come due and the stock price is above $300
a share, the holders of the notes will choose to take stock
and Tesla will not have to pay these notes off in cash.