PROFESSOR: So the next question, the eighth question,
talks about how much lease principle
is due for finance leases.
So here's a table that shows, starting
in 2021, how much is due for operating leases, how much is
due for finance leases, so that we see the two
totals there in 2020 and 2021.
But remember, these lease payments
are partly principal and partly interest.
So what we need to do is, assuming the interest
rate on these leases is 4 and 1/2%,
estimate how much interest there is on each of these payments.
Back that interest out and then come out
with a principal amount.
So we're assuming that there's 4.5% interest.
Notice that the total present value of the leases
is $1.618 billion.
So interest on the leases in 2020 is $73 million.
So that tells us the principal on the leases that are
due in 2020 is $401 million.
Similarly, if we roll this forward one
more year, the next year, the principal of $1.618 billion
will have been reduced by $401 million.
We take 4 and 1/2% of that.
That's $55 million in interest.
That tells us that the principal in 2021 is $423 million.
And then just as a reminder, so when
we talked about finance leases, we had an amortization table.
Here's an amortization table I've
created to put this on a more familiar format for you
so that we have our beginning lease liability of $1.618
billion in 2020.
That's column B there.
Our interest expense on that at 4 and 1/2% is $73 million.
The lease payment, which is given in the prior table,
is $474 million.
So that tells us the principal reduction is $401 million.
That's column E.
And then column F tells us that the remaining principal
at the end of 2020 is $1.217 billion.
And the rest of the table rolls on from there.
So that's just a more familiar way for you
to think of the lease amortization.