PROFESSOR: In this session, which is our last session,
we're going to use the Tesla case as a way to do a review
and to focus on liquidity and cash flow.
As a review, remember that firms need operating cash flow,
also known as cash flow from operations,
to finance their investments.
In order to grow, Tesla must build new factories.
And these investments in new factories
are investing cash flows.
It needs operating cash flow to pay down its debt.
And it needs operating cash flow, ultimately,
to return capital to its shareholders.
Paying down debt and returning capital to shareholders
are Tesla's financing cash flows.
In this session, we're going to use Tesla's 2019
financial statements to review, first, taxes,
then acquisitions, then equity and debt issues, then leases,
diluted shares, and finally, a review of cash flow.
I will give you one or more problems
for each of these topics.
After the problem, there will be slides
and a video discussing the solutions.
These Tesla case problems will not be graded.
The point of the problem is to help you review for the exam.
Again, after the problems, there are slides
and a video discussing the solutions.
But to get the most out of the review,
I recommend that you do the problems first
as if you were taking an exam.
Then after you've tried the problems
and solved the problems, review the slides and video
discussing the solutions.
As background on Tesla, at the time of the case,
Tesla's primary business is building electric cars
and electric trucks.
Tesla came public in June of 2010,
when it executed its initial public offering, or IPO,
at a price of $17 a share.
Its financial performance since then has been very strong.
It has had high growth, high growth in revenues,
and high growth in its stock price.
In the middle of July 2020, its stock price was about $1,500
a share.
However, Tesla has had a history of losses,
as startup companies often do, and has
had a history of negative cash flow from operations.
Although, in 2018 and 2019, that negative cash
flow from operations has turned positive.
In terms of concerns about Tesla,
competition is one concern with a company like this
that's so highly valued.
We know that there are other electric car and truck
companies coming into this industry
because the industry is so attractive.
Second, COVID has affected all of us.
COVID affected Tesla because its factories were shut down
for a while at the start of 2020, and demand for its cars
was lower.
This slide summarizes Tesla's performance
for the years 2017, 2018, and 2019.
The 2017 fiscal year is on the right.
The 2019 fiscal year is in the center.
Notice that Tesla has tripled the number of vehicles
it delivered from 2017 to 2019.
It has doubled its sales.
Its 2019 net income is still negative,
but it's less negative than it was in 2017.
Operating cash flow turned positive in 2018.
Investing cash flow, which is Tesla's acquisitions
of factories, new property, plant, and equipment,
has gotten smaller.
Therefore, because of the smaller shortfall
between operating cash flow and investing cash flow,
financing cash flow has decreased from $4.4 billion
in 2017 to $1.5 billion in 2019.
Here's a slide that we've seen before when
we were talking about bonds.
In the middle of 2019, Tesla's main publicly-traded bond
was trading for about $0.82 on the dollar.
At that time, Tesla's bond price was
flashing a risk of bankruptcy.
Since then, the bond has recovered.
In early 2020, the price is back over 100.
This higher bond price is telling us
that the risk that Tesla goes bankrupt is now lower.
Here is a chart of Tesla's stock price for the five years ended
July 10, 2020.
Notice that Tesla initially sold off in 2020--
in early 2020-- when the rest of the market also sold off.
But since then, it's accelerated,
and it's gone up to a price of about $1,500 a share
as of July 10, 2020.
Later on, we're going to use this price of $1,500
as part of our case.
But please do the case as if you received these 2019
financial statements early in 2020.
Tesla's performance has substantially
improved since the time of the case in early 2020.
And I want to summarize, briefly, two developments
at Tesla since then--
since the time of the 2019 financial statements.
First, Tesla split its stock 5 for 1.
Second, Tesla has done a number of stock offerings
and raised a lot of equity capital.
But Tesla split its stock 5 for 1 on August 28, 2020.
Just before the split, Tesla's price was $2,213,
and it had 186.4 million shares outstanding.
Now, as a review of our discussions of stock splits,
how many shares did it have outstanding immediately
after the split?
Well, this was a 5-for-1 split.
Tesla started with 186.4 million shares.
We're going to multiply that by 5.
So immediately after the split, Tesla
had 932 million shares outstanding.
Also as a review, what was the price
immediately after the split?
Again, it was a 5-for-1 split.
The price before the split was $2,213.
We divide that by 5.
So the price immediately after the split was $442.60.
Also, we noted above that the July 10, 2020 presplit price
was $1,500.
What was the split-adjusted price?
So this one is a little bit easier, mathematically.
Again, it was a 5-for-1 split.
The price was $1,500.
We divide that by 5 to come up with a $300 postsplit price.
Now, the second major development
at Tesla since the 2019 financial statements
is related to the fact that, on December 31, 2020,
Tesla's stock price has risen to a price of $705.
Now, notice that this is equivalent to a price of $3,525
presplit.
So it's a big price increase in 2020.
And Tesla took advantage of this price increase
to do three stock offerings in 2020.
And in total, over these three stock offerings,
Tesla raised $12.3 billion.
Because of the money raised through these stock offerings
and because of strong cash flow in 2020, Tesla, in early 2021,
has low need for liquidity or extra cash.
In contrast, in 2019, at the time of our case,
Tesla had a big need for liquidity, a big need for cash.
I wanted to tell you about these developments at Tesla
since the 2019 financial statements
to give you background for you when you encounter
Tesla outside this course.
Again, though, please do the case
as if you received the 2019 financial statements
in early 2020.
Please conduct your analysis solely
based on these statements and what
was known about Tesla in early 2020.