PROFESSOR: Let's talk about earnings per share.
Earnings per share is a commonly used metric
for assessing profitability.
It is typically calculated in two ways-- basic and diluted.
Let's first look at the basic EPS.
Basic EPS is calculated as net income
available to common shareholders divided
by weighted average shares outstanding.
Specifically, the numerator here is net income
minus net income attributable to non-controlling interest
minus preferred dividends.
For the denominator, let's look at an example.
The following table shows the number of shares on each date
and how long a firm maintain that number of shares.
For example, on January 1st, there
were 100,000 shares outstanding for three months
under column weight.
In April, the number of shares increased to 120,000 shares
for a month and so on.
Therefore, the weighted average of the number
of shares throughout the year in this example is 107,500 shares.
Diluted EPS goes one step further to calculate the EPS.
It represents the EPS under a what-if scenario
in which all in-the-money stock options are exercised
and all convertible instruments are converted to common stock.
The formula for diluted EPS is net income
available to common shareholders plus add-backs
divided by weighted average shares
outstanding plus conversions.
There are two additional items added from the basic EPS--
add-backs and conversions.
Add-backs in the numerator include
dividends paid to preferred shareholders and interest paid
to convertible debt holders.
Conversions include convertible instruments and stock option
exercises.
Assume all convertible instruments
converted into common stock.
Stock option exercises require more calculations.