PROFESSOR: In this section, we'll
cover two types of hybrid instruments.
First, preferred stock is similar to a bond,
but pays dividends like equity.
It generally does not come with ownership or voting rights
and pays a stated dividend.
Second, there is convertible debt.
Convertible debt is interest-bearing debt
that has the ability to be converted to stock.
Convertible debt allows the owner
to take advantage of increases in the stock price
via the conversion option.
Because of the value of this option,
convertible debt tends to have very low interest payments.
We will solve two examples regarding
these hybrid instrument accounting.