PROFESSOR: Question 2, diluted EPS conversions, Part A,
net effect of number of shares.
Suppose Kendall Corp. is trading at $50 per share.
Outstanding stock options include 200,000 options
with an exercise price of $30 a share
and 100,000 options with an exercise
price of $60 per share.
To assess the net effect of number of shares,
we conduct three steps.
Step one, assume exercise all in-the-money options.
There are 200,000 options with an exercise
price of $30 per share.
So the proceeds are $6 million.
We ignore $60 per share options, because those options are not
in-the-money.
Step two, assume use of proceeds to repurchase stock.
With the $6 million proceeds, we can purchase 120,000 shares,
since the current share price is $50 per share.
Step three, examine the net effect on shares outstanding.
In step one, 200,000 shares increased.
And in step two, 120,000 shares decreased.
Therefore, net, the weighted average shares outstanding
increases by 80,000 shares.
Part B, calculating diluted EPS.
Kendall Corp. maintained 500,000 shares outstanding
for the whole year.
Its net income was $2 million and did not have any addbacks.
What is the diluted EPS for Kendall Corp.?
Recall the diluted EPS formula, net income
available to common shareholders plus addbacks,
divided by weighted average shares
outstanding plus conversions.
Here, net income is $2 million.
There's no addbacks.
And divide this by 500,000 shares plus 80,000.
And this equals diluted EPS of $3.45 per share.