PROFESSOR: Question 3, part A, Preferred Stock--
"Use the BSE to record the issuance
of 10,000 shares of 6% preferred stock with a par value
of $100 for $150 a share."
10,000 preferred stock was issued at $150 per share.
So 150 times 10,000 equals 1.5 million.
Cash increases by 1.5 million.
Par value preferred stock increases by 1 million
because its par value per share is $100.
Additional paid in capital is the difference
between total cash proceeds and par value
preferred stock, which is $0.5 million.
Next question-- "Use the BSE to record the first payment
of dividends."
6% preferred stock means the preferred stock
will pay 6% of its par value.
Therefore, the dividend amount for 10,000 shares
should be $60,000.
If dividends are declared but is yet to be paid,
dividends payable, which is a liability account,
increases by $60,000, and retained earnings
decreases by the same amount.
If dividend is already paid in cash,
cash decreases by $60,000, and dividends
payable decreases by the same amount
and balances the equation out.
Part B, Convertible Debt--
"Assume Uber issues 1,000 one-year 2% convertible bonds
with a face value of $100."
these bonds have a conversion feature
that allows the bondholders to convert each bond
to one Uber share at maturity.
The market rate at issuance is 8%,
and the present value of the bonds is $94,444.
Use the BSE to record the issuance.
Convertible bonds are treated similarly as a regular bond
without conversion.
The present value of the bond is $94,444,
so cash increases by that amount.
Bond payable increases by $100,000
since 1,000 bonds with a $100 face value each were issued.
To balance the equation out, bond discount,
which is a contraliability account, increases by 5,556.
Use the BSE to require the coupon payment
at the end of year one.
Since it's a 2% bond, cash decreases by $2,000.
Interest expense is $94,444 times 8% which is the market
rate, and this is 7,556.
Bond discount decreases by 5,556 to balance the equation now.
Suppose that at maturity, the stock
is trading at $80 a share.
Assume no par value.
The stock is trading lower than the bond's face value,
so the bondholders will not convert.
The bond principal is paid back.
Cash decreases by $100,000, and bond payable
decreases by the corresponding amount.
Suppose that at maturity, the stock is trading at $200
a share.
Assume bondholders convert.
The bondholders convert, so bond payable decreases by $100,000.
And because par value is assumed to be 0,
additional paid-in capital increases by the same 100,000.