PROFESSOR: Question four deals with stock compensation.
Companies will often compensate employees
by granting them stock options.
These options may have a vesting period meaning that they cannot
be exercised until they vest.
Use the BSE to record the transaction
to grant employees 15,000 stock options on January 1st.
These options are valued at $20 each and will vest immediately.
For stock options BSE will be reported
once stock options are vested.
In this case since options are vested immediately,
contributed capital increases by 300,000
which is 20 times $15,000.
Since stock options are a form of employee wages,
retained earnings decreased by 300,000
and is labeled as wage expense.
Now, use the BSE to record the transaction assuming
those same options vest over three years evenly.
Again, BSE occurs once the options are vested.
Options are vested over a three year period
so contributed capital increases by 100,000
and retained earnings decrease by the same amount for three
years.