PROFESSOR: Now what I will do right now,
I will increase the number of stocks from 30 to 300.
I will maintain the assumption that the loadings
on the first factor for each of these 300 stocks
right now is still one and I will maintain the same loading
structure on the second factor but I
will assume that for the first 100 stocks
the second beta, beta 2 is equal to 1.
For the next 100 stocks, so from 101 to 200, the beta is 1.6,
and from 201 to 300, so for the last 100 stocks, beta 2 is 2.1.
Right now I want to understand what
happens to betas of the portfolio, the factor loadings,
of this equally weighted portfolio on factor 1
and factor 2.
And so let's see, for the first factor
we get, it's exactly the same expression
because it's an equally weighted portfolio,
so all that changes is just n1.
So before it was 30, right now it's 300.
And you can see that this expression again
is going to be equal to 1 because we're
adding 1 over 300.
So this is the weight that we put in each individual stock,
300 times.
Before we were doing it 30 times.
And so this sum is just equal to 1.
And again, this should be intuitive
that if each of the individual stocks have factor loading of 1
on the first factor, then again, if we combine them
into a portfolio, the portfolio loading on factor 1
is going to be just simply equal to 1 as well.
For equal weighted portfolio but then
again for any other portfolio as well.
Now let's see what happens to the factor loading
on the second factor.
So this is the same expression as we
had before again, n1 right now is 300, but all we're doing
is that we are adding the second beta for each
of the individual stocks and so here we're doing,
we're adding it 100 times for the first asset,
so it's 100 times 1, then 100 times 1.6
for the second class of stocks and then
another 100 multiplied by 2.1.
So this is for the last class of stocks with this beta.
And so then all we're doing is that we're adding this up
and we're dividing it by n1, which right now is 300.
And you can see that this is just,
it's a simple scaling compared to the case
that we had before when we had 30 stocks, so we
were multiplying by 10 and were dividing by 30, right now
we're multiplying it by 100 and dividing it by 300.
So this doesn't change the final answer
that the beta, second beta the loading
of this portfolio in the second factor is 1.57.
So this doesn't change.
So the result here is that as we increase
the number of stocks in this portfolio from 30 to 300 factor
loadings stay the same.