PROFESSOR: Let's use our estimated APT model
to forecast future expected returns.
Let's assume that the returns on those stocks
satisfy the exact two factor APT model
with the stock market and the gold ETF as the two factors.
Let's also assume that the estimated factor loadings
are exact.
Suppose that we are given a forecast
for the expected excess monthly returns going forward
for the market of 0.75% and for the gold 0.15%.
Let's use the average factor loadings we've computed
and compute the expected excess return
for the technology sector and for the gold mining sector.
To compute the expected returns on both of these sectors,
we need to take the factor risk premia
and multiply them by the loadings
that these two sectors have on the corresponding risk factors.
So let's start with the expected return on the technology
sector.
It will be equal the expected excess return
on the market multiplied by the loadings
that technology sector has on the market,
which is 0.98, plus the expected excess return on gold,
which is 0.15%.
This is the number given to us.
Multiplied by the loadings that the technology sector
has on the gold risk factor, which is negative 0.17.
And this would be our expected return
on the technology sector.
Similarly, for the gold mining sector,
we have the expected excess return on the market multiplied
by the loadings that the mining sector has on the market,
which is 0.19, plus the expected excess return
on the gold multiplied by the loadings
that the gold sector has on the gold, which is 1.75.
And the result would be 0.4%.
To summarize, given the forecast of the expected excess monthly
returns on the market and gold, 0.75% and 0.15%,
the expected return of the technology sector
monthly return would be 0.71 and the expected monthly return
in the gold mining sector would be 0.4%.