PROFESSOR: Let's find idiosyncratic volatility
of an equally weighted portfolio.
So we're after standard deviation of epsilon P
and we'll start with the variance
and then we'll take the square root of it
to find the standard deviation.
So let's start with the variance.
By definition since idiosyncratic risks
of individual assets are uncorrelated,
the variance or idiosyncratic risk of the portfolio P
would equal to the sum of the individual idiosyncratic
variances of each individual stocks, multiplied
by the squared weights that we have in the portfolio.
And so recall that again, all Wis are just 1 over 30,
or 1 over n1, and so therefore, each of these wi squared, which
is equal to 1 over n1 squared.
And now what we are left with is just
the sum of idiosyncratic variances of individual stocks.
And this is the structure.
So the first 10 stocks have the standard deviation
of 5%, idiosyncratic standard deviation of 5%.
The next 10 stocks 6% and the remaining 10 stocks 8%.
So if we add up all of them.
So we get 10 times 5% squared, so this is the variance
of these first 10 stocks.
Then 10 times 6% squared, so this is the total variance
of the second stocks.
And then 10 times 8% squared, so this is the variance
of the remaining 10 stocks.
Again, so n1 equals t0 30, so 1 over 30 squared,
putting this all together gives us 0.00014.
And so this is the variance or idiosyncratic variance
of this portfolio P.
To find the standard deviation, we're
just taking the square root of this number that we found here
and we get number 1.18%.
So the idiosyncratic volatility of this equally
weighted portfolio P equals to 1.18%.
Notice how much lower it is compared
to the individual idiosyncratic variances
of each individual assets.
The lowest one is 5% and so this portfolio right now
has very low variance, idiosyncratic variance
of just 1.18%.