PROFESSOR: Now let's see what happens to the idiosyncratic
volatility of a portfolio as we increase the number of stocks.
We will increase it from 30 to 300
and we'll compute the idiosyncratic volatility, again
of this equally weighted portfolio.
I will maintain the assumption that the first 100 stocks have
idiosyncratic volatility of 5%, the next 100 stocks 6%,
and the remaining 100 stocks of 8%.
So this is a standard deviation of epsilon I
of these individual stocks.
Now let's see what changes in the expression
that we've had before.
So one thing that changes is n1, so instead of 30, it
becomes 300 and so I'm raising, I'm
squaring 300 right now instead of 30.
And now I'm adding up instead of adding up
30 idiosyncratic variances, I'm adding
up 300 idiosyncratic variances because I have 300 stocks.
And so the first 100 stocks have idiosyncratic variance
of 5% squared.
So the remaining, or the next 100 stocks 6%
squared, and the last 100 stocks 8% squared.
So adding this all up gives me this variance.
You can see that already this variance is quite a bit smaller
than this one because it has an extra 0 here.
And so now if I compute the volatility
of the standard deviation of this portfolio P,
by taking the square root of the variance that I just computed,
this gives me 0.37%.
So you could see that the variance dropped quite sharply
from 1.18% for a portfolio that had 30 stocks,
to 0.37% for a portfolio that has 300 stocks.
And so the key lesson here is that it's exactly this drop.
In the limit we know that idiosyncratic volatility
of the portfolio, of equally weighted portfolio,
is going to go to zero.
You can see here that if I increase n1 to further
to 3,000, again, maintaining the same assumption here,
the volatility of this equally weighted portfolio
is going to drop further to 0.12%.
So if we continue increasing, it's going to go down,
it's going to go down to 0.
And this is the key lesson of this example.