PROFESSOR: In our discussion of financing so far,
we have taken the firm's investment decision,
or its asset, as given.
Towards the later part of our discussion
we have learned that the nature of its asset
may well influence the firm's risk
and cause financial distress if it takes on debt.
This suggests a potential connection between investment
and financing.
In this lecture, we want to consider this connection.
In particular, we want to examine
how financing may interact with a firm's investment decision.
This is because a project's asset
may bring actual debt capacity, which can bring tax shield
and increase firm value.
Therefore, our main question is how
to value a project, taking into account how it can be financed,
and the additional benefit it brings.