PROFESSOR: We now consider an example
to illustrate how the approach laid out above is implemented.
We are considering buying SuperSoft, a software company.
We have the following information.
SuperSoft is currently privately held and 100% equity financed.
Its projected annual pre-tax cash flow
is $1.5 million perpetually.
SuperSoft faces an effective tax rate of 30%.
Its assets can sustain a debt level of 20% of its asset value
without significant distress cost.
The risk-free interest rate is 5%,
which is also what SuperSoft pays on its debt.
In addition, there are two publicly-traded software
companies: 1 and 2.
Their financial data is given in a table on the slide.
For firm 1, which is described in the second row,
its required rate of return on equity
is 24.31%, given in the second column.
Its required rate of return on debt
is 6.95%, given in the third column.
Its debt-to-equity ratio is 0.5, given in the fourth column,
and its tax rate is 0.34, or 34%, given in the last column.
For firm 2, as given in the third row,
its required rate of return on equity and debt
are 29.07% and 9.88%, respectively.
It's debt-to-equity ratio is 1.2.
And its tax rate is 0.30.
Our first task is to uncover the required rate of return
for the assets of these two firms
and then use it to value SuperSoft.
Using MM II with taxes, we can uncover the required rate
of return on the asset of firm 1 and 2,
which are rA1 equals 18.51% and rA2 equals 18.60%.
Take the average.
We have rA equals 18.56%.
Using it to value SuperSoft's asset or after-tax cash flow,
we have its value without the leverage effect.
That is, VU equals 1 minus 0.3--
that's tax rate-- times 1.5--
that's the pre-tax cash flow--
divided by the discount rate, which is 0.1856.
That gives us $5.66 million.
Its value with leverage at 20% leverage ratio
is then given by VL equals VU plus PVTS,
and that equals 5.66 plus 0.3--
again, the tax rate--
times 0.05, the interest rate, times 0.2, the debt ratio,
times 5.66--
the asset value without leverage--
and then discounted by 0.1856.
That gives us $5.75 million.
Therefore, by using the debt capacity of the asset,
we can increase the value of the firm
by the PVTS, which is 5.75 minus 5.66.
And that is $0.09 million.