PROFESSOR: For the same example, we
now consider how to use the WACC approach to value SuperSoft.
The value of SuperSoft's asset is Vu.
That's $5.66 million given before.
It is independent of leverage.
The debt is safe at 20% of the asset value.
This gives D equals 0.2 times Vu.
Since the debt is risk free, the interest rate on the debt
is the risk-free rate rf, which is 5%.
The present value of the tax shield
is then PVTS equals tau times rf times D.
That's the total interest payment divide by rA.
And that equals 0.3 times 0.05 interest rate divide
by 0.1856, the discount rate, then
times the total value of the debt, which is 0.2 times Vu.
Summarizing this, we have 0.016 times vu.
The value of equity with leverage
is E equals vu plus PVTS minus D. That equals 1 plus 0.016
minus 0.2 times vu.
And that equals 0.816 times vu.
We then have the weight of debt WD equals 0.2 divide
by 0.2 plus 0.816.
And that is 0.2 divide by 1.016.
The weight of equity equals 0.816 divided by 1.016.
The required rate of return on equity is then given by rE
equals rA plus D over E times rA minus rD.
That's the MM II with taxes.
And that equals 18.56% plus 0.2 divide by 0.816 times 18.56%.
And that gives us 21.88%.
We can now compute the WACC for SuperSoft
with the leverage level and its tax shield.
WACC equals 0.2 times 1 minus 0.3 divide by 1.016 times
5%, the risk-free rate, plus 0.816 divided by 1.016 times
21.88%.
And that equals 18.26%.
Using the WACC, which is adjusted for tax shield,
the value of the lumber firm is given
by vL equals 1 minus 0.3, the tax rate, times 1.5,
the pretax cash flow, divide by WACC.
And that is 1 minus 0.3 times 1.5 divided by 0.1826,
and that gives us $5.75 billion.
Clearly, we all get the same answer as using APV.
With WACC, we can apply it to similar projects
with the same financing structure assuming
it's optimal.
It cannot be blindly applied to different projects,
which may have different discount rates for the assets
and different optimal leverage levels.
Before we move on, let's take a look
at some data concerning leverage and WACC
across different industries.
The table on the slide reports the debt ratio
that's debt to asset, equity beta, asset beta, and WACC
for a sample of industries.
The leverage ratio is higher at the top and decreases
over as we go down the list.
The second row is for the electric and gas industry.
As that ratio is 43.2% as we said before,
its equity beta is 0.58.
And its asset beta is 0.33, which is quite a bit lower
than the equity beta.
Using a risk-free rate of 6%, a market risk premium of 8%,
a cost of debt of 7.5%, and a tax rate of 35%,
we obtained the WACC for this industry to be 8.1%.
The third row gives the same information for the food
production industry.
Its debt ratio is 22.90%.
The equity and asset betas are 0.85% and 0.66% respectively.
And the WACC for this industry is 11.0%.
If we go to the sixth row, it is for retailers.
This industry has a debt ratio of 21.70%.
The equity and asset betas are 1.19 and 0.93 respectively.
The WACC is 13.2%
The eighth row is for the computer software industry.
Its debt ratio is 3.50%, which is very low for reasons we
explained before.
Its equity and asset betas are 1.33 and 1.28 respectively.
The industry WACC is 16.2%.
Looking down the list, we see the following patterns.
First, asset betas increases as we see from the fourth column.
This is how the industries are arranged
in the table in the first place.
Correspondingly, the debt ratio decreases
as the second column shows for reasons we have discussed
in the previous lecture.
The equity beta given in the third column
is always higher than asset beta as stated by MM.
But the difference decreases as we go down the list.
This reflects the fact that leverage is decreasing
as asset beta increases.
In general, WACC increases with asset beta
as the last column shows.
The 10th row in the table gives the average
numbers across all industries.
The average debt ratio is 21.50%.
The asset beta is 0.82.
The equity beta is 1.04 as expected.
The average WACC is 12.3%.