PROFESSOR: We will now introduce basic elements
of portfolio analytics.
In particular, we'll introduce concepts
of leverage and margin.
First, let's define a portfolio.
A portfolio is a collection of assets, risky or risk free.
The portfolio is defined by its composition--
how many shares of each security are held in the portfolio.
In terms of notation, we are going
to denote the total portfolio value by V.
And this value is going to be equal to the sum of investments
in each of the securities in the portfolio.
Each of the investments is valued
as the number of shares times the market price.
So the total portfolio value V is equal to the sum,
across all of the positions in the portfolio,
of the product of the price Pi and the number of shares Ni.
The composition of the portfolio can also
be described by portfolio weights.
The weight on each investment is defined
as the ratio of the value of the position, normalized
by the value of the portfolio.
It's the ratio of Ni times Pi, which
is the value of the position over V,
the value of the portfolio.
For this definition to make sense,
the value of the portfolio cannot be 0.
In fact, typically, the value is positive.
There are, however, some portfolios for which
the value V could be 0.
We call these arbitrage portfolios.
An arbitrage portfolio is special.
It does not require a positive investment.
For every long position in the portfolio,
there has to be a short position so that the total investment
into the portfolio is 0.
For a typical portfolio, V is positive.
Portfolio weights, in this case, are well defined.
And by definition, they have to add up to 1.
So the sum of W1 plus W2 and so forth
across all of the positions in the portfolio
is always equal to 1.
As an example, consider a portfolio
of three securities, A, B, and C,
with a total investment of $100,000.
Suppose that we buy 200 shares of assets A,
1,000 shares of asset B, and 750 shares of asset C.
You can see the relevant data in the table.
You can see the number of shares in each position,
the price per share, which is $50 for A, $60 for B,
and $40 for C, and the total investment into each security.
The total investment is equal to the number of shares
times the share price.
For example, for asset A, it's 200 shares at $50 per share.
It's $10,000.
It's $60,000 for asset B and $30,000 for asset C.
So the total investment is $100,000.
You can see, in the column on the right, portfolio weights.
As we said before, portfolio weight
is defined as the ratio of the value of each position
to the total value of the portfolio.
For A, it's going to be 10,000 divided
by 100,000, which is 10%.
It's 60% for B and 30% for C. By definition, these weights sum
up to 1 or 100%.
Now, suppose your broker informs you
that you could, in fact, maintain the same portfolio
with less capital.
Let's say, you could reduce your capital investment
to $50,000 from $100,000.
How can you achieve that?
You need to use margin.
You could borrow money at the risk-free rate
to buy risky assets in the portfolio.
In our particular example, in order
to buy $100,000 worth of stocks starting
with $50,000 in capital, you would
need to borrow $50,000 at the risk-free rate.
This changes the portfolio composition.
If you now look at the table, you
see that we have a new row, which corresponds
to the risk-free bond.
The investment into the bond is negative,
which means that we are borrowing $50,000.
The investment in each of the stocks is the same as before.
We're establishing the same portfolio.
The portfolio weights, however, now change.
The reason is that while the investment into each
of the securities, A, B, and C, is the same as before,
the total value of the portfolio in the denominator
is now $50,000 and not $100,000, which
doubles the weight on each of the risky assets.
It is now 20% invested in A rather than 10%,
120% in B rather than 60%, and 60% in C instead of 30%.
When we sum up portfolio weights across the risky assets
plus minus 100% invested in the risk-free bond,
the total of the weights is again 100%.
Another example of a portfolio that is commonly used
can be seen in buying real estate.
Imagine that you're buying a house.
The value of the house is $500,000.
You make an initial investment of $100,000, which
is 20% of the house value.
These ratios are typical for the US residential market.
The remaining $400,000 need to be borrowed.
And they could be borrowed by obtaining
a mortgage on the home.
As a result, a buyer of the house
has a portfolio with two positions--
$500,000 of real estate, which is the value of the house,
and a negative position of $400,000, which
represents the mortgage.
This is the amount of money that the buyer owes to the bank.
The total net value of the investment,
which has developed the portfolio, V, is $100,000.
It's the sum of the two positions.
If we now compute portfolio weights,
we see that the weight of the house--
the weight of the real estate in the portfolio-- is plus 500%.
And the weight of the mortgage, which is a loan, is minus 400%.
The total, again, is 1, 100%.
The ratio of the asset value to the net investment
is what we call leverage.
That's the leverage ratio.
In our example of buying a house, the asset is the house.
The net investment is $100,000, which
is what the buyer of the home invests into this property.
The ratio of the asset value to the net investment
is 500 over 100, which is 5.
That's the leverage ratio of this transaction.
Leverage magnifies movements in the asset value.
It scales up gains as well as losses.
For example, suppose that the house value declines by 15%.
A cash buyer would have seen a 15% decline
in the total value of the portfolio.
Someone who uses a mortgage is going
to see a much larger decline.
In fact, it's going to be 5 times as large, 75%.
To see that, let's compute the decline in the asset value.
$500,000-- that's the value of the initial investment--
declines by $75,000, which is 15%.
Following the decline of 15%, the value of the house
is now $425,000.
With the initial investment of $100,000
and the mortgage of $400,000, this
means that the buyer of the house
is left with a total of $25,000.
That is a $75,000 decline, or a 75% decline
relative to the initial investment.