PROFESSOR: Now suppose that the interest rates
drop by 1.5% at all maturities.
This means that the yield curve shifted downwards by 1.5%.
So first we will use the modified duration
to determine first-order approximate change in this bond
price.
So this is exactly what we have done in the previous question.
So the change in the price of the bond
is going to be negative again, negative sign because yields
and prices go in the opposite directions.
So is it going to be a negative original price
of the bond, multiplied by the modified duration,
multiplied by the change in the yield.
So recall that the price of this bond is 106.77.
The modified duration that we computed
in part A of this question is 4.41.
And we're multiplying it by negative 1.5%,
so this is the drop in the yield curve.
So doing this calculation gives us delta P equal to $7.06.
So therefore, as interest rates drop by 1.5%,
the bond price increased approximately by $7.06.