PROFESSOR: Let's summarize this question.
For a zero-coupon bond that matures in 20 years,
Macaulay duration was 20.
Modified duration was 19.61.
For a perpetual bond, Macaulay duration was 51.
Modified duration was 50.
And for a coupon bond--
5% coupon bond that matures in 20 years--
Macaulay duration was 14.43 and modified duration was 14.15.
Let's compare a and c.
So one of the key things that we learned here
is that for a zero-coupon bond, the Macaulay duration equals
the maturity of the bond.
And so in that case, it was 20.
Now, for the bond that also has 20 year maturity
but pays a coupon, Macaulay duration
has to be strictly less than 20.
So if you compare a and c, again, c
has Macaulay duration of 14.43, which is less than 20.
Now, if we compare b and c--
so both of these bonds pay the same coupon, but bond in c
has 20 years to maturity and bond in b is a perpetual bond.
And so here, of course, you see that the longer
the maturity of the bond, the higher is the Macaulay
duration.
So in this particular case, the Macaulay duration
is 51, which is much higher than the Macaulay duration
for a 5% coupon bond that matures just in 20 years.
Generally speaking, if we're comparing two bonds,
both of which have the same yield to maturity
and the same coupon rate, the bond that matures later
will have higher duration.