PROFESSOR: Now in this question, we
will use both modified duration and convexity
that we computed in part B to determine
a second-order approximate change in the bond price.
The second-order approximate change in the bond price
is given by the following expression,
so it's the original price, multiplied by negative modified
duration, multiplied by the change in YTM,
plus the convexity of the bond, multiplied
by the change in YTM squared.
So let's plug in the numbers that we have for the price,
for the modified duration, and for the convexity of this bond.
So the price is 106.77, the modified duration is 4.41,
the YTM again drops by 1.5%, the convexity
that we computed in part B of this question is 12.38,
multiplied by 1.5% squared.
Computing this gives us the change in price of $7.36.
So as YTM drops by 1.5%, the price of this bond
increases by approximately $7.36