PROFESSOR: Finally let us compute the actual change
in the price of the bond and then we'll
compare this change with approximations
that we obtained in part C and D of this question.
So the new yield to maturity on this bond right now is 2%.
So it was 3.5, dropped by 1.5, so the new YTM is 2%.
So given this new YTM we can compute the bond price
which will be $114.14.
So therefore, the actual change in the price of this bond
is $114.14, minus the original price
of the bond, which is $106.77, this will give us $7.37.
Now let's put this all together.
So the change in value that we obtained
using first-order approximation or approximation only using
modified duration was $7.06.
The approximation, the second-order approximation
that we obtained using both modified duration
and convexity of this bond is $7.36 and the actual change
in the price of this bond is $7.37.
Now you can see how remarkably close
the second-order approximation is
to actual change in the price of the bond.
This is because the price of the bond
as the function of yield to maturity is a convex function.
And in this question we've given you a very large change
in yield to maturity.
So the original was 3.5% and it dropped by 1.5%.
Recall that the first-order approximation,
or the approximation using just modified duration
would work well but only for small change in yields.
But for these large changes, such as drop by 1.5%,
the first-order approximation doesn't work that well.
It still works OK, but doesn't work
as well as both modified duration and the convexity
of the bond, where we can come as close as just
$0.01 within the actual change in the value of this bond.