PROFESSOR: The second part of the question
asks us to find share price of iDoc in the Year 1.
To help us solve this problem, I will put everything
on the timeline again.
So dividend 2 is going to be equal
to a 1.5 times 1.1 squared.
And we already computed the share price in Year 2.
So the share price in Year 2 is 37.39.
So to find the share price in Year 1, all we need to do
is that we need to take this payments in Year 2
that would get as stockholders and to discount them to Year 1.
So we're taking D2 plus P2 and we're dividing it by 1 plus r.
And this would give us P1.
So putting this all together, we get 1.5 times 1.1 squared.
So this is D2 plus 37.39 this is the share price in Year 2,
and we're dividing it by 1 plus 8%.
This gives us $36.30.
So the share price in the year one would be $36.30.
Now again, let me re-emphasize that this is ex-dividend
share price.
So it does not take into account the dividend
that this company iDoc is expected to pay in the Year 1.
So this is ex-dividend price in the Year 1.
And you can see that we are only counting Dividend 2
and the share price in Year 2.
So P1 equals to 36.30.
Let me show an alternative way of solving this question.
Let's start with the fundamental equation
that ties the share price today with the share price in Year 1.
So the share price today must equal to the dividend
that we get in the Year 1 plus the share price in Year 1
discounted to present, so divided by 1 plus r.
If we rearrange this equation for P1,
so P1 is going to equal to P0 multiplied
by 1 plus r minus Dividend 1.
So we can use this equation because we already
found the current share price of P0
in the first part of this question.
So I will take this P0 that we before,
so 35.14, multiplied by 1 plus r.
So recall again that r is 8%.
And minus the Dividend 1 that we expect to receive in Year 1.
So this is 1.5 multiplied by 1.1.
So computing this value gives us $36.30.
And so this is exactly the same value
as we've got in here by just computing the share price as--
share price in Year 1 as discounted
some of the dividend in Year 2 plus the share price
and Dividend 2 discounted to Year 1.
So either this way or this way, we've got exactly the same
share price of 36.30.