PROFESSOR: Now to practice, let me show you an alternative way
of solving this problem.
Let me first start computing the share
price as growing perpetuity, again, using Gordon growth
discount model, but starting from dividends that we
get from year six onwards.
So what I will do is that I will find
the share price in year five as dividend 6 divided
by r minus g.
So this is the value.
This is the share price ex-dividend
at point in time five that captures
the value of all of the dividends
that start in year six and continue forever.
So recall that D6 is $1 multiplied by 1
plus 3% percent.
So it is dividing that by r minus g.
So this gives me the share price of this stock
in year five of $11.44.
Now, to find the current price of the stock, what I will do
is that I will take the share price in year five,
plus I will add the dividend that we get in year five.
Recall-- and this is important.
Recall that share price in year five,
the way we're computing it here, it's
an ex-dividend share price.
So it does not take into account the dividend
it received in year five.
So this value only counts dividends
starting from year six onwards.
So therefore, to compute the current share price,
I'm taking the ex-dividend price in year five,
I'm adding the dividend that I will receive in year five--
this is $1--
and I'm discounting all of this to present.
So D5 plus P5 divided by 1 plus r, raised to the power of 5.
So this gives me $1 plus $11.44--
again, this is the share price in year five--
divided by 1 plus 12%, raised the power of 5.
And this gives me $7.06.
So unsurprisingly, we've got exactly the same answer
as we've gotten before.
This is just to illustrate that as long as you're doing it
consistently, you can have, potentially,
multiple ways of solving the same problem that gives you
exactly the same answer.
Again, the key is to make sure that you're counting
all dividends properly.