The real world exists in continuous time,
and we need models that evolve in continuous time as well.
We've looked at discrete-time processes
and discrete-time models, and they're great for what they do.
If we think about making discrete observations
or approximating time as being a series of discrete intervals,
then we can have a structure where we write down
models that show how information and other econometric variables
propagate forward in time.
We can do a lot of calculations, we
can solve some of those models in closed form,
and we can extend and generalize them in a variety of ways.
But time is continuous.
So while we might think of approximating time
as, say, each individual day is a separate point in time,
decisions are made in continuous time,
and we want some variables that do so as well.
Now, we want to distinguish between time
being continuous or discrete versus variables
being continuous or discrete.
We could have variables like pricing variables
that are continuous or near continuous
in both discrete time and in continuous time.
We'll see that although the world evolves
in continuous time, the mathematics
has some interesting twists, and it's more complex.
So many times we might want to use a simpler setting
as an approximation of discrete time.
When we want to put things on a computer,
we'll see the computers don't handle continuous variables
at all, and we'll need to discretize time.
So in a certain sense, we'll going back where we started,
but we'll pick up some new tools and intuition along the way.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to scale our random walk.
So we talked about our basic random walk
as being a series of steps of a stochastic process that evolves
in time where, with each new step,
the time window over which our walk has existed
gets longer and longer and longer.
What we're going to do now is keep the overall length fixed,
but let the time steps get smaller and smaller.
So rather than going farther and farther into the future,
we're going to be taking smaller and smaller steps.
We'll take advantage of linearity, our basic tool,
and expectations, one of our basic tools
for analyzing discrete processes.
But now we're going to take a limit where
we'll assign an interval delta t to the width of time
between two steps.
And we'll see that by scaling delta t and possibly the step
size, we come up with a new notion known
as Brownian motion that will be the basis for Ito processes
in finance in continuous time.
So let's begin with a standardized random variable z
with the usual properties, that its expectation is 0 and that
its variance is equal to , and that the covariance of any two
z's taken at different times is 0 unless they're at the same
point.
That is, zt and zs are independent unless t
is equal to s.
So we're going to construct a sum of z's and the origin
of time is not going to be important.
So if I let it be, say, t0, I can construct a set of steps,
and what I'm going to do is I'm going
to write this now as B because eventually it's
going to turn into Brownian motion,
so B will be for Brownian.
1 represents the size of the time step,
and big T represents the overall length of the path.
So if I'm taking unit steps on my path, then I take t steps,
so this should be t0 plus 1, t0 plus 2, t0 plus three.
So t0 is an arbitrary origin.
We could let it equal 0.
But it's important that things only
depend on time differences.
So what's the expectation?
Well, normally we would say that the expectation is equal to 0,
but we need to be careful about when
we're taking the expectation.
If we take an expectation after some of the steps
have been realized, then it's only the future steps
that have expected value 0, as we've seen.
So in the event that we take an expectation prior
to the start of our path, which I will designate in this way,
as E with a subscript t, meaning that's the time at which
the expectation is taken, provided that t is prior to t0,
then the expectation is 0.
It's just that the expectation of each of the z's is
0, 0 plus 0 plus 0 plus 0 is 0, and that's it.
Similarly, the variance is equal to big T.
But if I start computing variances
when I'm in the middle of the process, that
is, some time between the initial point
and the final point, then the only things
that contribute to the variance are things that are ahead
of my observation point.
Those are the points that have not yet been observed.
So the variance is equal to T minus the amount of time
that's already been elapsed.
So it's shortened by the amount of time elapsed.
The variance depends on the amount
of time remaining in the walk.
So whenever we take any limiting process,
whenever we do any limit, we should always
ask a few basic questions.
First, does the limit converge?
Second, if it does converge, in what sense
does the result that we obtain represent the thing that we
are starting with?
That is, how is the result representative
of the same dynamics that we started with?
And is it unique?
Might there be more than limit depending
on the way in which we take limits, particularly
in cases that might have multiple variables
or parameters?
Could there be different limits that
are obtained by taking limits in different ways?
Could we get different kinds of results?
So let's take a look at our random walk.
And I'd like to consider a few different cases,
show you a few different ways that we might
think about taking the limit.
So the first thing that we would do
is, let's just start with the most obvious.
Let delta t go to 0.
So what's delta t?
Well, let's let there be n steps.
We're going to hold big T fixed.
Big T is the overall length of time that we're interested in.
We're going to let there be n steps,
and we're going to let each step be of length delta t.
It's going to be t divided by n, the number of steps.
So if I want to let delta t go to 0, I can hold t fixed
and let n go to infinity.
Those will be equivalent.
Now, let's construct a B path, but now as I told you before,
instead of B1, T, I have the first argument here is delta t.
This is going to consist of a path of steps that represent
interval delta t in time, and there
are going to be n of them to get to my horizon.
So I'm going to let t go from to n,
and I'm going to take these z's.
What's the expectation of that sum?
0.
The expectation of each term is 0, and the sum of the 0's is 0.
What's the variance?
Well, they're going to be as usual
because these are independent.
The variance of the sum is going to be
n times the variance of an individual z.
So n times the variance of the z, the z's are standardized,
is going to give me n.
So what happens as n goes to infinity?
The variance becomes infinite.
Not too useful.
Let's try again.
Suppose we rescale the time step in the step size,
because it's easy to see what went wrong before.
We took an infinite number of steps, each of which was size ,
so of course the variance blew up.
So we should think about it, and instead of just varying
the time interval, we should, as we
let delta t get smaller and smaller,
we should also let the step size approach 0.
So let's see if we can do that.
Let's let delta t equal T/n as before,
and let's define epsilon to be our variable for our step size,
and let's let it be lambda times our unit variable
so that we can, instead of changing our beloved z's,
this way we can let lambda go to 0 to let the step size go to 0.
So what do we have?
Well, we construct a sum of n variables.
But this time, the n variables are the epsilons.
Each epsilon is lambda times z, so the lambdas
pull out in front of the sum.
So what do we have for the variance?
Well, the expectation is 0, as before.
The variance is going to be n times the variance
of the single step.
The variance of a constant times a variable
is the constant squared times the variance of the variable.
So we have n lambda squared times the variance of z,
and that gives us n lambda squared
for the variance of this process.
Now, we want the step size to go to 0,
so suppose lambda goes as 1/n, the same way
that delta t goes as 1/n.
Then we let n go to infinity.
What do we get?
Well, now we get that the variance of our process
is going to be n lambda squared.
That's going to be n over n squared.
That's going to vanish.
That is, as we let n go to 0 [CORRECTION: infinity],
it takes delta t to 0 and it takes the step size to 0
in such a way that the variance also goes to 0.
Variance 0 means it's deterministic.
There's no randomness at all.
And that would be nice, but it's not
going to be too useful for formulating
continuous-time finance.
So the problem here was the relative rate
of change of the time step and the step size, that is,
the spacing in the size of the step that we take
and how we interpret them as evolving in time.
Take a moment and see where you think we might go next.