PROFESSOR: Let's try exercising a little bit more control
over the way in which delta t goes to zero
and the step size goes to zero so that we can
get a limit which has a finite variance instead of one that's
infinite or zero.
So consider the following.
Let's let delta t be T/n as before.
This time, let's take our step size
to go as square root of delta t.
That is, let's let lambda, which is the step
size that we're going to have in our process,
be square root of T/n.
The important part isn't the T. It's the square root of 1/n
that we have here.
So as before, we construct our series B delta t,
T as consisting of a number of steps
to represent the entire time horizon of length big T.
That's our overall duration in macroscopic time.
And we're going to have n infinitesimal steps epsilon t.
Those steps are going to have this scaling.
They're going to be square root of delta t times zt.
And what about the variance?
Well, the expectation is zero as always,
but now the variance is n times the variance
of the epsilon variables of our scaled step sizes.
That means that the variance is n delta
t times the variance of z.
This variance is just equal to one,
and this here is equal to big T because n delta
t is being held fixed.
We saw that up here.
So what we get is the variance is equal to T, which is finite.
So by scaling our steps in a particular way,
by letting the step size go to zero as 1
over square root of n, or as the square root of delta t,
we can achieve a continuous limit
where delta t goes to zero and we still
end up with finite variance, not zero and not infinite.
This defines Brownian motion.
So Brownian motion is a process where
it's the limit we obtain by letting
delta t go to zero where we find that, relative to our starting
point, the endpoint is a Gaussian randomly distributed
variable with zero mean and a variance
equal to the length of time elapsed,
no matter what that time is.
Now, there are a lot of interesting properties
of Brownian motion, and we're not
going to derive all of them.
We're just going to work with the processes
to see the things that are most useful for finance.
The paths that we get that we obtain by taking this limit
are fractal in nature.
They're continuous paths, but they're nowhere differentiable,
so we're going to need to modify our rules for taking
derivatives to deal with these new paths.
Instead of looking at our usual definitions
for taking derivatives for doing calculus,
we're going to have to think about things probabilistically
and replace our usual limits by a kind of convergence
for probability distributions.
Now, we could have defined this abstractly from the beginning,
but it's useful for a lot of practical and conceptual
reasons to think about taking the limit in this way.
One of the interesting things is that this limit really
is universal.
We could have started with steps, remember,
that are drawn from any IID distribution that satisfies
the properties that we have for just our general things
for a standardized random variable.
So we're going to end up with something which has a Gaussian
distribution, regardless of where we started,
due to the central limit theorem.
Interestingly, we'll see that when
we want to do numerical approximations,
we want to do Monte Carlo option pricing, for example,
we're going to re-discretize, and it'll
look like we've come full circle,
and then we're going back to where we started.
Now, there is more than one limit possible,
and there's a literature on this, which
we're not going to go into.
I want to point out that the essential ingredient
for finance is that we have non-anticipating processes.
That is, we're taking a limit as t evolves
where we don't know what's in the future.
It's possible to take things that are symmetric,
that are agnostic between past and future,
or even things that go the other way and that anticipate
the future.
So there are some mathematical subtleties
in those different limits.
I'll point out what the rules are for the limit
that we're interested in, which is defined in just the way
that we went through right now.
So what are some of the properties of Brownian paths?
Well, we started by taking a finite path,
we broke it into infinitesimals, and we came up
with some properties that are true
of the finite macroscopic path.
So one of them is that the properties of the path
depend only on the time differences.
So if we think of X of t1 and t2 as being Brownian motion that
goes between time t1 and t2, we can think of it
as the difference between the endpoints, all right?
So the initial point doesn't matter.
The results that we have are a function
only of the elapsed time between the two.
It doesn't matter what the origin of time is.
So if we shift time forward or backward by any constant,
the properties that we have are the same.
The distribution is the same.
The variance only depends on the elapsed time
between the endpoints.
But that being said, the endpoints
don't need to be separated by a finite amount of time.
We could bring them back to where big T gets smaller
and smaller and smaller and to the point where
we get a new infinitesimal.
So we started by taking a finite path,
we chopped it into infinitesimals,
we got properties of that finite path,
and now I'm going to shrink the length of that path back
to delta t.
So this might seem as though we've done nothing
and we're going full circle, but I remind you
that our initial discrete process for any finite size
delta t could have had non-Gaussian distribution,
and the Brownian paths are Gaussian at all scales.
So if I look at a small chunk, a small piece
of infinitesimal time evolution in Brownian motion
for a Brownian path, and I'll call
that interval dB sub t just to remind you
of the time dependence.
Little subscript t is notation you'll see sometimes.
It's not particularly meaningful.
It's just a reminder of the time dependence.
This is going to be normally distributed
with mean zero, of course, and variance equal to the time
interval, which is delta t.
So if we'd started with something
that, for example, was a discrete random variable, maybe
with plus or minus one, we wouldn't
have had this property at all.
At small scales our granular thing
would have recovered the building blocks that we had.
So here we do have this universal behavior
for Brownian paths, that they're Gaussian at all time scales,
big and small.
They also are independent.
So if I look at the covariance taken
at two different times for two different infinitesimal time
intervals, I find that they're equal to zero if the times are
different, or the variance of the process
is dt if t and t prime are equal.
We can also talk about integrating the process
to go from an infinitesimal back to the finite values.
And sometimes we'll write this in integral form
as saying that BT minus B0, or I can
put the B0 on the right-hand side,
is the integral from time zero to time
big T of our infinitesimal.