PROFESSOR: So we have integral formulas
and we have differential formulas.
What are we going to do?
What are we going to use?
The answer is we're going to use them both.
Most of the time we're going to be working in differential form
and constructing what are known as stochastic differential
equations that involve things like that infinitesimal dB
that I showed you on the previous slide.
That's the small time limit of our finite Brownian motion
path.
And we'll see these stochastic differentials
involve these Gaussian random variables.
And under certain circumstances, we
can reduce them to partial differential equations,
familiar from calculus, that don't have any randomness.
And then we can apply normal techniques
that we have from the theory of partial differential equations.
However, we also sometimes use the integral form,
where we want to take a differential version
and integrate it up.
That's something that we need to think
about a little bit differently from doing integrals
in ordinary single or multiple-variable calculus
because the thing that we're integrating
is a random variable, and its randomness
depends on where it is in time.
So we can't just do a straightforward integration.
We need to think about the results of the integration
as themselves representing a probability distribution.
But an important example of where
we think about things, these integral forms
for finite values, is in doing option pricing,
and a discrete approximation to that on a computer
that we'll be seeing where we do Monte Carlo simulations.
So we might like to--
it turns out that we can define the price of an option
as an expectation over a bunch of Brownian paths
that are integrated over a finite time period.
And for that, we'll want to have our integral representation
of what the paths are and what their probability
distribution is.
Finally, let's do a quick version
of our generalized random walk because just pure Brownian
motion is a bit boring.
It's like a standardized random variable.
There's not a whole lot that we can
do with it if it only depends on time
and it doesn't have any parameters.
We'd like to include something that
could represent our old friends, return and risk.
So remember what we did with our basic random walk
to get to the generalized random walk.
We introduced parameters.
So we started with a return variable
for our log-normal process where we
took our variable z, our standardized random variable,
we multiplied it times a constant,
sigma, to represent the step size,
and we possibly added another constant mu that
represented the drift.
So I've written this as mu 0 and sigma 0
because I don't exactly know right now what
scale I want to use.
And let's think of those as being the bare parameters
for constructing a process where the time interval was fixed.
So when delta t was equal to 1, this was how we set things up.
We said that if I had bare parameters mu 0 and sigma 0,
then the random variable constructed in this way, r sub
t, was normally distributed with mean mu and variance
sigma squared.
Then, if I added a whole bunch of them
together to get some finite-length path
of multiple steps, I could go from 0
to a value of, let's say, big T, letting big T be an integer
number, by aggregating a bunch of individual time steps,
mostly T of them.
And because the logarithm of a product
is the sum of the logarithms and because the variances add
and all our usual rules, we see that by adding together big T
variables, I could get a process that was normally distributed
with parameter mu 0 t, variance sigma 0
squared T relative to the bare parameters.
Well, now we'd like to let delta t go to 0.
So how are we going to do it?
What we'd like to do is find a way
that we can pick a scaling for our parameters
such that we get finite values that we
can interpret financially when we get our Brownian motion
limit.
So we'd like to think about getting the same kind of value,
a finite path, logarithm of ST over S0, same
as we had up here, by taking the limit as delta t goes to 0.
How are we going to do that?
Well, we're going to have our path consist
of a bunch of steps, but now we're
going to let our parameters scale in the following way.
We're going to let the drift term go as mu delta t
and we're going to let the step size
term go as sigma square root of delta t.
And with that particular scaling, when we take n steps,
where n is t over delta t, as we saw before,
we'll get a finite result. So it's the same thing
that we saw.
The part that's random is the square root of delta t.
The part that's deterministic, a 1/n result is just fine.
So if we do these sums, I've got n terms here, mu delta t times,
each term is going to be identical,
times t over delta t.
That's going to give me mu times t.
Over here, I can scale out in front a sigma square root
of delta t times the sum of the z's.
But the square root of delta t grouped
with the z, if I only pull the sigma out in front,
then I have exactly my definition of my Brownian path.
So with this scaling, by introducing mu and sigma
in precisely this way where the drift and the volatility
of a process as we let delta t go to 0,
we get the finite result that we can
have stock price evolution, let's say,
represented by a random path that
has mean mu times the length of time.
And sigma integral dB is going to give us
something which is finite--
for finite times, is a random variable
that's drawn from mu of--
excuse me, from N of mu, t sigma squared t.
That is, it is going to have a mean that
grows with time linearly and a variance that
grows with time linearly and a volatility that grows
with the square root of time.
More generally, we don't need to let mu and sigma be constant.
If they depend on time, if they're deterministic functions
of time, then we could think about letting
them change slowly in time.
If they're smooth functions of time,
or actually just integrable functions of time,
we can have this general result, but provided that they're not
random variables.
So the typical case is mu and sigma are constant,
but we'll see shortly that we can generalize even
further when we introduce Ito processes.