PROFESSOR: An Ito process is like a generalized random walk,
and Ito's lemma will give us a formula for doing calculus
with Ito processes.
So an Ito process is defined to be a differential that's
a linear combination of dB, our Gaussian Brownian
random variable, plus possibly times a scale factor little b,
plus some deterministic part I'll call a dt.
If the second term were absent, this
would just be an ordinary differential,
and we could look about ordinary ways of integrating it.
But dB is going to be random, and that's going
to give us something different.
In particular, because the Brownian path
itself is not differentiable, X won't be differentiable,
and we can't take derivatives in the usual way.
If we had a function of X and t where X were a normal variable,
the usual chain rule would say that we compute
the differential of our function F of t and X
as partial of F with respect to t times
dt plus partial with respect to X dX,
and that would be it for our ordinary chain rule.
But we're going to see that there's an extra term that
gets added when we're dealing with Ito processes,
and that comes about because we can't use this rule because we
can't differentiate directly for Brownian paths.
So the idea behind the proof is we're
going to try to rewrite our familiar ideas from calculus
in a way that makes sense probabilistically.
Let me tell you up front that, number one,
I'm going to sketch out the proof
and it's not going to be rigorous.
This is going to be a somewhat heuristic proof.
And number two, the results actually
matter more than the proof.
So I'll be upfront about this.
I want you to see where it comes from.
I'd like you to see where the probability arises and the Ito
term in the modified chain rule, but this
is an area where even if you don't remember
how to derive it, if you start with Ito's lemma, the rule
that we're going to have, you can apply it successfully
without really needing to come back to the derivation.
So with a little bit of chagrin, I will admit that.
But I hope it gives you confidence that you can--
if you don't follow every detail in what we're doing,
it's not going to make any difference for the result.
So the idea is we'd like to capture the expression up here
in a case where we're dealing with probabilities.
So you can think of this as we construct
the object on the right by taking finite changes
dx, where I've written it here as delta x.
I construct this ratio F of x plus delta
x minus F of x over delta x, and then I take a limit.
And that defines the object that's on the left-hand side
that we typically call the derivative of F,
or in this case, F prime.
So what I'd like to do is I'd like
to say in probability, because the result
on the right-hand side is going to be different every time I
compute it, because x is a random variable,
F is going to be random.
I'm not going to get a concrete, definite result for F.
The sense in which I'm going to define it
is to say that I have found a sensible definition for F prime
if the probability that this function deviates
from the right-hand side goes to 0 as delta x goes to 0.
So I can write this in the following two ways.
I can write it either as saying that the probability
of a deviation-- so I've written this
as being the difference between the left and right-hand sides
above me, quantity squared, so that it's always
a positive quantity.
The probability that that's greater than 0
goes to 0 as delta x goes to 0.
In other words, they're equal.
So if a construct, F prime of x, satisfies this,
I would say I've found the derivatives.
You notice that's the same flavor,
same result in the non-probabilistic case
as the traditional formula.
I can also state it in terms of expectations.
I can say that the expectation that the squared difference
will be non-zero goes to 0.
So what are we going to do?
Well, we're going to start by writing things out,
a differential for a Taylor series,
including lots of higher-order terms,
and then we're going to only keep
terms that are of order dt.
Anything that vanishes as dt or delta t
goes to 0 faster than dt, we're going to toss out.
But what we'll need to do is keep a couple extra terms
because a few things that we might have thought
would vanish actually, it turns out, stick around.
So we're going to start with our definition of our Ito process
and just plug it in.
So I start by writing out an ordinary Taylor expansion
for a differential in terms of all
these higher-order derivatives.
There will be cross terms, partial
of F with respect to X and t, dX/dt, term in dt squared,
terms in dX cubed, dX squared, dt, and so on.
And what I'm going to do for each of these
is I can substitute in my expression here for dX, here
for dX squared, and so on.
And then what I'd like to do is think
about taking expectations of the left side
and the right-hand side and see which
terms survive as we think of dt as being an infinitesimal.
So to do that, we want to look at our basic building block.
Remember that dB is a Gaussian random variable.
So it has mean 0, it has no skewness for its third moment,
its square.
We know its variance is dt, the length of the time interval,
which is infinitesimal.
And if we want the fourth power, we
get-- whereas a normal random variable, the fourth moment is
equal to 3, that's the reason we subtract off
3 for our excess kurtosis, in the case of infinitesimals,
when you put it in the dt's, I get the result
for the fourth power.
This is the same as the usual 3 times
dt squared, which we get just on dimensional grounds.
So if I take those building blocks for dB
and I apply them to Ito processes
and ask about expectation and mean and variance and so on,
do the usual thing.
I apply linearity.
So dX is just a dt plus b dB.
Apply linearity, so it's the expectation of a sum
is the sum of the expectations.
a dt is deterministic.
It's like a constant.
So I get a dt out here.
The mean of dB is 0, so all I get
for the mean of my Ito process is
a dt, which is deterministic.
What about the square?
Well, for the square, I put in the square,
take the second power, expand it out, do the exponentials using
the formulas on the top of the screen,
and I get a squared dt plus b squared dt.
When I compute the variance, remembering
that the variance is always the expectation
of the square minus the square of the expectation,
I find that the variance of dt is just little b squared dt,
and so on.
And I can compute higher moments as well.
So let's go back to our formula for dF,
and remember that we're going to be interested in terms
that are of order dt.
The key thing to keep in mind that's
going to drive our results is that because the expectation
of dB squared is dt and the variance
or the expectation of dX squared has a dt in it
for the variance, that we can think of dB as being
like a square root of dt.
And remember, as dt goes to 0, the square root of dt
is going to be bigger than dt.
But let's just put in the terms, we'll group things together,
and then we'll take the limit and see what vanishes.
So first I've got my expression for dF.
Next we're going to substitute in for dX, for dX squared,
and so on, where we're thinking about expectations.
And the higher-order terms are going to be non-stochastic.
We can group things together, where I can now
group together coefficients of dt.
Notice that I have a dt over here, a dt here, and a dt here.
Let me take the first and last terms and group
them together here, and I'll take the middle term,
and let's just keep it in this form for the moment,
bring it down here, partial of F with respect to X times dX.
Alternatively, instead of writing things
as a function of dt and dX, I can write them
as a function of dt and dB simply
by using the definition of dX.
So either way, in either this form or in the bottom form,
I have an expression for dF that I can work with.
So either of these two forms, depending on our applications,
will be useful.
The point about looking at the last one
is look at its structure.
You notice that it's of the form something times dt
plus something else times dB.
That's just an Ito process.
So the differential of F when F is a function of an Ito process
is also an Ito process, and that's why these are useful,
because they're closed when we take differentials.
We get more Ito processes.
Here's the heuristic.
It's the easy way to keep track of things
without doing a lot of Taylor expansions.
If every time you see a dB squared,
you think of it as being a dt and every time you
see a dX squared, you think of it-- remember,
this is the pure, standardized random variable.
This is with a scale factor in it.
If every time you see a dX squared, you replace it
by little b squared dt, you'll basically
get the right answers.
So the differential that we have has one extra term
beyond the usual chain rule, OK?
So this is our result from the previous page.
When we take a look at this expression here,
we see that this term dt--
this term-- get my pointer working.
This term dt and this term dX are the usual chain rule,
but this one here is something new.
So writing it in standard form, we have Ito's lemma in the box,
and I'll circle it again in red.
So this is worth getting to know very, very well.
It says that the differential of a function of X,
where X is an Ito process, is partial of F with respect
to t dt, plus partial of F with respect to X dX
plus a new term that involves the second partial derivative
with respect to X squared, but it's multiplied by dt.
So we've seen that the differential
of a function of an Ito process is itself an Ito process.
And this formula is Ito's lemma.