PROFESSOR: In this video, we will demonstrate
how to value a leveraged firm with a loan that requires
constant interest payments.
Consider a firm that generates $10 million
in earnings before interest and taxes each year,
in perpetuity with no risk.
Suppose the firm takes a perpetual loan on which it
is required to pay $8 million interest each year
in perpetuity.
Assume that the corporate income tax rate is 25%,
and the risk-free rate is 2%.
What is the value of this firm?
To find the value of this firm, we
will apply the Adjusted Present Value Method.
The levered firm value equals to the unlevered firm
value plus the present value of interest actuals.
Since the firm generates safe perpetual earnings
of $10 million, the value of the unlevered firm
is the present value of the risk-free perpetuity
with after-tax earnings generated every year.
Given the tax rate of 25% and the risk-free rate of 2%,
we find that the unlevered firm value equals to $375 million.
Next, let's find the present value of interest tax shields.
Since the firm generates $10 million in risk-free earnings,
it has enough funds to pay interest
each year with certainty.
This means that the debt is risk-free,
and that the tax shields generated by this debt
are risk-free as well.
Annual tax shield equals to the tax rate,
which is 25%, times the annual interest
expense, which is $8 million.
The present value of this stream of tax shields
equals to the present value of the risk-free perpetuity.
Given the risk free rate of 2%, we
find that the present value of tax shields is $100 million.
Adding the value of the unlevered firm
to the value of interest tax shields,
we find that the value of this firm equals to $475 million.
Note that the interest tax shields
account for 21% of this firm's total value.
This is because annual interest expense is large,
and because these tax shields are safe,
which results in the high present value.