INSTRUCTOR: So part C of this question asks us--
how much of the wealth growth in B is
due to return earned in the previous return?
Well, to answer this question let's
first compute the total return that we
would earn just on the principal amount that we invested.
The annual return on the principal amount is just 10.2%
times x.
And since we're earning this over a 20-year period,
this would be just 20 times 10.2 times x.
So our wealth would grow just 2 times
if we were earning a return just on the principal amount
invested.
But in B, we computed that our wealth grows 7 times, so 7x.
So the difference between this 2x and 7x
is the return that we earn on previously earned return.
And in this case, it's very clear
to see that most of our wealth that we are generating
on our investment is due to return that we are earning on
previously earned return.