INSTRUCTOR: What would happen if we invested the initial amount
x into the stock market and the stock market
during this time period on average produced 10.2%
annual return?
Well, the future value of this x invested at 10.2% for 20 years
would equal to x times 1 plus 10.2% raised
to the power of 20.
And that would equal to 7x.
Therefore, the initial amount of x would grow to 7 times, 7x,
over this 20-year time period.
So questions A and B give us the following information.
If we invest x at 5.65% annual rate of return over 20 years,
our wealth would grow 3 times.
But if we invest it at 10.2% annual return,
our wealth would grow 7 times.
So therefore, relatively small differences
in annual interest rates may imply large differences
in wealth over a long time periods.