PROFESSOR: What is the average annual rate of return
that we earned on this purchase?
Let us denote by x the purchase price of this apartment
that we paid for 20 years ago, and by 3x its present value,
because it's tripled since the time we purchased it.
To help us think in terms of present and future value
in this particular problem, let's shift the timeline 20
years to present, and denote the starting point by t
equal to zero, and this ending point by t equal to 20.
Then x times 1 plus r raised to the power of 20
would be the future value of this x in 20 years from now,
and it has to equal to its actual future value
right now which is 3x.
The only thing we have to do here
is to solve this equation for r.
Well x is, of course, irrelevant here,
so it cancels out from this equation.
And then we are left with one plus r equal to 3
raised to the power 1/20.
Solving this equation gives us the interest rate of 5.65%.
So the answer to this question is
that the average annual rate of return that we earned
on this purchase is 5.65%.