PROFESSOR: In this question, we asked,
what is our expected rental revenue in year 1,
2, 3, and 4 in nominal terms?
Recall that our current revenue in year 0 is $650,000.
Then the nominal revenue in year 1
equals to the current revenue multiplied
by 1 plus nominal growth rate.
Now recall that the nominal growth rate equals to--
and can be found from the following equation.
So 1 plus nominal growth rate equals
to 1 plus real growth rates multiplied by 1
plus the rate of inflation.
Recall that the nominal growth rate equals to 3%.
And inflation in this question equals to 2.5%.
So this gives me 1.05575.
And from this I get the nominal growth rates of 5.575%.
And now this is the nominal growth rate
that we can use to find normal revenue in years 1, 2, 3,
and 4.
In year one, nominal revenue would
equal to $650,000 multiplied by 1 plus 5.575%.
And this equals to $686,237.50.
This number is the same as the one
we found in part C of this question above.
Now continuing this logic, nominal revenue in year 2
is going to be current revenue multiplied by 1
plus nominal growth rate squared, again, because we
receive this revenue in year 2.
And therefore, it grows for 2 years at this growth rate gn.
And this equals $650,000 multiplied by 1
plus 5.575% squared.
This equals to $724,495.24.
Nominal revenue in year 3 equals to current revenue multiplied
by 1 plus nominal growth rate raised to the power 3,
which again equals $650,000 multiplied
by our nominal growth rate raised the power 3.
And this equals to $764,885.85.
So finally, nominal revenue in year 4
would equal to the current revenue multiplied
by 1 plus nominal growth rate raised to the power 4.
And this equals to again $650,000 multiplied by 1 plus
5.575% raised to the power 4 now.
And this equals to $807,528.24.
So these numbers together give us nominal revenue
that we expect to receive from renting out our property in
years 1, 2, 3, and 4.