PROFESSOR: Next, let us find the present value
of your real rental revenue over the next four years.
The present value would equal to the real revenue
that you receive in each of the four years discounted
to present at the real discount rate.
So real revenue in year 1 divided
by 1 plus real discount rate, then real revenue in year 2
discounted to present, again, at the real discount rate.
So here, of course, we have to raise this to a power of 2,
because this revenue occurs in year 2.
So, therefore, this is the appropriate way
to find the present value of that exact real revenue
that we'll get in year 2.
Then real revenue in year 3, divided by 1 plus real discount
rate raised to the power of 3.
And finally, the real revenue in year 4,
divided again by 1 plus r--
that is real discount rate, raised to power of 4.
So putting this together, we get $669,500 divided by 1 plus 6%,
plus $689,585 divided by 1 plus 6% squared,
plus $710,272.55 divided by 1 plus 6%
raised to the power of 3.
And the final real revenue in year 4,
which is $731,580.73, divided by 1 plus 6%,
raised to power of 4.
Altogether, this gives us the present value of $2,421,171.
So the present value of your rental revenue
that you expect to receive over the next four years
is $2.4 million.