PROFESSOR: So what is the return on this bond?
Well, let's start with the definition
of what expected return is.
It is the expected payoff that we
get from this bond minus its price divided by its price.
We already know the price of this bond, which is $96.
So what's left to find is the expected payoff
that we get from investing into this bond.
Well, the expected payoff can be found
as the probability of the first state, which
is 0.3, times the payoff that we get
from this bond in this first state, $100.
Plus the probability of the second state, which
is 0.4, times the payoff that we get
from this bond in the second state, which is $100.
Plus the probability of the third state, which is 0.3,
multiplied by the payoff that we get
from this bond in the third state, which is $100.
So adding this up gives us $100.
And it's very intuitive, one to expect the payoff on this bond
is $100, because in each of the three states, we get $100.
So no matter which state is realized, we get exactly $100.
So therefore, the expected payoff is just $100.
So now we know the expected payoff.
We know the price of the bond.
So we put them back into the return equation.
And this gives us $100 minus $96 divided by $96,
and that equals 4.17%.
Note that this return of 4.17% is guaranteed.
Why?
Because there is no uncertainty in what payoff
we will get from holding this bond next period.
We're going to get $100, regardless of which state
of nature is realized.
So in this sense, this return is risk-free.
Note that in the question, we didn't ask
what is the expected return.
We just asked what is the return on the bond.
Because again, this return is guaranteed to us.