PROFESSOR: Now suppose that a real annual growth rate of 3%
will continue over the next four years.
The inflation is also expected to remain
at 2.5% over the next four years.
Assume that the appropriate real discount rate is 3%.
What is your expected rental revenue
in year 1, 2, 3, and 4 in real terms?
Let us solve this question.
We already found what is real revenue in year one, which
is our current revenue, $650,000 multiplied by 1
plus real growth rate, which is 3%, which gives us $669,500.
Now to find real revenue in a year 2,
we're taking the current revenue in the year 0
and multiplying it by 1 plus real growth rate
gr squared, because this revenue grows
at this rate gr for two years.
So this is $650,000 multiplied by 1
plus 3% squared, which gives me $689,585.
Similarly, real revenue in year 3
equals current revenue multiplied
by 1 plus gr raised to the power of 3,
which is $650,000 multiplied by 1
plus 3% raised to the power of 3, which gives us $710,272.55.
Finally, extending this logic all the way to a year 4,
we get current revenue in year 0 multiplied by 1
plus real growth rate raised to the power of 4, which, again,
equals to $650,000 multiplied by 1
plus 3% raised to the power of 4, which gives me $731,580.73
So altogether, these numbers give us real revenue
in years 1, 2, 3, and 4.