PROFESSOR: In this question, we're
given a state space model that consists of three states.
All three states are equally likely.
The first question asks us to find the price
and expected return on asset x that
pays off $100 in the first state, $80 in the second state,
and $100 in the third state.
So let's start with the price of this asset first.
So the price would equal to the payoff
that we get from this asset in state number one multiplied
by the price of the first state plus the payoff
that we get in the second state multiplied
by the price of the second state plus the payoff
that we get in the third state multiplied
by the price of the third state.
This gives us $100 times 0.2 plus $80 times 0.55
plus $100 times 0.2 and gives us $84.
So the price of this asset x right now is $84.
Now, the second part of the question
asks us to find the expected return.
To find expected return, the first thing we need to find
is the expected payoff that we're expecting
to get from this asset.
Let's find it.
So to find expected payoff, we are multiplying the payoffs
that we get in each of the states by their probabilities.
In this case, all three states are equally likely,
so probability of the first state is 1/3,
second state is 1/3 as well, and the third state is 1/3 as well.
So therefore, the expected payoff
equals to $100 multiplied by 1/3 plus $80 multiplied by 1/3
plus $100 multiplied by 1/3.
This gives us $93.33.
Now, to find expected the return,
we're taking this expected payoff, $93.33,
minus the current price of the asset divided
by the current price of this asset, which is $84.
So 93.33 minus 84 divided by 84--
this gives us 11.11%.
So the expected return on this asset x is 11.11%.