PROFESSOR: In part B of this question,
we are asked again to pick between two options.
Option one, which is the same, it gives us $10,000 today,
and option two gives us $18,000 in 10 years.
To choose between these two options,
we are going to compare their value at one point in time.
We're going to compare their value at present.
The present value of option one is just $10,000.
The present value of option two is $18,000
received 10 years from now, discounted
to present at 8% rate, which gives us $8,337.
Since the present value of option one
is greater than the present value of option 2,
in this case, we would prefer to take
$10,000 right now as opposed to waiting 10 years
and receiving $18,000.
To develop intuition, let's look at this problem
from a different angle.
Let's take this $10,000 and invest it
in an asset that has similar risk that our sisters promise,
and therefore offers the same 8% rate of return.
If we do so, in the future we will get $10,000 multiplied
by 1 plus 8% raised to the power of 10, which gives us $21,590.
So the future value of $10,000 invested at 8% for 10 years
is $21,590.
This is a higher amount then what
we would receive from our sister in 10 years-- $18,000.
So therefore, we are better off taking $10,000 today
and investing it at an 8% rate and receiving $21,590.
10 years from today.