PROFESSOR: Question c: what is your expected rental revenue
next year in nominal terms?
Well, nominal revenue in year one
equals to the current revenue multiplied
by 1 plus nominal growth rate.
But the question does not give us
nominal growth rate directly.
So we have to compute it.
1 plus nominal growth rate equals to 1
plus real growth rate multiplied by the rate of inflation.
So we can use this equation to plug it into here
and, therefore, the nominal revenue year 1
is going to be equal to revenue now multiplied
by 1 plus real growth rates times 1
plus the rate of inflation.
Plugging in the numbers, we get $650,000 multiplied by 1
plus 3% multiplied by 1 plus 2.5%,
which gives us $686,237.50.