PROFESSOR: In this question, we're
given a state-space model that has
three states and three assets currently traded in the market.
Asset 1 is a riskless bond with the current price of $95.
It pays $100 in each of the three states.
Asset 2 is a stock.
Its current price is $150.
And it pays $250 in state 1, nothing in state 2,
and $500 in state 3.
And finally, asset number 3 is another stock that is currently
priced and traded at $100.
And it pays $0 in states 1 and 2.
And it pays $500 in the state 3.
The question is, what are the state prices?
To answer this question, let's start
by writing down the pricing equation that
connects the payoff that we get from an asset with the state
prices.
So recall that in question two, we
were working with the following equation.
So the price of any asset equals to the payoff
that asset pays in the first state multiplied by the state
price of that state.
And similarly, what that asset pays
in the second state times the price of that second state,
plus here we have three states in total,
so we have the third state as well.
So now we can write down the prices
of each of our three assets as the function of the state
prices and what these assets pay in each of the states.
So let's start with the riskless bond.
So we get 95 equals to phi 1 multiplied by 100
plus phi 2 multiplied by 100 plus phi 3 multiplied by 100.
Now for the second asset, or for our first stock,
we can write down the following equation.
So its current price is $150.
And it pays $250 in the first state.
So it's phi 1 multiplied by 250.
It doesn't pay anything in the second state,
so it's going to be phi 2 times 0, which is 0.
Plus phi 3-- and I can put 0 here--
phi 3 times 500.
And finally, for the asset number 3, or the second stock,
we can write down the pricing equation
for that stock, which is 100 equals
to phi 3 multiplied by 500.
And so the remaining, phi 1 times 0 is 0.
And phi 2 times 0 is 0 as well.
So now we have this system of equations with three unknowns.
It's a very easy system of equations to solve.
So from the last equation, we get phi 3 that equals 0.2.
We can plug this phi 3 into the second equation.
And by solving that equation, you
could verify that phi 1 would equal to 0.2 as well.
And finally, we can plug phi 3 and phi 1 into equation 1
and solve that equation for phi 2.
And so if we do that, we find that phi 2--
and I will write it down here--
so phi 2 would equal 0.55.
So altogether, we get that the state prices, in this case,
equal to--
so phi 1 equals to 0.2, phi 2 equals 0.55,
and phi 3 equals 0.2 as well.
So this is the set of the state prices
in this state-space model.
If we were to use the state prices to price these assets
again given their payoffs, the way we have priced assets
in question two, we would have found
that each of these assets, so the riskless bond, its price
would be $95.
The price of stock 1 would be $150.
And the price of stock 2 would be $100.
So altogether, this question teaches you
how to find the state prices from the given
prices of traded assets.