PROFESSOR: The last part of this question
asks us to find the present value
of our nominal rental revenue over the next four years.
Let us start this question by finding the nominal discount
rate, which we will have to use to discount
the nominal rental revenue back to present.
We have already done this in part D of this question.
So let me remind you.
1 plus nominal discount rate equals to 1
plus real discount rate multiplied by 1
plus the rate of inflation.
Recall that the real discount rate is 6%.
And the rate of inflation is 2.5%.
Multiplying these two quantities gives us 1.0865.
And therefore from this equation,
we obtain that the nominal discount rate equals to 8.65%.
Now we can find the present value
of our nominal rental revenue.
Let us start by writing down what this present value should
be.
Let me write it down in a more compact way.
So it's the sum of all nominal revenue in every year,
i, where i is going to go from 1 to 4,
discounted to present by using the nominal discount rate.
So 1 plus r nominal, raised to the power i.
And so now we can expand this.
And we can use the nominal revenue
for every year 1, 2, 3, and 4 that we
found in the previous part of this question.
So the nominal revenue in year one is 686,237.50.
We're discounting this to present at 8.65%,
plus the second nominal revenue, which is $724,495.24 .
We're dividing it by 1 plus our nominal discount rate
8.65% raised to the power 2, again,
because this revenue occurs in year 2, plus continuing.
Nominal revenue in a year 3 is 764,885.85, divided by 1
plus 8.65% raised to the power 3,
plus the final nominal rental revenue 807,528.24 divided by 1
plus 8.65% raised to the power 4.
Now adding this all together gives us $2,421,171.
Notice that this value equals exactly the same present value
that we found in part F of this question.
And this is the key lesson of this exercise
is that the present value, whether you
are operating in nominal terms or in real terms, should equal.
If it doesn't, you have made a mistake somewhere
along the way.