PROFESSOR: In this question, we're given two options.
We are offered $10,000 today or $11,500 in 1 year from now.
To compare the two options, we have to compare them
at one point in time.
The easiest way to do that is to compare them as of now.
What is the present value of option 1,
and what is the present value of option 2?
So the present value of option 1 is trivially just the value
that we offer today.
It's $10,000.
Now, the present value of option 2,
we have to find what is the present value of $11,500
that we are receiving one year from today as of now.
And for that we are given an interest rates of 8%.
So the present value of this payment that we receive
one year from now is $10,648.
So the present value of the second option
is greater than the present value of the first option.
So therefore, we should prefer the second option.
Let's try to understand why in this question
we are preferring option 2 to option 1.
Let's look at the interest rate of 8%.
This interest rate represents our opportunity cost
of capital, which means what the rate of return we
can earn on investments that have similar risk
as our sister's promise.
So let's consider the following hypothetical scenario.
Let's take $10,000 from our sister
today and invest it in one of the assets that
have similar risk and therefore gives us
expected rate of return of 8%.
Then the future value of this investment
will be $10,000 that we invest today and 8% rate
that we earn at the end of this year, which gives us $10,800.
So in this hypothetical scenario,
if we take $10,000 today, at the end of the year,
we're going to get $10,800, which
is lower that what we were going to get from our sister, which
is $11,500.
And because these two options have the same risk
and one gives us more money than the other one,
we should be preferring the second option.