PROFESSOR: Let's look at state prices again.
The price of state two is .55.
And the price of states one and three is just 0.2.
So the price of state two is much higher
than the price of states one and three.
This means investors are willing to pay a higher price
to receive $1 in state two.
Put differently, investors value of money in state
two more than they do in states one and three.
State two, for example, can be an economic recession.
In recessions, many economic agents
may receive lower income.
For example, workers may receive lower wages,
firms may earn lower profits, therefore, a security
that pays money in bad states of the world, typically
has higher prices, because money in bad states is more valuable.
Assets x and y pay off the same amount in state one.
However, asset x pays off $80 in state two
and $100 in state three.
While asset y pays off $100 in state two and only $80
in state three.
So therefore, y pays $20 more in the bad state,
while x pays off $20 more in good state.
So intuitively, this implies that the price of y
should be higher than the price of x.
And because asset y pays more when money is more valuable,
investors are willing to accept a lower rate of return
from investing in asset y compared to asset x.
Indeed, as we have seen above, the expected return on asset x
is 11.11%, while in asset y, it is only 2.56%.