PROFESSOR: In this problem, we're given state prices.
And we're asked to find the price of the bond.
To find the price of the bond, we
have to multiply the payout that we get from this bond
by their state prices.
We have only two states in this particular case.
So, therefore, the price of the bond equals to the payoff
that we get in the first state, multiplied
by the price of that state, plus the payout that we
get in the second state, times the price of that second state.
It's $100 times 0.35 plus $100 times 0.55.
That gives us $90.
So the price of this bond today is $90.
Notice this is a riskless bond.
So one shortcut that we can take here
is just simply to add up state prices, 0.35 plus 0.55--
that gives us 0.9--
and multiply by the payoff that we
get from this bond, $100 in both states.
So that would give us $90.