PROFESSOR: The second question asks us to find the price
and expected return of asset Y. Asset Y
pays off $100 in the first state,
$100 in the second state, and $80 in the third state.
Let's start with the price.
The price of asset Y equals to the payoff
that we get from this asset in the first state,
$100, times the price of the first state, 0.2,
plus the payoff that we get in the second state, also $100,
times the price of the second state,
0.55, plus $80 that we get in the third state times the price
of the third state, 0.2.
This gives us the price of this asset, $91.
Now, to find the expected return,
we again start with the expected payoff
that we get on this asset.
The expected payoff would equal to the payoff
that it would get in each of the three
states times the probabilities of each of the three states.
Because each of the three states are equally likely,
the probability is, again, 1/3.
So putting this all together gives us $93.33.
Now, notice that the expected payoff on asset Y, $93.33,
is exactly the same as the payoff of that we computed
on asset X in part A. This is due to the fact
that the payoffs from assets X and Y are similar in the sense
that both of them give us $100 in the first state.
But in the second state, asset X pays off $80,
while Y pays off $100.
And in the third state, asset X pays off $100,
while Y pays off $80.
Because of the symmetry and because of the fact
that each of these states are equally likely
and occur with likelihood 1/3, the expected payoff of asset X
is the same as the expected payoff of asset Y.
So finally, to find the expected return on asset Y,
we're taking the expected payoff, $93.33,
we're subtracting the price of asset Y, which is $91,
and dividing it by the price of this asset Y, $91.
This gives us 2.56%.
So the expected return on asset Y is 2.56%.