PROFESSOR: Now what is the expected return on the stock?
Well, again, by definition the expected return
is the expected payoff minus the price of the stock divided
by the price of the stock.
Well, we need to find the expected payoff
from investing into the stock.
Well, it's going to be the probability of the first states
0.3 times the payoff that we get from the stock
in the first state, 120, plus probability of the second state
0.4, multiplied by the payoff that we
get in the second state, $75, plus the probability
of the third state, which is 0.3 times the pay that we
get from the stock in this third state, $130.
So this gives us $105, which is the expected payoff that we get
from investing into the stock.
Well, the expected return is then 105 minus 80 which
current price of the stock divided
by 80, which gives us 31.25%.
So, therefore, the expected return
from investing into the stock is 31.25%.