PROFESSOR: Question d, what is the present value
in nominal rental revenue next year?
The present value would equal to the nominal revenue
that you receive in the year one, discounted to present
at the nominal discount rate.
Now the question does not give us directly
the nominal discount rate.
So we have to find it.
To find a nominal discount rate, we use the following equation.
1 plus the nominal discount rate would equal to 1
plus real discount rate multiplied by 1
plus the rate of inflation.
Plugging this equation into here,
we'll get nominal revenue in the year 1 divided by 1
plus real discount rates multiplied
by 1 plus rate of inflation, which gives us
$686,237.50 divided by 1 plus 6%, which is the real discount
rate multiplied by 1 plus 2.5%, which is the rate of inflation,
which gives us $631,604.
Now notice the present value that we get in this question
is exactly the same as we've gotten in part
b of this question.
The present values, of course, should not
be affected, whether we're dealing
with nominal or real units.
If we're discounting nominal revenue or the nominal discount
rate and real revenue of the real discount rate,
we should be getting exactly the same answer.
If we don't, it means we have made a mistake somewhere.