PROFESSOR: Now, let's do cash out refinance.
So instead of lowering our monthly mortgage payments,
we will continue paying the same amount as we paid before.
But because this new mortgage is cheaper,
we will be able to borrow a larger amount from a bank
and pay the existing loan and use the remaining
cash for other purposes, such as, as the question states,
buying a new car or doing something else.
So the question is, given this new cheaper rate, how much we
can borrow if we were to continue paying the same amount
that we paid before on our old mortgage.
So the answer is simply this.
So this question is asking us to find the present value
of our old payment.
Recall that our old payment was $2,121.88.
At the new monthly rate, which was 0.375%.
So 0.375%.
I'm just using the annuity formula
to find the present value of this amount.
1 minus 1 divided by 1 plus this interest rate
raised to the power of 240.
Recall that this is a 20 year loan on which we
are paying monthly payments, so there are 240 months.
And by computing this amount--
this is the present value of how much we will be able to borrow.
This gives me $335,395.29.
We will take this new loan from the bank
and pay $300,000 on our existing mortgage to the other bank,
therefore leaving ourselves with $35,395.29.