PROFESSOR: Jeff Bezos recently made an announcement
that he would donate $10 billion to combat climate change.
Suppose that he plans to establish
a foundation to which he will pledge the entire amount of $10
billion.
Every year his foundation will distribute funds
to organizations that fight climate change.
Let's assume that the foundation will invest funds
into financial assets that will on average generate
nominal annual rate of return of 8%.
Now the first question is asking us
if Bezos' foundation wants to be able to distribute funds
in perpetuity and if they plan to distribute the same dollar
amount each year, what will be the annual distribution amount?
Now we will assume that the first distribution happens
in exactly one year from now.
Notice that the distribution stream from the foundation
represents perpetuity.
Suppose that the annual distribution equals
to C dollars, then the present value of the stream of payments
can be written as present value equals to C divided by 1
plus r, plus C divided by 1 plus r squared, plus C divided by 1
plus r cubed, and so forth.
Remember this is a perpetuity, so this is an infinite stream
of cash flow.
We have learned in the lecture that the present value
of such perpetuity equals to C divided by r.
Now the question gives us the present value
of this perpetuity.
This is the amount of money that Jeff Bezos
pledged to the foundation, which is $10 billion.
Now given the interest rate of 8%
we can solve this equation for the annual payment
amount, which would be C equals present value
multiplied by interest rate r or in this case $10 billion
multiplied by 8%, which would be equal to $800 million.