PROFESSOR: Let's start solving this question
by first computing monthly interest rates
on the old and the new loan.
Recall that, on the old loan, we're
paying 6.5% effective annual rate.
To find the monthly rate, let's start
with the following equation.
So 1 plus effective annual rate would equal to 1
plus monthly rate raised to the power of 12.
From this equation, we can find monthly rate
by just inverting it.
So it's going to be, 1 plus effective annual rate
raised to the power of 1 over 12 minus 1.
So it's going to be 1 plus 6% raised to the power of 1
over 12 minus 1.
And this would give me 0.487%.
So this is the monthly rate that we're paying on the old loan.
To find the monthly interest rate on the new loan,
note that the new loan is quoted to us as annual percentage rate
monthly component.
So therefore, for us to find the monthly rate, all we have to do
is, we're taking this monthly component APR
and we're dividing it by 12, which is 4.5% divided by 12.
This would be 0.375%.
So this is the interest--
monthly interest on the new loan, and up here
was the monthly interest rate that we're
paying on the old loan.
So you can already see that we got a better
deal on the new loan.
So therefore, refinancing the old mortgage
with the new mortgage would lower our monthly payments.
Now, let's find monthly payments on the old and the new loan
and compare them.
First, let's start with the old loan.
So the current value, the present value
of the mortgage that we have is $300,000.
So this must equal to the monthly payment
that we're making--
and I will denoted it as c o--
as the monthly payment on the old mortgage, divided by r m.
So this would be the rate--
the monthly rate on the old mortgage
multiplied by 1 minus 1 divided by 1 plus r
m raised to the power 240.
240 because we have 20 years left
on the life of this mortgage.
And so for us to find our monthly payment, all
we have to do, we have to invert this equation.
So it's going to be $300,000 and then
we'll divide it by 1 divided by r m, 1 minus 1
divided by 1 plus r m, raised to the power of 240.
If we solve this equation by plugging in the interest
rate of 0.487%, the monthly interest rate,
we will get c o, which is the, again, monthly payment
on the old mortgage of $2,121.88.
Now, let's do the same for the new loan.
So I can write down the same equation.
So it's the same if we were to refinance.
Right now, we need to still raise
the present value of $300,000 so that the proceeds
from the new loan can be used to repay the old loan.
And that again would be equal to our monthly payments.
And I will denote it as c n, to denote
the new payment, the new loan, divided by r m 1 minus 1
plus r m also raised to the power of 240.
So now this r m is the interest rate on the new loan.
And I can find c n, similarly, by just
inverting this equation.
So c n is going to equal to $300,000 divided
by 1 divided by r m, 1 minus 1 plus 1 r m
raised to the power of 240.
And so if we compute-- if we plug-in
r m that equals to 0.375%, we're going
to get monthly payment on this loan of $1,897.95.
Now we can see that by refinancing the old loan
with the new loan, we're saving the difference
between these two amounts.
What we used to pay on the old loan and our new
lower monthly payments.
The difference is about $223.93.
So this is by how much we're lowering our monthly payment
on the mortgage.