PROFESSOR: So the payoff matrix is
how we think about what it's possible to create.
And when we think about looking at derivatives markets, when
we think about many problems, business problems, managing
risks, looking for insurance, covering and hedging
risky positions, we're often looking for ways
to construct a portfolio of financial instruments
or contracts that will balance certain risks that we have
that are either part of an investment portfolio
that consists of securities, or possibly other business
and financial and corporate risks that
occur in different states of the world.
So this is the problem of risk management.
We want to ask, can we find portfolios
of financial instruments that meet desired payoff
profiles that might either satisfy an urge for gambling
in different states of the world,
but more commonly in the financial industry context.
We're looking for combinations of assets
that can match certain exposures or risks that
might occur in different states of the world.