PROFESSOR: In the next question, we
are asked to form the following portfolio.
So we will mix or we'll invest 60% of our wealth
into stock A and 40% into stock B.
So we're going to form this portfolio which I will refer to
as P, which again invest 60% in a 40% in b.
The question asks us to find the expected return
on this portfolio, P.
Let's do the definition of expected return
for a portfolio.
Expected return on a portfolio would equal to the weight
that we'd invest in the first stock times the expected return
on this stock, plus weight that we'd
invest in the second stock times the expected return
on the second stock.
Now, if we've had more --
you could see that this is just a simple linear function --
so if we had more stocks in our portfolio,
we could just continue writing the following linear
expression.
So now since we have only two stocks
we can plug in the weights and the corresponding expected
returns.
So weights in a 60% expected return 20.
40% in b and it's expected return is 15%.
So if we compute this, this will give us 18%.
So the expected return on this portfolio P is 18%.