PROFESSOR: Suppose that you have $20,000 that you
would like to invest.
You're very bullish on the future of clean energy,
and you found the following exchange traded fund, or ETF,
that you would like to invest--
iShares clean energy ETF, the ticker symbol ICLN.
But you are so bullish on the clean energy
that not only do you want to invest
all your wealth into this ETF, you
would want to borrow and invest borrowed money into this ETF
as well.
Your broker allows you to borrow up to $45,000,
giving you wealth of $20,000.
So what do you will do is that you
will borrow the full amount of $45,000,
and you will invest all of it into this ETF.
The first question asks us, what is
the weight on this ETF on ICLN in your portfolio?
By definition, the weight in your portfolio on ICLN would be
your position in this ETF, which is $20,000--
this is your initial wealth--
plus your borrowed funds divided by your total wealth,
or often referred to as the equity of your portfolio.
So your position divided by your wealth, by $20,000.
So this gives us 325%.
So the weight on this ETF in your portfolio is 325%.
We can also compute the weights that you have on the loan,
or the borrowed funds in your portfolio.
So you borrowed $45,000, hence a negative sign,
divided by your wealth.
So this gives us negative 225%.
Now, this indeed is a portfolio, because if we add up
your weight in this borrowed funds
plus your weight in this ETF, this gives us 100%.
And so recall that by definition,
weights in the portfolio have to add up to 100%.