PROFESSOR: Now let's assume that Portfolios P and Q get
combined.
They get combined into a new portfolio.
And we'll call this portfolio R.
So for example, imagine that P and Q are trusts
and they just combined and merged.
And they combined their assets.
And so all of these assets get combined into portfolio R.
And now the question is, what are
the new weights of these individual assets
in this new portfolio, in the merged portfolio,
R. To find the weights of individual assets
in this new Portfolio R, first, let's
find the total value of Portfolio R.
So we're simply adding up the value
of each of these individual assets
or because we knew the value of Portfolio P
and the value of Portfolio Q so $75,000 and $70,000
respectively.
So the total value of this combined portfolio right
now is $75,000 plus $70,000.
That's $145,000.
So that's the total value of Portfolio R.
To find the weights, we're simply
adding up the weights of individual positions
in Portfolios P and Q and dividing it
by the total value of the new portfolio.
So $25,000 for SPY in Portfolio P
plus $10,000 for SPY in Portfolio Q.
So that's $35,000 divided by $145,000.
And that's 0.24.
Same exact process for the remaining three assets.
So for the short term treasury ETF $35,000
here plus $10,000 here divided by $145,000.
That's 0.31.
For emerging markets ETF, $15,000 here, $30,000 here,
divided by $145,000, also 0.31.
And for the mortgage backed securities ETF, $0 here,
$20,000 here divided by $145,000.
That gives us 0.14.
And so these are the weights of each
of the four individual securities
in this new portfolio, combined portfolio, are.
Again, just to make sure that we haven't done arithmetic
mistakes somewhere, to make sure that that didn't happen,
we add up the weights of individual assets
and just make sure that it all adds up to 1.
And in this case, it indeed all adds up to 1.
So this portfolio looks OK.
So all of the weights add up to 1.
And this is how you compute portfolio weights given
the position and individual assets in a portfolio.