PROFESSOR: Now in the second part of the question,
we have the same investor with the same utility function.
But now, she has a choice between the following two
lotteries.
Lottery A is the same exact lottery
we had in the first part of this question,
and Lottery B. So a Lottery A with probability 1/2
pays $1,100 and probably 1/2 pays $900.
Now lottery B with probability 1/2
pays $1,250, with probability 1/2 pays $750.
Now the question is which of these two lotteries
this investor will choose.
Now let's compute the expected utility that this investor will
get from Lottery A and Lottery B.
We've already done this calculation for Lottery A.
So the expected utility equals to 1/2 the utility of $1,100
plus the other half utility of $900.
This gave us 31.58.
Now let's do the same calculation for Lottery B.
So the expected utility equals to 1/2 utility
of $1,250 plus the other half utility of $750.
So the utility function, again, is the square root function.
So it's 1/2 square root of $1,250
plus 1/2 square root of $750.
That gives us 31.37.
So given these two expected utilities,
which of the two lotteries our investor prefers?
Well, since Lottery A gives her a higher expected utility
compared to Lottery B, then this investor
is going to prefer Lottery A to Lottery B.
The reason for this choice is exactly the same reason
as we had in the previous part of this question.
Both of these lotteries A and B offer
the same exact expected payoff.
So it's $1,000 in both cases.
You could see the symmetry of these outcomes.
However, there is more uncertainty
and more risk in the Lottery B because the outcome
is more dispersed.
So it's $1,250 or $750 while the first one is either
$1,100 or $900.
And just because this investor is, again, risk averse,
his utility function is concave, this investor
would prefer to take less risky lottery
that offers the same expected payoff.
And so therefore, she chooses Lottery A
in this particular case.