PROFESSOR: Now suppose that the correlation
between returns on Stock A and Stock B
increases from 0.2 to 0.6.
We're going to keep the same Portfolio P that invests 60
into A and 40 into B. And we will
try to compute the expected return on this portfolio
and the standard deviation.
So first, let's answer the following question.
Does the fact that correlation changed from 0.2 to 0.6
affect the returns on this portfolio?
The answer is that it doesn't.
The expected return on the portfolio
only depends on the weights that we
put in the corresponding stocks and on the expected
returns on the stocks.
It does not depend on how returns on different assets
could vary within that portfolio.
So therefore, expected return in this case
stays the same as it was before.
In particular, it is 18%.
Now standard deviation, on the other hand,
for the Portfolio P, is affected because if we
look at the formula for the variance of Portfolio P,
we see that it obviously depends on the correlation of returns
between A and B. And so now, to compute the standard deviation,
what I will do is that everything else stays the same.
So the only term that changes in this equation
is the correlation term.
So instead of point 0.2, what it was before,
it is 0.6 right now.
And so I highlighted it in pink color.
And so if it computes the variance of this portfolio
period now, given this new correlation,
it gives me 0.0388.
And so to compute the standard deviation,
I again have to take the square root of this term.
And so this gives me 19.7%.
So when correlation goes up to 0.6,
expect the return stays the same at 18%.
But the standard deviation of the portfolio
increases from 17.1% to 19.7%