PROFESSOR: In this next question,
we are asked to construct a portfolio
with expected return of 19.5%.
I will call this Portfolio Q. So we
want to construct a portfolio such
that expected return is 19.5%.
So let's again start with just the expression
for the expected return of the portfolio.
So expected return of the portfolio
Q equals to the weight that we put into A times
the expected return of stock A plus the weight that we
put into B times expected return on stock B.
Now notice that by definition of a portfolio, weight
A plus weight B has to add up to 1.
So here I will write an expression of for a weight B
as the function of weight A. And I will plug this
into the above equation.
So this is going to give me expected return for Portfolio Q
as the function of weight we put into weight times expected
return on stock A plus 1 minus weight that we put into A times
expected return of stock B. And now we
want to make this expression equal to 19.5%.
So now I'm going to plug in expected returns for stocks A
and B from what's given, so 20% and 15%.
And this becomes just an equation with one unknown.
So we can solve it for wA.
And this gives us 90%.
So therefore to construct a portfolio that gives us
expected return of 19.5%, we put 90% of our assets
into stock A and the remaining 10%,
because again, weights have to add up to 1
and we have only two stocks so the remaining
10% we put into stock B. So Portfolio Q
would be 90A and 10B.