PROFESSOR: In this question, we are
given two stocks, stock A and stock B,
with the following properties.
Stock A has expected return of 20%.
Stock B has expected return of 15%.
Standard deviations are 20% and 25%, respectively.
The correlation between the returns on stock A and stock B
is 0.2, or 20%.
The first question asks us whether any investor would ever
invest in stock B. And this is a reasonable question
to ask because if you look at the properties of stock B
and compare them to stock A, stock B looks, indeed,
on its own, inferior to stock A. So it has lower
expected return, and it has a higher standard deviation.
So hence, the question, would ever any of the investor here
would ever invest into stock B?
And the answer is yes.
Because of its low correlation with stock A,
this stock, although on its own inferior,
may provide diversification benefits.
And hence, a rational investor may
want to invest a fraction of his or her own wealth into stock B
to get these diversification benefits.