PROFESSOR: In this question, we will learn what is a portfolio
and how to compute portfolio weights.
Suppose that you're a financial advisor
and you have the following two clients,
client P with a portfolio P, and client Q with a portfolio Q.
Client P has the following securities in her portfolio,
she invests $25,000 in SPY, which
is ETF that tracks S&P 500 Index, 35,000 into this ETF,
this is ETF, Vanguard's ETF, that
tracks returns on short term Treasury securities,
and $50,000 into this ETF, this is
iShares ETF that tracks return of emerging markets.
Now client Q has the following portfolio, so $10,000
invested in SPY, so same ETF, $10,000 invested
in this short term Treasury ETF, 30,000
is invested in this emerging markets ETF,
and 20,000 invested into this additional ETF that
tracks returns on mortgage backed securities.
So notice that client P does not have
MBB or this ETF in her portfolio but client Q does.
So the first question that we'll answer here
is that we'll compute portfolio weights that clients P
and Q have on each individual securities in their portfolios.
Let's start with client P. So first to compute
the weights of each of these individual ETFs
in her portfolio, first step is to compute the total value
of her portfolio.
So this is just weighting up the total asset
value of each individual ETF, this gives us $75,000.
Then to compute the weight that SPY has in her portfolio
we're taking the value of SPY in her portfolio, so $25,000,
and dividing it by the total value of the portfolio, which
is $75,000.
This gives us one third or 0.33.
We're doing exactly the same for the second ETF,
for the short term Treasury ETF, so the $35,000,
this is assets on that or the value
of this ETF in this portfolio, divided by the total value
$75,000, this gives us 0.47.
And finally, for the emerging markets ETF,
15,000 divided by 75,000 gives us 0.2.
Now these are the weights.
So this is the answer to this question.
So the weight of SPY is 0.33, the weight
of short term ETF in this portfolio is 0.47,
and the weight of IEMG is 0.2.
Now let's verify, so this is going to be trivial
but let's still verify that the weights in this portfolio
add up to 1.
Remember that this is a definition of the portfolio.
So a portfolio is a collection of securities such
that the weights of each individual security
in the portfolio should add up to 1.
If they don't, then this is not a portfolio by definition.
So here, just to verify, so 0.33, plus 0.47, plus 0.2,
this gives us exactly, exactly 1.
Again, in this particular case, this is trivial,
but this just re-emphasizes the definition
of what portfolio actually is.
Let's repeat the same process for client Q
or for portfolio Q. So the total value of this portfolio
is the sum of the value of individual ETFs,
so this is $70,000.
To compute the weight of SPY we are
taking the value of SPY, 10,000, dividing it by 70,000.
That's the total value of the portfolio,
so that gives us 0.14.
We're doing the same for short term Treasury ETF,
so 10,000 divided by 70,000 also 0.14.
The weights of the emerging market ETF
is 30,000, its value divided by 70,000, that's 0.43.
And finally, the weight of the mortgage
backed securities ETF, 20,000 divided by 70,000, that's 0.29.
So these are the weights of each of these four
assets in the portfolio of this client Q.
Again, just to check to make sure that all of the weights
add up to 1, we can add them all up.
And just to verify that they all add up to 1
and this indeed is the portfolio so
that we haven't made a mistake computing any of the weights
here.