PROFESSOR: Now suppose that you were right,
and the value of this EFT--
so the value of clean energy EFT--
increases by 25%.
The question is, what is the return on your investment?
Let's answer this question.
First, I will compute the total asset value of your portfolio.
So recall that we have $65,000 invested into this ETF.
So this asset value right now increased by 25%.
So the new value is $81,250.
Now, of this, $45,000 is borrowed.
So therefore, the new value of your net investment
is the new asset value minus this borrowed amount.
This gives us $36,250.
So therefore, you have invested $20,000.
And right now, your net investment is $36,250.
So now we can compute the return.
So the return is the new value of your net investment
minus the original value divided by the original value.
And so this gives us 81.25 percent return.
So therefore, if the energy ETF increased in value by 25%,
the value or the return on your investment is 81.25 percent.
Now let me show you an alternative way
of doing the same calculation.
Recall that the leveraged investment
return equals to the leverage ratio times the asset return.
So this is the overall change in the value of your portfolio.
And so in this case, our leverage ratio
that we computed before was 3.25.
And now, we are multiplying by how much the asset
value or our ETF has changed.
This is 25%.
And so this gives us 81.25 percent return.
And this exactly matches the number
that we've computed up here.
So this is one of the major benefits
of knowing the leverage ratio of your portfolio
because it allows you to quickly understand, and approximate,
and measure by how much the value
of your original investment has changed
as a function of how much the total value of assets
changes in your portfolio.
So in this case, the value of assets increased by 25%.
And because we have a leveraged position
and this is our leverage, we have the net investment gain
of 81.25 percent.