PROFESSOR: Now, what is the standard deviation
of this portfolio Q that puts 90% into A and 10% into B?
Let's use, again-- this is the formula for the variance first,
and then we'll compute standard deviation
based on the variance, as we computed for this portfolio Q.
So again, it's weight squared times the variance of A plus B,
weight that we put into B squared, times
the variance of the returns of stock B,
plus 2 times weights times standard deviation
of A, standard deviation of B, times the correlation.
So notice that I go back to correlation,
the original correlation coefficient
that we had between the two stocks, which is 0.2.
So I plug in all of the numbers, so 0.9 squared--
this is our weight, 90%, that we put in this portfolio Q,
into stock A, so 90% squared, times 20%
squared, plus 0.1 squared plus 0.25 squared plus 2 times
the two weights, so 0.9 and 0.1, times the standard deviation,
so 0.2, 0.25, times the correlation, so 0.2.
So this gives me 0.035.
And this is the variance of our portfolio Q. Taking
square root of that gives me the standard deviation
of this portfolio Q, which is 18.8%.
So what we have done in this question is,
we were able to construct a portfolio with a given expected
return that we want, which is 19.5%,
by putting 90% into stock A and 10% of our wealth into stock B.
And this particular portfolio Q has
a standard deviation of 18.8%.