PROFESSOR: Now, assume on the contrary
that instead of increasing in value by 25%,
the value of this clean energy ETF declined by 25%.
So in this case, what is the return on your portfolio?
Let's do exactly the same two steps, two calculations,
to answer this question.
So first, let's compute the new asset value.
So this is our original value, now declined by 25%.
So the new value is $48,750.
The net investment, then-- so this is the new asset value
minus your borrowed amounts--
so the net investment is $3,750.
And now we can compute the return.
So the return is your net investments,
minus your original net investments, so
your initial wealth, divided by your, again,
initial net investment of $20,000.
This is negative 81.25%.
So if the value of this ETF declines by 25%,
your returns in your portfolio, or your initial investment,
is negative 81.25%.
So that's very significant.
So this is a very highly negative number.
Remember that the return cannot go below negative 100%.
So now, the final calculation here
is that it computes exactly the same return on your investment
as a function of the leverage ratio of your portfolio.
So again, leverage investment return
equals to leverage ratio times the return
on the assets in your portfolio.
So in our case this is 3.25% multiplied by negative 25%.
So this is the decline in the value of our assets.
So this gives us negative 81.25%--
again, the same number as we've computed here manually.