PROFESSOR: In this question, we will practice the concept
of expected utility.
Let's start with a very simple example.
We have the following investor with utility function
square root of x.
And this investor is offered the following two choices,
receive $1,000 with probability 1,
or participate in the following lottery,
lottery A, which with probability 1/2 pays $1,100,
and with the remaining probability, 1/2, pays $900.
So the question is, this investor,
with this utility function, which of the following two
choices she prefers.
What I have done here is, I've written
expected utility of this investor for this lottery
and for this sure payoff.
Let's start with the lottery.
The expected utility of this investor
equals to 1/2 the utility of the payment in the first outcome,
which is $1,100, plus another 1/2 times the utility of $900.
This is the second outcome.
So this is the utility from these payoffs weighted
by the probability of these two outcomes.
So our utility function is just the square root function.
So this first part becomes 1/2 multiplied
by square root of $1,100.
The second part becomes 1/2 multiplied
by the square root of $900.
So if we compute this, I get $31.58.
Now, in this first choice, which is the short payoff of $1,000,
the expected utility is just the utility of this $1,000,
because this is a certain outcome.
Which equals to-- again, given our utility function,
this equals to the square root of $1,000.
And this equals to $31.62.
Now, which of the two these investor picks?
Well let's figure out which of the two options
gives us higher expected utility.
The expected utility of the first option is $31.62.
The expected utility of the second option is $31.58.
Since $31.62 is greater than $31.58,
this investor should go for this first choice,
which is the certain outcome.
Now, the reason for this choice here
is that we're dealing with a risk averse investor.
If we compare the expected payoff
of the first option and the second option,
they are the same.
The expected payoff for the first option
is just literally $1,000.
The expected payoff of the second option is also $1,000.
It's 1/2 times the first pay of $1,100 plus the other 1/2 times
$900.
This is the payoff in the second state of the world.
So the average of the two is just $1,000.
So the expected pay of the first option
is exactly the same as the expected
pay of the second option but there is more uncertainty
of the second option.
And since we're dealing with the risk-averse investor, who
has a concave utility function, this investor
goes for a certain outcome with exactly
the same expected payoff as less certain outcomes
with the same expected payoff.