Finally, let's find certain equivalent
for the third investor.
Recall that this investor has utility function x raised
to the power of 1 over 3.
We will do exactly the same two steps
as we have done in the part a and part b of this question.
So Step 1, we're starting with the same equation.
The only difference right now will
be that the utility function is different
and so therefore $80,000 will have
to be raised to the power of 1 over 3.
So $20,000 will have to be raised
to the same power, 1 over 3.
And $5,000 will have to be raised
to the power of 1 over 3.
Computing this gives us expected utility
for this investor of 22.71.
And now in Step 2, we can find certainty equivalent.
So we need to solve this equation.
So u of CE equals to 22.71.
u of CE equals to CE raised to the power of 1 over 3.
Because this is just our utility function.
That equals to 22.71.
So therefore CE equals to 22.71 raised to the power of 1/3.
And this equals to 11,715.61.
So therefore this investor is indifferent between taking
$11,715.61 and playing this lottery.
Let's conclude and summarize what we've learned so far.
We're given three investors.
Investor A is risk neutral because she
has a linear utility function.
Both investors B and C are risk averse,
because they have concave utility function.
Investor C is more risk averse than investor B.
So therefore if all three investors
are presented with the same lottery,
we would expect that certainty equivalent of investor A
would be higher than that of investor B
which in turn will be higher than that of investor C.
And this is exactly what we found.
Investor A is willing to trade the lottery
for a guaranteed payoff or certainty
equivalent of $17,000.
Investor B is he's willing to trade off
this exact same lottery for $12,800.
So the difference between certainty equivalence
of investor A and investor B shows you
how much more risk averse investor B
is compared to investor A.
And certainly equivalent of investor B
is greater than certainty equivalent of investor C
which is $11,716, which again is due to the fact
that investor C is more risk averse than investor B
and is willing to trade this lottery for a lower guaranteed
amount.