Let's find certainty equivalent for the second investor.
Recall that her utility function is square root of x,
or x raised to the power 1/2.
Let's do the same two steps as we have done
in part a of this question.
So step 1, we'll find the expected utility
of this lottery for this investor.
We're starting with exactly the same equation.
The only difference right now is that utility function
is different.
So therefore, where we had 80,000 before,
it's going to be 80,000 raised to the power of 1/2.
So the full expression looks like this,
0.1 multiplied by 80,000 raise to the power of 1/2
plus 0.3 multiplied by 20,000 raised to the power 1/2
plus 0.6 multiplied by 5,000 raised to the power of 1/2.
So computing this gives us expected utility
that this investor will get from this lottery of 113.14.
Now, in the second step, we can find certainty equivalent.
So u of CE equals to 113.14.
Now, for this investor, u of CE equals
to CE raised to the power 1/2.
And so now we have to solve the following equation.
So CE raised to the power of 1/2 equals to 113.14.
This is a simple equation to solve.
So this gives us CE equals to 113.14 raised to the power 2.
Computing this gives us 12,800.
So therefore, this investor is indifferent between taking
$12,800 and playing this lottery.
So in other words, her certainty equivalent,
or the riskless amount that she's
willing to trade instead of playing this lottery,
is $12,800.