PROFESSOR: Estimating the parameters of model
is pretty easy and relatively straightforward
when we're given this data set.
Finding the right model or choosing among a set of models
can be much harder.
And there might not even be a right answer.
So let's take a look at a few examples.
We're going to start with the Monte Carlo example.
And the reason is that it helps to know that your data actually
comes from a model.
So we'll start from a case that has a known answer.
That way, we'll have some confidence when we start
looking at other data sets.
It's tough.
And there may not always be a clear decision
that you can make.
And it requires judgment-- not only in selecting the model,
but in understanding what the practical consequences are
of having the wrong model.
Is it just a good approximation?
Or is it missing some essential components
of the dynamics of the system and data generating
process that you want to study?
There's no easy way to know.
And you need to constantly be on guard
for things that might go wrong, and keep
going back and refining your techniques.
So let's start with an AR(2) example.
Now remember that autoregressive models
have the property that they do have
correlations-- autocorrelations-- across time.
And typically those autocorrelation functions
drop off over time, but they exist at all lags.
This is in contrast with MA models
that are also defined recursively.
But they're defined recursively in terms of the innovations
that are localized in time.
So at a sufficient separation in any given MA(q) model,
the autocorrelation will go to zero.
So that already helps us differentiate between the two.
So let's look at our example.
I'll generate some data here.
You can download the notebook-- in fact,
pause the video and do this now if you'd like--
so you can follow along and tweak the parameters
and try your own examples.
Obviously the random numbers you generate will be different.
But if you'd like to see the same random numbers, actually,
why don't we set this up so that we
can look at the same random numbers together.
I'm going to add a command in our notebook
which will make sure that we get the same random numbers
by setting the seed 2021.
Now, your computers may come up with a different set
of random numbers.
What this guarantees is, within a given setting,
you will get on each one the same random numbers.
So obviously in actual applications,
this is the last thing you want to do.
Because you want the random numbers to be random.
Not just a single draw of random numbers to be reused.
But for debugging purposes you might find it helpful.
So you can put this in, comment it out or delete it afterwards.
So here are the parameters of the model.
We've got c_0 is 0.001.
So it's a small intercept.
It's close to zero.
C_1, the first autoregressive parameter
that is the coefficient of the lag 1 observation,
is going to be minus 0.1.
And c_2 is going to be larger and opposite sign.
0.4.
So let's take 1,000 times steps.
We'll organize them in a column vector
and set this up so that it generalizes
for the case where you want to do an ensemble of paths
together.
But we'll run this forward.
Now, one thing we need to be careful of when
we start with time series models that are simulated--
they obviously can't go infinitely far in the past.
So we usually bootstrap them by setting the initial values off
into zero.
And we do need to make sure that our results don't
depend on that.
Those need to be a good approximation
for larger values.
So that's why I've initialized my variable r
to be full of zeros, and I've started
my recursion at time step 3.
Because it needs to go back to previous time steps.
So if we run this-- so we can see
that I've defined a set of space placeholder for my variables.
And I could set that to be plus 1 if I were doing market data.
So I have a time 0, but here it's all simulated.
It doesn't matter.
I pick a bunch of random numbers.
Which, in this case, I'm choosing
from a N (0,1) distribution.
These are normally distributed.
And then I have a for loop where this is
the basic line of my recursion.
So notice I do need to iterate it forward.
I can't do this with some clever algebraic tricks
because I need to know what the values are at time t
to know what they are for the next time step at t equals 1.
So let's run this chunk of code, plot the results
and see what we get.
So the first graph that we have is going
to be the AR(2) sample path.
So it wanders.
It looks random.
Can you tell that it's autoregressive from looking
at it?
I can't.
Let's look at the autocorrelation function.
Well, here we see we're getting out what
we expected when we put it in.
That is, the first coefficient is nothing to do with c_0.
That's normalized to equal to 1.
That's the correlation of the series with itself.
At lag 1 we have a negative number.
And at lag 2 we have a positive number.
And all the others look like they're
at the limits of statistical significance.
So that's about what we would have expected.
Here's the partial ACF.
Now remember what the partial ACF does.
What it does is, it fits-- for each lag--
it fits an autoregressive model of that number of terms.
And the partial autocorrelation coefficient
is the coefficient of the highest lag term.
So what we would expect is that we're
going to get non-zero results for each coefficient
up to the order of our model.
In an AR(p) model for the first p terms, in an AR(2) model
for the first two terms.
And everything above that should be close to zero.
And that's exactly what we see here.
So this would give us confidence that what we're looking at
is an AR(2) model if we didn't know what the data was.
Now let's go and remove this seed parameter and rerun it.
Let's do a new set of random numbers.
So I will run this chunk again.
And let's take a look.
This is a different process.
We'll move over here, click on the second box.
Here are its autocorrelation coefficients.
You notice that the third and fourth are still showing up.
But we do see the expected alternating signs and decay.
And when we look at the partial ACF,
we, again, see the lag 1 and 2 coefficients looking large,
and all the others being small.
And, of course, this plot out 30.
And for 30 things to within 5% significance,
we might expect a couple to be up.
So these are things to do iteratively.
If you see something suspicious, go dig in and investigate
a little bit further.
How do we estimate?
So suppose we've decided, great, that data set is
generated from an AR(2) model.
It's looking good.
Let's find the parameters of the AR(2) model.
So once we settle on a model, really what we're doing
is applying standard estimation techniques.
There's nothing very special.
In R there are some functions that help streamline it.
But the basic idea is that we can do linear regression
techniques.
The only difference is that the variables
on the right-hand side that normally would
be independent variables are just
lag versions of the variables on the left-hand side.
So we can use ordinary least squares, maximum likelihood
estimation, usual ways.
And we can do that if we take the series
and create lagged versions of it.
Or R happens to provide-- and other languages do, too--
packages that have some of these functions already built in.
So let's take a look.
In this case, let's define.
Let's first write it--
we'll do it in two methods.
First we'll write it as an ordinary least squares.
And then we'll do it using an special case
of the built-in ARIMA function, where
we'll look at the AR(2) as a special case of that.
So the first thing is, I can define my variables.
y is an independent variable in x1 and x2.
Excuse me, y is a dependent variable.
x1 and x2 is independent variables.
But, of course, there are all from the time
series of r, which we generated synthetically.
Notice the time offset.
Because we're looking at the correlation series with itself
as the lags move, I'm going to end up
with some non-matching points-- either at the beginning
or at the end.
And I need to trim those off so that I have
data series of equal length.
If the number of points you trim is significant,
then your data series is too short.
Or you're looking at--
this is not a good model for what you want to be doing,
if it's too sensitive.
So the two ways we can look at it
are we can run in R the lm function.
Builds a linear model.
It just runs linear regression.
And you can do this in any language.
You can do it in Excel.
Alternatively, we can run the ARIMA function in R
and fit this to a series where the order is
given by the first parameter is the autoregressive part.
The second is an integration level.
And the third one is moving average part.
So let's take a look and see what we get.
So if we fit this by ordinarily least squares,
we get the usual results in r.
So we have an intercept.
We have an x1 and an x2.
We see that the intercept is close to zero.
It's 0.034 with the standard error of 0.032.
So that's close to zero.
We didn't exactly pick out our carefully set c_0.
But the x1 and x2 values are within the standard errors.
So for that given the data series.
That is, we have minus 0.07.
And there's an approximation to minus 0.1.
And we have, for the second coefficient,
we've got plus 0.41, 0.42, no, 0.41.
It's an approximation 0.4.
So we got out what we expected going in.
And we can take a look at the significance
of the different values.
Now, if we run this second method, this ARIMA function,
we also get the coefficients here.
It's laid out a little bit differently,
but these are the same numbers.
And it's just to show you that this is dressed up.
It's really just doing an ordinary regression.
So that's where we have the order correct.
And we fit the parameters.
So we decide what the model is.
In this case, we generated the data, then we set that aside.
We ran the data, we identified the order.
We said that looks like it's order 2.
We ran a fit to AR(2) model.
We have estimates for the coefficients.
They're noisy estimates because we have some noisy data,
but then we can proceed with that estimated model
with that set of parameters.
Now, what if we got the order incorrect?
That is, what if we thought--
suppose there had been a spike, just a random jump, at order 5.
And we said, ah, we've got an AR(5) model.
Well, let's try running that.
And in that case we find a set of coefficients here.
And we can, again, take a look at what the estimates are.
And we see that the standard errors show us
that the errors are much larger than the coefficients
themselves for the higher order terms.
For AR(4) and AR(5).
And even the third term is not statistically significant.
So if we go too far, we can pull back
and refit the model and retune for what we're doing.
Try it yourself on some other data.
See how well the quality of the estimates
depends on the length of the series.
That we can then turn around and think
about how much data is required to get a good
handle on the models.
Let's take a look at this for an MA(2) model.
So here is a model, which is MA(2).
So it's got two lagged parameters.
But those lag parameters this time are
the z's on the right-hand side, not the r's.
Not our random variable that we're
observing, but the innovations.
The shocks that occur in each time period.
So I need to bootstrap this a little bit.
Because at the beginning, again, we're
not going infinitely far back in the past.
So we're going to do this with our first two innovations.
And then from time 3 forward to the end of the series
we'll run this recursively.
So our recursive definition is terrific for programmability.
And let's run this model with a set of parameters.
So if we take a look at what we get.
Here's an MA(2) sample path.
Does it look different from an AR(2) sample path?
I can't say so.
It looks like a noisy bunch of data to me.
We did pick a very large value for sigma
in relative terms for financial applications.
But that's OK.
Finance things are noisy.
And you can try scaling these to different sizes
to see how they look.
How about our ACF and PACF functions?
Well, here remember for the MA(2),
we expect the ACF function to tell us when to stop.
That is, the autocorrelation functions are only going
to exist through the value q.
And we see that here.
We see that we've got autocorrelation functions
and autocovariances, non-varnishing, for lags 1
and 2.
And then everything drops off.
So that as we would expect.
If we look at the PACF, the partial autocorrelation
function, that's not much help here.
So if this isn't showing us much,
the reason is not that we've applied it incorrectly.
It's because it's not the right tool
for doing this identification.
So when we pick our tools, you can throw everything
at every dime series you have and you might
see some interesting stuff.
But think about the question you want to answer
and specifically what it is we're looking for.
Suppose we now want to estimate the parameters.
Let's do that this time.
We can run in R. You can repeat the ordinary least squares.
Or we'll do it this way, using this notation.
So (0,0,2) means it's only a moving average model.
And as we run this, we get our coefficients.
And we see our intercept is consistent with zero.
And our MA(1) and MA(2) are lag 1 and lag 2.
Coefficients for the phi's in the right-hand side
are given by the results here.
And again, try it out for longer data
sets, for shorter data sets.
And then for some real-world data.
Speaking of real-world data.
It's much harder.
First of all, it typically doesn't
fit any particular model.
So if we're going to pick a model
we'd like to estimate something that
captures the important features of the data.
And we don't even know what those necessarily are.
So let's take a look at a data set.
In this case, we'll grab some data
from Yahoo Finance using the tidyquant package.
And we'll get it for Tootsie Roll stock.
So if you haven't used tidyquant before,
you can uncomment this line and install it.
We load it with the library command.
And we'll define a ticker, a start, and an end date.
And then this tq_get function grabs data from Yahoo Finance.
Or you can just load it from a flat file yourself.
So what does the data look like over time?
Let's take a look at a chart.
So that looks pretty noisy, too.
This is more data points than we had before.
There's an upward drift, which is definitely significant.
Notice I set the drift term close to zero
in both of our previous two examples.
But here's the data.
Now let's take a look at the time series of returns
by taking the difference of the logarithms
of the successive prices.
And here's the return series.
Now, when we get data for a stock or an asset,
usually what we do-- in fact, what I almost always do--
is I'll take the price data.
I will turn it into returns like this.
I'll use adjusted prices so I account for corporate actions
and splits and dividends and so on.
I'll take the adjusted series.
And what I want to know is, what are the basic descriptive
statistics for it?
Which we can do on any data set.
What is the mean?
What is the standard deviation?
Or, in financial terms, if we annualize numbers,
what's the return and what's the risk?
What are the parameters?
Now, one of the things-- so we can do that
anyways for anything.
Those are just descriptive statistics for a set of data.
They don't have anything to do with models.
But if, in addition, we think about the generalized random
walk model and we wanted to fit the data to that,
well, mu and sigma are given by the same formulas
that we have for the descriptive statistics--
the mean and the standard deviation.
So we would be in great shape.
So we could ask.
Is the generalized random walk a good fit for this data?
Well, the answer is no.
But what do you think?
What do you think the reason is?
So one of the things that I look at is the feature--
there are a couple of features that
are important-- of the random walk model.
One of them is the lack of serial correlation.
So we ought to immediately take a look at a plot of the ACF.
Because if it's a random walk, there's
no information propagating from one time period to the next.
But before that, even at the level
of the descriptive statistics, even before we compute them,
we can see visually here that this does not
look like a stationary process.
So remember that stationarity means
that we have time independent probability distributions.
And it can be a very difficult thing to nail down, exactly.
But certainly in the case of the random walk model,
one of the things that we know is that in a stationary model,
if the probability distributions are the same,
then that necessarily means that if we estimate parameters
from different subsets of the data,
we ought to get the same values.
At least, to within sampling errors.
That means that there ought to be a given mean and a given
standard deviation that we could sample over time.
Now, a model that looks like this, if I run a Monte Carlo to
simulate data that has matching statistics of the Tootsie Roll
data, it looks like this.
This is a white noise process that has a constant mean--
zero, in this case--
and a standard deviation that is constant over time.
So we see that the data is time varying.
But the probability distribution is not.
On the other hand, the data that we see here for Tootsie Roll
just, without running any fancy statistics,
we can see that it's very, very unlikely
to come from a generalized random walk
model because of the presence of extreme spikes and outliers.
So depending on what assumptions we
would make for the distribution, this
is unlikely to come from a single model
with fixed parameters of the type
of the generalized random walk over the entire period.
The model that might fit much better
is something that combines many of the elements we have here,
but I'm not going to go into in this video.
Something that's a model, for example, that has a time
varying volatility parameter that
would explain the difference between this and this.
So this data, you can take.
And I encourage you to try it and fit it
to each of the models and answer these questions.
Which of the models is the best fit?
If you're looking for a model of autoregressive
moving average or ARIMA type model, which is the best one?
And what would be the parameters in those case?
And what's the significance of the parameters?
And do you think that the time series is stationary?