PROFESSOR: We saw in lecture how to use Monte Carlo
techniques to simulate price paths,
for example, for asset prices.
For example, behind me I have some sample prices
for a stock that might follow a log-normal process.
That is, its logarithmic returns are normally distributed.
And the parameters over here are that I have 252 time steps.
I have 10,000 simulations of which
I have plotted the first 10.
I have an initial price of $100.
I have a mu of 0.6.
And I've got a sigma of 0.42.
So this shows a particular set of realizations.
But there's more than we can do than just
look at pretty pictures.
Monte Carlo methods give us a powerful approximation tool.
And they give us some direct computation tools when
it comes to derivative pricing.
So how are they a powerful computation tool?
Well, if we know the exact probability distribution,
then if we want to compute some expectations of operators,
we end up doing some intervals.
So even for something as simple as the Gaussian distribution,
we might be interested in some transforms, some exponentials,
some other complex functions.
We'd have to do a bunch of Gaussian integrals, which
is fine if you like integrals.
But there's another way to do it,
which is we can simulate price paths on the computer,
and then we replace the exact expectation operator,
the mathematical operator, where we
take a probability weighted average of our function
or variable of interest.
And we replace it by an average, just an ordinary arithmetic
average, of the quantities that are
observed within our ensemble.
What makes this work is the fact that all of our paths
are equally likely.
So we don't need to write down the explicit probability
measure.
What we do is we generate the paths
because each one is as likely to be drawn as any other.
The weights will come up, and they will
sample the probability measure.
And they'll sample the space with appropriate weights
and appropriate frequencies.
So this is a very good approximation technique
for problems where it might be difficult to do
the integrals in closed form, or we might not even
have an explicit expression for the probability measure.
There are two things to keep in mind regarding the accuracy,
and you should try out these examples.
So there are things on problem sets.
But you should go beyond that.
Try changing the parameters.
In particular, two things to take a look at to
see how they affect the accuracy--
one of them is the number of simulations.
I typically use 10,000 pounds to start
with because in general, the accuracy of the result
goes like 1 over the square root of the number of paths.
So if I have 10,000 paths, that should give me things
that are accurate to around 1%.
What's more important-- the number might be different,
but the scaling is important.
If I want to get it 10 times better,
I need to do 100 times more simulations.
If I do only 1/100 of the number of simulations,
my answers are going to degrade by a factor of 10.
The other thing that you might want to experiment with,
though, is the size of the time step.
How does dt make a difference?
Does it matter?
For example, if we're looking at approximating
a log-normal price process by breaking it up
using a binomial random walk, by using
steps that are plus or minus 1 scaled appropriately
to the mean and volatility of the process
that we're interested in, how does that affect the answer?
So a useful thing to do is to start
with a known example, something that you
could do in closed form, where you could look up
the answer, where you could compute the integral.
And you can do the interval for this set of parameters
if you'd like and then compare with what
you get in Monte Carlo
Now, keep in mind when doing problem sets,
because the numbers are randomly generated,
your answer might not exactly match.
It's going to be within some range.
And in fact, as you rerun your Monte Carlo,
you'll see the answers change.
So what you might want to do is take
an average of your own answers.
In fact, what you might want to do
is not only run an ensemble of 10,000 paths,
compute the approximate analytics using the rules
that I mentioned before--
we approximate an expectation by taking an average
over the results--
but you could go further and run those 10,000 paths maybe
100 times and take the average of those,
or at least look at what their distribution is.
That tells you something about the confidence interval
within which your estimate lies.
Now, that's true in general for doing statistical analytics.
What about financial applications?
So one of the interesting things that we can do
is, when we've got these stock price paths,
is think about the behavior of financial derivatives.
Derivatives are securities like stock options
whose value depends on the value of another security.
And one of the important constructions
in applications and quantitative finance
and in derivative pricing is to compute expected values that
are functions of stock prices.
So the value of an option is a function
of the value of the stock underlying the option.
And in a Monte Carlo setting, we can compute plots
of functions of our variable.
So here's how we plot our paths initially.
And if we wanted to plot a function, say, s squared,
we can go into the code and change s to s squared
and take a look.
So if I had a derivative whose value
is equal to the square of the stock price,
these are simulations of what its value would be
Now, we're often interested in the terminal values,
especially for derivatives like options that expire.
So what we sometimes want to do is compute the terminal
or the final value of the stock price
and then the final value of a derivative.
So if we do that, I've plotted here
or I've computed S.terminal to be the final row of S.
And if I look at a histogram of S.terminal,
we can see what the distribution is.
If we want to take a look at the distribution
of our s squared values, because it follows the value all
the way along, we could just compute the histogram
of this quantity squared, but typically we'd
like to know of the entire lifetime of the option.
Now, let's take a look at an interesting example
is to take a look at a call or a put option.
And in those cases, the derivative
has a value along the entire trajectory of the option,
but the valuation techniques that we often look at
involve separate considerations for the interior
prior to expiration and at expiration.
So if we consider a European-type option,
which has nothing to do with Europe--
it's just the name of the option--
it's something that can only be exercised at expiration,
at no time prior.
If it can be exercised early, it's typically
known as an American option.
So if we consider a European call option
on a stock with strike price K, and we'd
like to know what its distribution of terminal values
is, that would be an interesting question.
So for example, suppose we go back to our--
let's go back and look at our previous graph--
our original graph right here.
And suppose we have an option--
a stock option that gives us the right but not the obligation
to buy the stock if the price exceeds, say, $150.
So it starts at 100.
And we want to know a year later,
is it going to be in excess of $150 or not?
If yes, we will make money on our option.
If not, we would not exercise the option.
So one of the interesting questions we might ask
is, how likely is it that the value of the stock
will exceed a particular threshold?
And that's something we can answer with Monte Carlo.
Let's take a look at that.
So let's define a strike price K. Let's let it be 150.
And now let's define the value of our call option.
And we'll define it at all points
in time relative to the value of our stock price.
So let's say C is S minus K. Now, that's partly true.
That's good for all the points where S is greater than K
but not where it's less than K.
So what we'll do-- this is an r-specific construct.
You can do the same kind of thing
in different ways in other languages.
But I'm going to multiply this times
the expression S greater than K, which is a Boolean expression.
So it's equal to 1 if S is greater than K,
0 if S is equal to or less than K.
And it multiplies these point by point.
So this expression for C should give me
the value of the option when it's
in the money, when the stock price exceeds the strike price.
And it'll give me 0 otherwise.
So let's take a look at what some of those paths look like.
And I'm going to go back to my plotting function.
And I'm going to change S to C, and let's plot those.
Now, we notice the value never goes below zero, which is good.
So the options-- you cannot lose money apart from the premium
that you paid for the option.
So all the places where the paths hit 0 or don't even
show up, those are cases where the value was below the strike
price, and the other ones are above.
Now, we could ask-- this is just for the first 10 paths.
We could look at what happens over 100 paths.
But if we do that, we're still not getting the whole flavor.
Because we don't know what fraction of paths
are ending up above versus the number that we
don't see that are below.
So let's take a look.
We can look at the histogram of the terminal values, which is
going to be C of 252 comma 0--
excuse me-- 252 comma.
So we get all of the columns in our simulation.
And what we see is that of our 10,000 simulations,
6,000 of them ended up at 0.
So what we saw was the distribution
of the values above the strike price, but most of the values
are below the strike price.
So we have a very asymmetric distribution.
60% of the paths are worthless.
They finish below the strike price.
Of those that are above some of them go to quite large values.
In fact, that highest point that we can see in the pixel range--
600 is above the strike price of 150.
So that would be a very fortunate outcome.
Unfortunately, it's quite unlikely to happen.
So when we are working with derivatives,
we often create a sample of paths for the underlying.
We then compute functions of the underlying that
are appropriate to the value of the derivative,
and then we look at the analytics of interest.
One of the analytics of interest is
going to be the distribution of terminal values
and maybe some moments of its distribution,
such as the mean and the variance.
In this case, because the distribution
is so skewed and so unusual, we might
want to ask conditionally, for example,
conditioned on having a positive value, what is the mean?
And in other cases, such as options,
and it might have early exercise opportunities
where early exercise could be optimal
or where there may be barrier options whose value could
go to 0, say if it hits a particular value
during its lifetime prior to expiration, in those cases,
we want to work not just by averaging over
the entire ensemble of paths.
We might look path by path at which paths
meet certain conditions either at different points in time
in the case of early exercise or at different points in space
and in stock price in the case of barrier options.