PROFESSOR: Let's talk about forecasting.
We saw in lecture that forecasting
is an application of conditional probability to time series
models.
So we think of the time series as generating the data.
And we ask at a given point in time,
given all the observations that exist up
through that point in time, what can we say about the future?
We might want to know what happens one time step ahead,
two time steps ahead, or in limit
as the number of times that goes to infinity,
but the key thing is the break between past and future.
So we take the present time to be just after we've
made our final observation.
And we're first forecast period is one step ahead.
And, as I said, the key tool is in addition to
our previous ones with expectations,
linearity, algebraic substitution, recursion.
We had a new one, which is conditional probability.
In this setting, conditional probability simply
means that for any variable that was
a random variable in the past that has been realized,
it's no longer a random variable.
Now it's a scalar.
Now it's a number.
So those things that show up in the recursion
that we previously thought of as random variables,
in this setting, when we take conditional expectations
of our defining equations or equations of evolution,
then they take a different character,
because they're already known.
They're no longer random variables.
So we looked at an example in lecture.
Let's just do a couple of examples together.
It's the same structure.
They're just one or two things it might be worth
paying attention to as you look at the blind forecast
of your own.
Some of the things that might have look special for the case
of the AR 1 are quite general.
So let's take a look at a model.
Let's look at, say, an AR MA 1, model, AR MA 1,
1, which is this form.
Let's say that Xt is equal to a constant C0 plus C1 X
the previous 1 plus a bunch of Z's.
So I'm going to keep the notation sigma
Zt for our shock for innovation in the period.
You could give it another name for its coefficient.
Remember that sigma, in this case,
is not the standard deviation of x.
It's just a scaling parameter for the random shock z.
And then we'll call this phi 1 Zt minus 1.
So the first thing we'd like to do
is compute the mean value for x and simplify our expression.
So we use our usual trick.
Mu is the name will give the expectation of Xt.
And then we take expectations on the right hand side
and apply linearity.
So we have this is going to be C0 plus C1 expectation of X
t minus 1, but we know that that is just
the same thing as C1 times mu.
And then we're going to have plus 0 plus 0,
because the Z's have 0 expectation.
So we have the result that mu is going to be equal
to C0 over 1 minus C1.
And you should recognize that expression from our AR 1 model.
It's exactly the same expression.
And therefore, we can substitute and rewrite our equation
as a bunch of things that are grouped together in such a way
that they all have 0 mean.
That is to say, if I substitute for C0
and say it's equal to mu times 1 minus C1,
then I can write this as Xt--
let's keep our colors consistent here--
Xt minus mu--
I can put this on either side of the equation,
depending on what I'd like to do--
but just for looking at the structure of the model,
I'll right this is Xt minus 1 minus mu
plus sigma Zt plus phi 1 Z of t minus 1.
Now the next thing we want to do is put things
in forecasting form.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to shift t to t plus 1.
Everywhere where I see a t, I'm going to write t plus 1.
And that puts the future values on the left
and the present and past values or the known
values on the right hand side.
So for one-time step ahead, this makes exactly the split
that we want to have.
So what I'll do is-- let me just write this as Xt plus 1.
Here I can put the mu on the right hand side if I like.
And this is going to be C1 of Xt minus 2 plus sigma Zt plus 1
plus phi 1 and Z.
So notice that in our original description,
in our terms of our original coefficient
C1 was a reminder that it matched the lag 1x variable.
And phi 1 was a reminder that it matched lag 1 Z variable.
If we had C2, C3, and phi 2, phi 3, phi 4,
those would have matched the corresponding lags of the Z's,
but what really matters are the relative amounts.
So when I add 1 to everything, there's no surprise
or there shouldn't be the C1 now gets
multiplied by Xt without a lag and similarly with phi 1.
So that's here.
So what's our forecast?
So our definition for our forecast
is going to be the conditional probability.
So our first forecast is going to be f of t comma 1.
That is the forecast made at time t for one-time step
ahead in the future.
And there are different notations for this.
So what you really should rely on is not the notation,
but reduce everything to expectations.
So this is the expectation of t plus 1 given everything
up through that point, which includes Xt, Zt,
and any previous failures, but those
don't show up in this equation on the right-hand side.
So let's compute the expectation.
And what we noticed is that the only random variable
on the right hand side is this one.
That's the only thing that's random.
So this value here is known.
This value here is known.
There's only one random variable.
And we take expectations, the expectation of t plus 1
is going to vanish.
So what do we get?
We're going to get that the forecast is equal to--
we'll leave this here--
is going to be mu plus C1 times Xt minus mu plus phi 1.
So we just do the calculation.
It's exactly the same as the expression
above, except for this term, this random term
that dropped out, because it has zero expectation.
So let's take a look at the forecast error.
So the first forecast error for one-time step
ahead is going to be, e is going to be f,
or actually it's going to be the outcome, excuse me,
but we're going to square it.
So it won't matter.
The error is going to be X t plus 1 minus f t comma 1.
That is the forecast error as defined
as the difference between what we predicted
and what actually happened.
What we'd like to do and the way in which
we have this definition for the forecast being optimal
is we're going to minimize the mean squared forecast error.
That is going to minimize the square of e
in expectation of all possible things that would happen.
Now we could use other kinds of loss functions.
Those will depend on the settings,
depending on the economic values.
So it's just a question of doing and minimization,
but in this case, we have this basic result
that this will be our expectation,
but let's compute the forecast error.
So the idea is that what we really want, in general, if you
want to drive this and check, what we really want
is we want a predictor for f, that some function of all
the previous observations, in this case, just Xt and Zt,
we'd like to be a linear function.
And when we find the linear function that
minimizes the mean squared error,
we find that it's this conditional expectation.
So let's compute this quantity.
And we'll see that there's a really nice structure that
shows up.
Xt plus 1 minus the forecast, you
notice that most of the terms are common.
So Xt plus 1 involves this term and this term.
Xt plus 1 involves-- this is the only term that
doesn't appear in ft 1.
So when I take this quantity and I subtract this quantity given
down here, I've got a very simple result.
This is just equal to sigma z plus 1.
And therefore, the mean squared forecast error
is Et plus 1 squared is equal to the expectation of sigma
Zt plus 1 quantity squared.
And that's just equal to sigma squared.
Now what about looking at multiple forecasts?
So we'd like to go for future horizons.
One-step was easy.
So the general rule is that when we
want to do it two-step ahead forecast,
we're going to shift everything.
We're going to add one more.
So we write an expression for X of t
plus 2, but now on the right hand side,
I've got 2 plus 1, which isn't known yet.
So here's the general procedure.
Keep doing the recursion.
Keep substituting in back until all of the X's on the right
hand side of the equation have a time index of t or earlier.
The Z's can be later.
That's OK, because we're going to take their expectations,
and they're going to vanish.
So we might have some possibly unknown Z's.
But the basic idea is once we go beyond one-time step,
how do you know what to do?
It's easy.
You're doing Xt plus h for horizon h
on the left hand side.
And on the right hand side, you do probably h or h
minus 1 recursive substitutions of the defining equation
until we can express Xt plus h in terms of X, Xt
minus 1, and so on.
Those are all known quantities.
Then we take conditional expectations.
We have our forecast.
We compute the forecast errors.
We take expectations of their squares.
That's easy as well, because it's just the same quantities.
Now we have the known and the unknown ones
clearly delineated.
And we get our results for our mean squared forecast error.
And there are two really important properties
to keep in mind for our solution.
One of them is the forecast error has zero expectation.
And the forecast error is orthogonal
to the other variables, to the other random variables--
excuse me, to the other predictor variables.
So let's take a look for another example
Let's take a look at an AR MA 2, 2 model, shall we?
So now when you're given numbers for the forecasts
or particular horizons, you can either plug them in right away
or you can leave the parameters general.
That generally makes it easier to check your math
and find any sign errors that might be there,
but either way, whether you substitute indefinite numbers
for the parameters before or after shouldn't
make any difference.
When you're doing forecast, you do want to pay attention though
to the initial conditions if you have to bootstrap your process,
because if you're asked for a forecast one or three
or seven steps ahead, you'll need enough data to get
the process started before you can generate the recursion.
The recursive techniques that we have
that I'm writing down here for the forecast
are technically appropriate for the case, where we go
infinitely far into the past.
Even if the series did exist an infinitely long time,
we wouldn't have an infinite amount of data.
So we do need to make sure we have the initial conditions set
to get numerical answers, but the basic rules are compute
conditional expectations after writing our defining
equations with variable to be forecast on the left hand side
and only known observations on the right hand side.
So let's do this for AR MA 2, 2.
So it just has--
it's little bit more complicated at least initially.
So it looks like C0 plus C1 Xt minus 1 plus C2 Xt minus 2
plus our old friend sigma Zt.
And now let's add some phi terms plus phi 1, Z of t minus 1
plus phi 2, Z of t minus 2.
And you can see how it would go for a general ARMA PQ.
I'm going to write it in concrete form
so we don't have summations running around.
And when we shift, it gets a little messy
keeping track of the indices, but you can do it.
And you can take a look at the literature as well for that.
So what's our expectation in this case?
So mu is the expectation of Xt.
And now that's going to be C0 plus C1 mu plus C2 mu.
And that tells us that mu is actually
equal to C0 divided by 1 minus 1 minus 2.
And you can guess how this generalizes
for the general ARMA PQ model, we
get the generalization of this expression.
And then we can write our equation
as Xt is equal to C1 of Xt minus 1 minus mu
plus C2 Xt minus 2 minus mu.
And we start to recognize some patterns.
And we get the hang of it, plus phi 1 Ct minus 1
plus phi 2 Ct minus 2.
And let's not forget our sigma, Zt, which we can put over here,
let's do some forecasting, shall we?
Oh, excuse me, this should also have on the left hand side,
this should be Xt minus mu.
You should notice that each of the terms that I've
written down is a way that it has 0 mean.
That just makes it a bit easier to see what's going on,
to see what the dynamics are, and to do some calculations.
You can also, if you want to clean it up,
you can find a new variable y to be Xt minus mu and shift things
back.
So you can do any rescaling things you like.
The end results are going to be the same if they're just
redefinitions of the parameters and rescalings
of the variables.
So let's take a look for time T plus 1.
So for time T plus 1 minus mu, we're
going to C1 of Xt minus mu plus C2 of Xt minus 1 minus mu
plus sigma Zt plus 1 plus phi 1 Zt plus phi 2 Zt minus 1.
So that one is pretty easy.
It looks like the expression that we just
did before for the AR MA 1, 1.
That is everything on the right hand side has an index of--
all of the X's are taken at time T or T minus 1.
And the Z's are mostly in the past.
We have these two with coefficients
of phi's both in the past.
And this is the only one that's still a random variable,
but at time 2, things change.
So let's look one more time step ahead.
Let's contrast a little bit.
So if we write this as Xt plus 2 minus mu,
we see that we have C1 Xt plus 1 minus mu.
And that is going to be something
we're going to need to replace.
And then plus the other terms are not
going to give us any major problems.
And this is going to be Ct times Xt minus mu plus sigma
plus T plus 2 plus phi 1 Zt plus 1 plus phi 2 Zt.
So all I've done is I shifted T to T plus 1 again.
And the terms that are in orange are the things that--
well, let me put the other one in orange-- so a little
more consistent.
So let's put in orange things that pertain to the future.
So I have two of the terms on the right hand side
involve the present or the past.
And that's OK.
Those are known quantities, but I have these other expressions.
So I can't just directly compute the expectation
on the left hand side.
Now I could take the previous work I did before
and substitute that would be fine.
But if I want to see the general approach for doing it
at a particular time step, what I'm going to say
is that the expressions here and here, I can leave alone,
because those are both fine.
These just involves Z's.
And I know their expectations, but I
don't want the recursive structure for Xt
plus 1, because remember this is saying that the value two
days from now depends on the value tomorrow, which
I haven't yet observed.
So the value today, the value yesterday, those are all known,
but rather than expressing it this way,
I'd like to do my recursions, get it out.
And then I can take clean ordinary simple expectations
and get an answer.
So let's do that.
And we just need to substitute one more time and put that in.
So which term are we going to substitute--
we're going to substitute in?
We'll have Xt plus 2 minus mu is going
to be C1 times this entire expression above.
So let's just write that out.
This is going to times C1 Xt minus mu plus C2.
Xt minus 1 minus mu and so on.
Sigma Zt plus 1 plus phi 1 Zt plus phi 2 Zt minus 1.
And then plus the other terms, plus C2 Xt minus 2
plus sigma Zt plus 2 plus phi 1 Zt plus 1 plus phi 2 Zt.
So what have we got?
We finally have an expression, where--
and actually, let's do one more thing.
Let's just kick mu to the other side of the equation.
So I now have an expression for X of t
plus 2, where on the right hand side,
everything depends on known quantities.
So we put it in.
We turn the crank.
We compute the expectation two-time steps ahead.
That will give us our forecast today for two-time steps ahead.
When tomorrow is realized, that forecast
for what will then be one more day ahead is going to change.
And how will it change?
It will be updated by the new observation.
So if today is Monday and I'd like
to know about Wednesday's weather,
I would make a forecast today.
Tomorrow I'll have a new forecast for Wednesday.
And that will change.
It will change by my knowledge of what happened on Tuesday.
But from a mathematical point of view,
we separated things into the form that we want.
We can first take the expectation
with the appropriate conditions.
And second, we can compute forecast error in advance.
And we can compute the mean squared forecast
two steps ahead.
And so that's looking ahead for what
our expected forecast error.
The reason that that's important is
that we want to think not only about distributions.
What's the exact value?
Because that exact value probably won't be realized.
It gives us characteristics of the full distribution
of the actual outcome.
And it lets us have a sense as to how we
should evaluate our forecasts.
So that's an expectation.
Once Wednesday is realized, then we'd like to go back.
And then our Xt plus 2 will be a known quantity.
We can compare it with our forecast.
And, of course, this will differ by some amount,
but if we'd like to improve our forecasting techniques,
our forecasting methodology, and our forecasting quality,
what we do is we look over time.
We take a large collection of forecasts and outcomes.
And we study the statistics of the forecast errors.
So we use forecast errors both in expectation going forward
and to assess forecast quality and look
for improvements going backward once we've
collected the relevant data.