PROFESSOR: At last, we will consider a capital budgeting
example that is slightly richer than the previous examples.
MSW Inc. is a small manufacturing company
selling widgets.
It is now considering the launch of the next generation
of widgets, Turbo-Widgets, or TW for short.
The data on TW is as follows.
TW was developed over the last three years
at an R&D cost of $1 million.
Producing TW requires a new machine,
which costs $2 million.
The new machine lasts 15 years, with a salvage value
of $50,000 at the end.
The new machine can be depreciated linearly to 0
over 10 years.
TW needs to be painted.
This can be done using the excess capacity of existing
painting machines, which cost $30,000 to run, independent
of how much it's used.
Operating cost is $40,000 per year.
TW sales are expected to be $400,000 per year.
But cannibalization will reduce existing sales
of regular widgets to drop by $20,000.
Working capital is $250,000, which
can be recovered at the end of the project.
MSW's tax rate is 34%, and its cost of capital is 10%.
The question we want to answer is should TW be launched now?
Let's go down the list to identify each piece of the cash
flow for this project, its incremental cash flow.
The R&D expense is sunk cost.
It should not be included, of course.
CapEx of $2 million for the machine
is a cash outflow in year 0.
Of course, that should be included.
Depreciation of $2 million over 10 years--
that is, $0.2 million for each year from year
1 to 10, that's for tax purposes.
Salvage value of the machine of $50,000 in year 15
is an income, but fully taxable.
This is because the book value of the machine
already hits 0 in year 10.
The project should not be charged for painting.
The painting machine is running anyway at no additional cost.
Operating costs and sales should be included, of course.
However, loss of existing sales should
be charged to the project against its sales.
Working capital is also an initial investment,
but recovered in year 15.
Adding up the different pieces, we then
have the cash flow of Turbo-Widgets from year 0
to 15 in $1,000.
In year 0, the cash flow is minus $2,000 CapEx
plus $250, the working capital.
That gives us minus $2,250.
In year 1 to 10, the cash flow is after tax profit,
which is $400.
So sales minus $40--
that's the expenses-- minus $20.
That's actually the cannibalization
of existing sales.
And then times 1 minus 0.34--
that's the tax rate--
plus the tax credit from depreciation,
which is 200 times 0.34.
The sum is $292.4 thousand.
From year 11 to 14, there's no more depreciation, no more tax
credit.
The cash flow is just the after tax profit, which is $224.4.
In year 15, the cash flow has three pieces.
The first piece is the after tax profit, which is 224.4.
The second piece is the after tax salvage
value of the machine, which is 50 times 1 minus 0.34.
Because we have to pay taxes on it.
The third piece is the working capital recovered.
Adding them up gives a total of $507.4 thousand.
At the cost of capital of 10%, the NPV of Turbo-Widgets
is minus $57.6 thousand, which is negative.
Therefore, we should not launch it now.
This example merely illustrates some issues
we need to pay attention to informing cash flow
forecasts for a project, given its financials.