PROFESSOR: So now we're going to talk about accounting
for stock issuance.
So we've issued some shares.
It might be in a company's IPO, which
is the first time they issue shares, the Initial Public
Offering, or it might be they've done a secondary offering.
So the accounting for this is-- again,
we're going to keep track first the par value
and then additional paid in capital that's received
in excess of par value.
And we're-- account for those two things separately.
So let's just start off with a simple example.
Suppose that we sell 4 million shares, we get $68 million
in cash, and let's pretend this is a company that
doesn't have any par value.
So the balance sheet equation for this is--
keep track of cash.
So we raise $68 million.
And that $68 million goes into common stock,
or you could also call that additional paid in capital.
So there's no par value here.
Now let's change the transaction just slightly.
And let's pretend that the shares had
a par value of 1/1000 of $1--
so 0.001.
So what would the par value of 4 million shares
be if they had a par value of 1/1000 of $1?
So 4 million shares divided by $1,000 is $4,000.
So the way this transaction would change--
cash will be the same.
Now we're going to have $4,000 worth of par value.
And now our additional paid in capital
is not going to be $68 million.
It's going to be $68 million minus $4,000 in this example.
So that's accounting for stock issuance.
Let's look at how a real company does this.
Tesla, in March of 2017, sold 1.536 million shares of stock.
It got a price of $262 a share.
So this was a secondary offering.
So Tesla came public in 2010.
And it's doing another secondary offering here
to raise some additional money.
So it raised gross proceeds.
So gross proceeds-- there's just 1.536 million shares times $262
a share--
gives you $403 million.
And Tesla has a par value of 1/1000 of $1 per share.
So the way that Tesla would account for this transaction
then is cash went up.
We got $403 million worth of cash.
How much par value was there--
plus $1.536 million divided by 1,000--
is $1,536.
And then additional paid in capital-- it's basically
$403 million minus $1,500, which still gets you to about $403
million when you round it.
And we'll see this transaction as a reminder in Tesla's cash
flow statement.
So Tesla-- 2017 cash flow statement--
their cash flow from financing shows
that they raised $400 million in this common stock offer.
Now, notice there's a difference between the $403 million
we calculated above and the $400 million in cash
that Tesla said--
it raised a difference of $3 million.
And what this generally is is investment banking fees.
So remember, investment banks perform
a service for companies.
They help them raise capital.
And the investment banks, in this case, were paid $3 million
for this service.
So instead of raising $403 million,
Tesla only raised $400 million.
So that's because the underwriting fees
or the investment banking fees.
Now, the stock issuance cost us $3 million
in investment banking fees.
There's basically two ways to account for them.
I'm going to show you both of them briefly.
The first one is to capitalize the issuance costs.
So that means we get $400 million in cash.
We're going to put an asset on our balance sheet
equal to the investment banking fees.
Then we got the common stock at par.
And then we're going to have additional paid
in capital of $403 million.
Now, this is puzzling and a little bad
because you've got an asset, which is your investment
banking fees.
But remember, the intuition of this
is the investment bankers have helped you.
They've created an asset by giving you
access to the capital markets.
And then we're going to reflect that-- the value of that
help on our balance sheet for $3 million.
So some companies will do this.
But what most companies do is what Tesla do--
does-- is just knock the investment banking fees out
of additional paid in capital.
So in that case, the balance sheet entry--
we're still getting $400 million in cash.
Common stock is still $1,536.
In this case, we're going to reduce
the additional paid in capital.
It's not going to be $403 million.
We're going to sense-- immediately expensing
the investment banking fees.
And we just got an additional paid
in capital of $400 million.
So probably most companies choose option 2,
although you will see occasionally
companies doing option 1.
We're going to look at an excerpt
from Tesla's 2017 statement of stockholders' equity.
In this excerpt, they describe their sale
of stock for $262 a share.
As a review, recall that they sold 1.536 million shares
for gross proceeds of about $403 million.
This excerpt shows that issuance costs were $2.854 million,
or about $3 million.
Subtracting these issuance costs gives net proceeds
of about $400 million.
Note that additional paid in capital in this case
is net proceeds of $400 million minus the par value of $1,536,
or approximately $400 million.
Since additional paid in capital and net proceeds
are about the same, we know that Tesla expensed the $3 million
in issuance costs.
If Tesla had capitalized these issuance costs,
additional paid in capital would be $403 million.