PROFESSOR: So we've looked a lot,
as we've been talking about stockholder's equity,
about how changes in equity show up
in the same in the cash flows.
So let's just summarize that briefly here.
So in terms of the cash flow from operations,
as we saw in the Amazon case, if we give stock compensation,
that's a non-cash item.
It's a reduction in net income, but we're
going to add it back to net income
to compute cash flow from operations.
In terms of cash flow from financing,
we're going to see the proceeds from the issuance of stock
as we saw with Tesla.
We're going to see the proceeds from option exercises
we'll see in just a second.
We'll see proceeds from issuance of debt
as we saw in our debt discussions earlier.
We're going to see stock repurchases.
We're going to see debt maturities,
so if debt matures and we have to pay out the debt,
we'll see that in the cash flow from financing.
And we'll also see debt repurchases.
So in the case of Tesla, if we were
to look at their 2017 cash flow statement, at the top there,
you see we're adding back stock compensation expense.
Tesla had stock compensation expense in 2017
of about $467 million.
That's a non-cash item.
You can see in the cash flow from financing,
we see the proceeds from common stock and public offerings.
We see issues of debt, we see repayments of debt,
we see stock option exercises, and we also
see transactions related to capital leases, as well.