PROFESSOR: Now, in terms of computations,
we're going to first work through the basic computation,
which is basic and a little easier.
And then we'll do some wrinkles and talk
about the diluted computation.
So basic EPS, again, is net income
available to common shareholders divided
by the weighted average number of shares outstanding.
And here net income available to common shareholders
is equal to net income minus any income that goes
to non-controlling interest.
Remember, non-controlling interest
are a case if we bought part of a subsidiary,
but not all of it.
The part of it that we don't own is
the non-controlling interest, and it
gets a share of our net income.
So we're going to subtract that off.
We're also going to subtract off any preferred dividends.
So preferred dividends go to preferred shareholders.
What we're interested in is net income to common shareholders.
In terms of computing shares outstanding,
we're just going to do an example here.
So we start off with 180,000 shares outstanding.
We repurchase 30,000 shares.
That leaves us with 150,000 shares outstanding.
Then we do a 3 for 1 split, which causes
the shares to go up to 450,000.
Then we issue 50,000 more shares, and that gives us an ending balance
of 500,000 shares.
So as we talked about with splits,
the first thing we want to do is to put
the shares outstanding on an apples-to-apples basis.
And we want to do is go back and adjust
shares outstanding before the split to reflect the split.
So the split was a 3 for 1 split.
So on January 1, we had 180,000 shares outstanding.
We'll split adjust just that.
That's 540,000.
We repurchased 30,000 shares.
Split adjusted, that's 90,000 shares.
And then we got our stock split, and then we
got our ending balance.
Now, we're going to compute a weighted average.
So we've got our adjusted shares outstanding
in the second column.
Notice that the 540,000 shares from January 1 to March 31
were outstanding for 3/12 of a year and then so on down.
So we're going to weight the shares
by the fraction of the year that they were outstanding.
That gives us the numbers in the far right column.
And then we just add up those additional weighted shares
to come up with.
On average during the year for this company,
there was about 489,000 shares outstanding.
And then we have to now compute net income
available to common shareholders.
Let's pretend the net income was a million two,
but we had $200,000 in preferred dividends.
So that gives us our net income available
to common shareholders of a million dollars.
We got our weighted average shares
that we calculated a moment ago.
So take net income available at common of a million,
divide by 489,000, and that gives us
our basic EPS of $2.04.