PROFESSOR: The biggest use of forward futures and swap
contracts are by financial institutions, like banks
and pension funds, seeking to manage their exposure
to interest rate risk.
This week, we're going to focus on the most
popular and versatile strategies for managing interest rate
risk using these derivatives, combined with cash market
transactions.
Those strategies are based on two characteristics
of a security or portfolio that are
used to quantify the risk arising from the interest rate
volatility-- duration and convexity.
We'll go over the concepts of duration and convexity
and how they can be applied to cash market
positions like a bond portfolio and to derivatives
like swaps and interest rate futures contracts.
Then we'll look at their application
in a very important class of hedging strategies known
as delta and gamma hedging.