PROFESSOR: We have continuous random variables that
don't have discrete outcomes.
They can take an uncountably infinite number of variables.
The classic case is a uniform distribution.
For example, we might think of the interval between 0 and 1
with all values being equally likely.
Because they're uncountably infinite,
the probability of finding any one point,
which is equal likelihood for any other point,
is proportional to 1 over the number
of points, which is infinite.
So the probability of any particular observation is 0.
We say that if a given point has "measure 0", that doesn't mean
it can't be observed.
What it means is that we really should ask a better question.
Rather than asking about the chance
of finding an exact value, an exact real number,
we can ask about the probability that it lies within a range.
And there, for that, we have a probability density function,
p of x, that describes the probability of finding
a value, the particular value x, in an interval with dx.
And in the case of the uniform distribution, p of x
is just a constant.
It's equal to 1.
But more generally, we define the probability
that the random variable x, is observed between two values
a and b, when x is continuous, by taking
the integral between a and b.
Probability distributions need to satisfy two properties.
First, probabilities need to be positive.
Second, they need to sum to 1.
So we don't have a definition of negative probabilities.
But we do require that the probabilities sum to 1.
And we think of that as saying that our sample space is
appropriately designated, and our probability function
is a reasonable description.
If we assign a probability to everything and probability
equals 1, it means that something happens.
So in the case of a discrete distribution,
the probabilities sum to 1.
In the case of the continuous distribution,
they integrate to 1.
We sometimes think about the cumulative distribution
function, which is the partial integral
of a continuous function or a partial sum
of the discrete function.
It's the probability of observing
the random variable, big X, taking
a value less than some particular value, little x.
So we can think of that in the case of a distribution
as integrating in the continuous case,
from minus infinity up to the value x of interest.
And if we let x go to infinity, that then
covers the entire support of the probability density.
And it should be equal to 1.
Obviously, this is closely related to p of x.
And we can go backwards just by differentiating.
So because f is the integral of p,
we have the p is the derivative of f.
Now that's trivial from the definition.
But there are certain cases where
it's easier to construct f than p,
and this formula lets us recover p by differentiating
the formula for f.
Also, just from the fundamental theorem of calculus,
there's a convenient formula for the probability.
If we know what big F is, if we know
what the CDF, the cumulative distribution function
is for a given distribution, then we can just
take f of b minus f of a.
That computes the value between the two limits of integration.
It's the same value that we would
have for doing the definite integral from a to b.
Sometimes we'll want to change variables.
And if we do that, we need to be aware that the probability
density is the density in the sense
that we need to integrate it.
So we need to change not only the x in p of x,
but we need to change x in the differential that
accompanies it.
So the rule for change of variables is very simple--
that if we change variables, if we replace
x by y, which is some function of x, then
we define a new probability distribution for y
simply by saying that g of y dy, whatever g of y is,
had better capture the same thing as p of x dx.
So that means that p of x is of why do
y we divide both sides by dy.
And we can write this saying g of y
is p of x divided by dy/dx.
Now, if we're given a function y of x,
we can compute the derivative.
We take its absolute value in the event
that y is a decreasing function of x.
So probabilities, remember, need to be positive.
If our change of variables goes in the opposite direction,
if it decreases as a function of x,
the absolute value makes sure that we get a positive sign.
And we need to take special care and break things up piecewise,
in the event the y of x changes sign,
that there are places where the derivative vanishes.
But that's not really going to happen
in the financial application.