PROFESSOR: We use probabilities to serve
as weights for computing weighted averages.
And these, we call expectations.
These expectations are going to be
very important for what we do.
In fact, our next slide, our next proposition
is going to give us a shortcut through a lot
of complex mathematics to get straight to the analytics we
want in terms of using expectation values instead
of full probability distributions.
So the important thing is that an expectation value
can be thought of as a kind of a weighted average.
In the discrete case for any function,
f of x, the expectation that I write with E and brackets
around it, is a weighted average over the possible states,
the possible allowed values of the random variable, x
sub k, however many there are.
And it's the value of f at each of the possible values
of the random variable, weighted by the probability of observing
that variable.
So it's a weighted average.
If f is 1, identically, then, the expectation of 1
has to be equal to 1, because the probabilities sum to 1.
In the continuous case, it's even more elegant.
This just becomes an integral.
So we integrate f of x times p of x dx.
And again, if f is just 1, then the integral of p of x dx
has to be equal to 1, the normalization of probability,
and we get 1.
So expectations are weighted averages of functions
with probability numbers.
But the important thing is that they're numbers,
they're not functions.
We do a definite integral.
We do a definite sum.
So p of x is a function.
The expectation of some function of x, though, is just a number.
The classic example is the mean of the distribution,
which is just the expectation of the random variable itself.
And we have lots of different notations for expectations,
and I'll just give you a few of them.
One of them, for the mean in particular,
is often denoted by mu.
And that's going to be our definition for E of x.
Sometimes this is written as x-bar.
Sometimes it's also written is x inside angle brackets.
All of these things mean the expectation
of x for the mean value.
And we'll use the angle brackets a little bit more just when we
want to simplify the notation.
Generally, we'll be using the E notation.
So in this case, in the case of the discrete,
it means the sum of x times p of x.
In the integral case, it just means x p of x dx.
So in the case of a discrete sum--
if there are a finite number of states,
we're always going to get a finite result.
When we have integrals, even though we require
that p of x be an integrable function,
it's possible that x p of x might not
have a convergent integral.
So it is possible to have a perfectly well-behaved
probability distribution where the mean doesn't necessarily
exist.
Similarly, we can generalize to the moments of a distribution.
And those might not exist in the case
of a continuous distribution.
So the moments just generalize.
Instead of e of x, we take the expectation of x to a power--
in this case, x to the lth power.
So this is our definition of the lth moment.
And you might not be surprised to know
that if we know all of the moments,
then we can read to reconstruct the full probability
distribution itself.
Think of it as a kind of Taylor's theorem.
And we'll see that when we look at generating functionals.
So we can go back and forth from moments
to the full distribution.
But if we're interested in a particular moment,
here's the formula for how we compute it.
So expectation of x to any power is
for the continuous case, integral
of x to the l p of x dx.
Now, the most important property of the expectation operator--
because it's either a sum or an integral,
is that it obeys linearity.
And linearity means we have the following two properties--
first, the expectation of any scalar, c, times any function
f, is just the scalar times the expectation.
And if we have the sum of any two functions, f and g,
the expectation of the sum is the sum of the expectations.
That's simple property, that the sum of that expectation
is the expectation of the sum, will
let us bypass a lot of complicated calculations
that we'd rather cut through.
Now, there are some moments and algebraic functions
of moments that are particularly interesting.
And maybe the most important one in finance
is the variance or its square root,
which is a standard deviation.
So the variance is related to the expectation
of x squared by the expectation of x
squared minus the square of the expectation.
But to get there, let's look at how we formally define it.
The variance of x is the expectation
of x minus its mean, the whole quantity squared.
So if x were not random at all and were equal to m,
this would be equal to 0.
We look at x minus mu to measure how much x
deviates from its mean value.
We take the square so that we don't
have positive and negative fluctuations canceling
each other out.
Once we have this definition, the rest of this
is just algebra.
So what we do is we expand out the quantity in parentheses--
x minus quantity squared.
We expand it out it's a quadratic.
We use our rule for linearity, that the expectation of the sum
is the sum of an expectation.
So we get the expectation of x squared
minus 2mu times the expectation of x plus mu squared.
This is just a constant.
Expectation of x squared minus--
now, I have minus 2mu, you but e of x is mu.
So this is minus 2mu squared plus minus square, gives me
a minus mu squared.
And of course, mu squared is the same thing as the expectation
of x squared.
So this is a good rule for calculation.
The variance is the expectation of the square minus the square
of the expectation.
And we often use the square root of the variance, which
plays the role of the volatility in looking
at financial processes.
And one reason we do that is that the square root
has the same units.
It has the same dimensions.
We measure it the same way as we do the random variable itself.
So if x is in dollars, sigma is in dollars.
If x is annualized return, then the standard deviation
is also in the same units.
So we might say, for example, that a given stock has
an expected return, a mean return in a probability
distribution of 10% per year, with a sigma or standard
deviation of 30% per year, which is a little bit easier
than the square of 30% for the variance.
Now the moments and particular combinations,
linear combinations, of them, help
us characterize some of the properties of a probability
distribution.
And we're going to see that we're
going to get quite far using only a few
of the lower moments.
And we won't need all the details
of the full function, p of x.
There's a lot of universality in low moments.
So in addition to the variance and the mean,
the next two moments of interest are the main ones.
Then we can kind of stop.
The third moment gives us what's called the skewness.
And the skewness is an asymmetry parameter.
It tells us whether we're more or less
likely to see things above the mean versus below the mean.
So a skewness of 0 is what we'll find if a probability
distribution is symmetric.
And that's because it depends on an odd power of x minus mu.
Notice that after the variance, the skewness
is defined in a way that's dimensionless.
That is if x is in units of dollars or of return,
sigma has the same units of 3 powers in the numerator, 3
in the denominator.
So s is a pure number.
Similarly, the kurtosis involves the fourth power.
And to make it dimensionless, I divide by four powers of sigma.
Sometimes you'll see this called the excess kurtosis,
with the minus 3 subtract it off,
and the non-excess kurtosis, just without the minus 3.
We like this definition because as we'll, see,
for Gaussian distributions, for a normal distribution,
the skewness and the kurtosis measured in this way
are both equal to 0.