PROFESSOR: What if we've got more than one random variable,
as we often do?
Well, if we have two random variables,
they could be independent, but they might not be independent.
And one of the measures we have for how
two different random variables might be related to each other
is to look at an expectation, as well.
It's to look at the expectation of a bilinear product.
So the covariance of two random variables x and y,
which I sometimes write in this notation, covariance
of x and y, is the expectation of x minus its mean,
times y minus its mean.
Now if you expand this out and do the same trick
that we did for the variance, you
find that this can be simplified to be
the expectation of the product minus the product
of the expectations for two variables, x and y.
This has units, unsurprisingly, the units
of x times units of y.
So if x is in dollars and y is in yen,
the product is going to be in dollars times yen.
We often like to have things in dimensionless units.
So we define the correlation to be the covariance divided
by the square root of the variance of x
and the square root of the variance of y.
That makes the correlation a dimensionless number.
And in fact, it's bounded between minus 1 and plus 1
for the correlation of two random variables.
Notice that we can rewrite this by taking
the square root of the variances,
writing that as sigma x, sigma y.
Because those are constants, I can bring them
inside the expectation.
And I can write the correlation as an expectation
in this interesting way.
It's the expectation of x minus mu over sigma times y
minus mu over sigma, where the mu and the sigma
are for the y distribution.
And each of these quantities in parentheses,
you'll notice has 0 mean, because I've subtracted off
its mean.
And it has unit variance, because I've
divided by the variance.
Now if the random variables are independent of each other,
then these expectations factorize, and we'll get 0.
So if the variables, x and y, are independent,
then they're covariance and correlation are 0.
What about the other way around?
Well, the other way around is different.
So it is possible to have vanishing covariance,
but not have the variables be independent. .
Let's take a look at a quick example.
If we have x to be a function that takes,
let's say, plus or minus a with probability p1,
and it takes plus or minus b with probability p2,
then we can see that it's mean has to be 0,
simply because it's symmetric.
It's equally likely to have a positive number
and a negative number.
Now what if we define y to be x squared?
So if y is a function of x, it's not independent.
It's completely dependent.
If we know what x is, then we know what y is.
It's the square the value of x.
So in this case, this would be a squared with probability 2pi1,
because whether it's plus or minus a, each
with probability pi, y is going to have value a squared--
and similarly for b.
So its mean is not going to be 0 because y
is a positive function, and we can compute its mean.
And now if we go and compute the covariance,
and we put in the numbers, we take the probability
weighted average of the functions,
we find that the covariance of x and y is 0.
So if the covariance vanishes, it does not imply independence.
Independence implies vanishing covariance, but not
the other way around.
So let's summarize-- random variables are functions
that assign probability to events or outcomes
in the sample space.
They can be discrete.
They can be continuous.
They can be a mix of both.
We describe the probabilities by a probability distribution,
which could be discrete.
It can be continuous, but either way, it's sums
or it integrates to 1, and the values are always positive.
Expected values or expectations-- and I'll
use those interchangeably-- are weighted averages, where
the weights are taken from the probabilities.
The moment of a distribution are the expectation,
not of some general function, but in particular, of powers
of the random variable.
The first power, x to the 1, gives us the mean.
X squared minus the constant gives us the variance.
We can do x cubed, x to the fourth, and so on.
So the variance, skewness, and kurtosis
are simple functions of the moments that are used,
the second, third, and fourth moments of the distribution,
and they help us characterize the shape of the distribution.
And if there are multiple random variables,
we define using expectations again, the covariance
and the correlation.
And for independent random variables, those vanish.