PROFESSOR: Let's take a quick look
at some of the common distributions
that we see in finance.
First, uniform probability distribution
is always our starting test case.
The probability density p of x is equal to 1
if x is in the interval between 0 and 1, and 0 otherwise.
We compute the probability for X to lie between two values
a and b by computing the interval.
So this one is obviously just b minus a.
How do we get the cumulative distribution function
from minus infinity to x?
Assuming that we're inside the interval where
x is between 0 and 1, this is just the function x itself.
What about moments?
Well, we do the integrals The mean is the integral
of x p of x dx, and that's 1/2.
We can obviously do these integrals
in closed form for any value.
So for x to the l, we get the l-th moment is 1 over l plus 1.
And for the variance, for sigma squared, we use our definition.
It's the integral of p of x, which is 1,
times x minus the mean, so x minus 1/2 quantity squared.
Do the integral, and we get 1/12.
The binomial distribution is very important
since it describes random walks and it's
used in the binomial tree model for option pricing.
So the binomial distribution provides a model for anything
that has two possible outcomes-- success or failure,
they're typically called.
But we could be thinking of heads or tails,
we could be thinking of something going up or down,
or left or right, or two possible outcomes, win or lose.
But they don't need to be symmetric.
So for example, if we put our money on 19 in roulette,
it could be 19 is one state and not-19 is the other state.
So lots of possible examples where we
have two states of the world.
What we do is we define the probability for one state
to be-- we'll call it p-- the probability
for the complementary state to be 1 minus p,
and then we'll imagine that we repeat
this a certain number of times.
And we want to know-- our question for the binomial
distribution is--
how many successes and failures do we
have out of the given number of experiments,
out of the given number of trials?
So imagine that we do the experiment n times.
And we want to know, what's the probability, if I do this n
times, of observing k successes and n minus k failures?
So if I flip a coin 10 times in a row, n is equal to 10.
If I want to know the probability
of getting 5 heads and 5 tails, I would take k equals 5.
If I want to know about getting 2 heads and 8 tails,
I would take k equals 2.
So how do we compute the probability?
Well, it depends.
Probability is a function that depends on k.
But it has two parameters, n and p, that are held fixed.
So n could be 10, p could be 1/2,
for the example of flipping a fair coin.
But actually, n can be any integer,
and p can be any number between 0 and 1.
So we can see that if we want all possible ways
that in n trials we could have k successes,
the number of ways of doing that is n
choose k-- n factorial over k factorial n minus k factorial.
And by properties of combinatorics and factorials,
that's the same as n choose n minus k, of course.
Now, we're going to weight that by the probability of success
to the k-th power.
Because these are independent events happening separately,
the probability of having it happen k times are it
needed to happen each of k times.
So the probabilities multiply.
So in the case where I have k successes and n minus k
failures, I'm going to have p raised to the k,
q raised to the n minus k will be that probability
of a particular event, and the multiplicity
will be n choose k.
Now, what's the mean of that expectation?
Well, we could compute it.
And let me just show you how it's done the hard way.
And very shortly, we'll find a much easier way
to do it, which will generalize.
And that's what we'll be doing for the rest
of our calculations.
It's both easier to compute and it opens doors
to some other properties of stochastic processes.
So the hard way is we use the definition.
So the definition is that we take
the mean is defined as the expectation of X.
So we take the value of X, we sum over all possibilities.
We take the value times the probability
of finding that value.
So we could have k could be 0 successes up through infinity,
theoretically, and we would compute this sum.
Of course, it can't really go to infinity.
If we have n trials, k can either be 0 through n--
so we can cut off our sum at n on the upper end of the limit.
And if k is equal to 0, that term
is not going to show up either, because k
equals 0 would just drop out because of this factor here.
So let's write our sum from k equals 1 to n
and then plug in our definition.
So we've got our factorial, k factorial n minus k factorial
on the bottom, n factorial in the numerator times the k
prefactor here, p to the k, q to the n minus k.
I can rearrange the terms a little bit.
I can cancel a k in the numerator and the denominator
here.
See if my magic screen will cooperate.
Here and here, we can cancel out a k to get k minus 1 factorial.
And now to neaten things up, I'd like to write this as n minus 1
factorial times n.
That's the same thing as n factorial.
So written in this way, I'm getting
ready to shift the variables.
So I've written this in terms of n minus 1 choose k minus 1.
And I've pulled a factor of n out in front,
and I'm also going to go ahead and pull a factor of p
out in front as well, so that the coefficient up here is
k minus 1.
I can then redefine my variables, k prime and n prime.
I notice this whole expression right here
is the same thing as my function f, just
in terms of new variables k prime and n prime,
where k prime is k minus 1, n prime is n minus 1.
And then that entire summation is just equal to 1.
So after going through all the combinatorics, all
the shifting around of variables,
I get a very simple result--
that the mean value is n times p.
And if you think about it, of course it is.
We have probability p of seeing a success.
Let's say the probability is 1/10.
We maybe do the experiment 100 times.
What would we expect to see?
Probably about 1/10 of 100 mean value of n times p.