PROFESSOR: The next distribution that's common everywhere
in finance and statistics and in many other areas
of applied mathematics is the Gaussian distribution
or the normal distribution.
And I'll use the two terms interchangeably.
So the normal distribution is the famous bell curve
that we see over here, OK?
So the bell curve is symmetric around 0.
It has a width like, goes all the way out
to minus infinity and plus infinity.
So it's unbounded.
But most of its support--
99% of its support lies between plus and minus 3.
And the tails get short very quickly.
What's the functional form of it?
Well, it's e to the minus x squared.
Specifically, we can write this as e to the minus x
minus mu quantity squared over 2 sigma squared.
And mu and sigma have a particular meaning.
If we set mu to 0 and sigma equal to 1,
we would have this standardized form, which
I've written in terms of z.
And generally, I'll try to reserve z for this special form
for this standardized random variable where in terms of z,
this is peaked at 0.
And its width-- its standard deviation,
which we can compute, is equal to 1.
If I replace z by x minus mu divided by sigma,
I can recover this form here.
And if I remember to use my change of variables formula,
that's where this sigma squared under the square root
in the denominator comes from.
But there's a good physical interpretation of mu and sigma.
So the mu is the center of the distribution.
Because exponential will decrease as its argument
increases, the largest value the exponential takes
is when either z vanishes down here or when x is equal to mu.
And that corresponds to the peak of the distribution here.
Or at the peak of these different distributions,
each of which is computed for a different value of mu,
mu tells you where the center of the distribution is.
So if we want to shift the distribution left or right,
we change mu.
If we want to change the width of the distribution,
we change sigma.
A small sigma is a narrow distribution.
A large sigma is a wide distribution
because the area under the curve needs
to equal 1, the curve if it's wide,
it's going to be lower down.
And if the sigma is narrow, then it's going to be peaked.
And the center will be higher.
There are a couple of handy formulas
for checking the normalization of the Gaussian.
And you should get familiar with doing small scale integrals.
We'll be doing them a bit.
But handy formula for getting the normalization
are a definite integral with this generating function.
There's a trick for doing this using polar coordinates.
But for right now, you just need to know the result
because you can get everything you need from this that if you
look at the integral of e to the minus ax squared,
we notice that this is a definite integral.
But it contains a as a constant under the integral.
So the integral is a function of a.
And the function is square root of pi over a.
And that's what gives us that normalization factor,
the 1 over square root of 2 pi sigma squared.
And so that when we integrate the probability density,
it integrates to one the way it has to.
And if we need to get higher moments,
we can do it by differentiating.
So, for example, you notice that if I differentiate the integral
with respect to the parameter, if I compute dI da--
or actually minus dI da, OK, I can move the derivative
inside the integral.
The coefficient of a in the exponential is x squared.
And that gives me the integral of a squared
e to the minus ax squared.
And that we recognize as the expectation of x squared.
So I can get moments by taking derivatives.
And we'll see how to generalize this as well.
What about the cumulative distribution function?
Well, F of z in this case, which is sometimes known as capital
phi--
in some places, you'll see it written with the letter N
and sometimes related to a function known
as the error function-- is a definite integral.
We integrate from minus infinity to infinity [correction: z]
of e to the minus z' squared over 2.
And that gives us this distribution function.
You notice that if we differentiate the integral
we get back our probability density.
So this gives us the probability that the random variable
will be between any two points.
Or for F of z itself that it will be
equal to the given z or less.
The log-normal distribution shows up in finance as well.
We often look at logarithmic returns.
And our standard model for return distributions on assets
is a starting point to see if the logarithmic returns might
be normally distributed.
And that distribution is called the log-normal distribution.
The way it's defined mathematically
is simply to define X to be log of Y.
And we can compute x is log of y here
for a probability density and substitution,
apply change of variable formula.
And we see that we get this form right here.
Now, computationally, this is just to change the variable.
So if we're going to compute moments,
we can use whichever variables we prefer.
And the usual application of this is in looking at returns.
So we often have a relationship between the simple returns
that we designate by R, simple returns on an asset.
And the logarithmic returns are defined
to be e to the little r minus 1 is big R.
We'll see in more detail how that works with pricing.
But we can compute with respect to either distribution.
Remember that the moments are just numbers.
And whichever way we choose to do the integral-- whatever
changes the variables we make in the integral--
it isn't going to change the final result.