PROFESSOR: The Poisson distribution
shows up in looking typically at the arrival of events
or at jump processes.
So we look for the arrival of a jump,
maybe in a market price, or the arrival of an event,
such as a credit default or customers
arriving or customers departing, for orders
arriving at an exchange.
So we often apply it where we're thinking
of continuous time and discrete events arriving
at some unknown interval.
And we use a Poisson distribution
to model those intervals.
So mathematically, the Poisson distribution
has two parameters, two values.
And sometimes it's convenient to think of it as a function
of one or the other.
But we have k, which is an integer, and lambda, which
is a real valued variable.
And the probability is e to the minus lambda, lambda
to the k over k factorial.
So when we're looking at arrivals,
we apply that by thinking of lambda
as being an arrival rate.
And we replace lambda by lambda t
as being the number of events that
might arrive during a particular time interval, t.
And we would use this probability distribution.
What are its properties?
Well, the mean value we just compute.
We sum over k, over all the possible k's times
the probability of observing each k.
And we find the expectation of X, the average value of k,
is just equal to lambda.
And if we do the calculation for the second moment,
we do the math and we compute this sum.
And we find that it's lambda plus lambda squared.
If we then go and compute the variance--
remember that the variance is the expectation of the square,
lambda plus lambda squared, minus the square
of the variance, which is lambda quantity squared.
And what we get is that sigma squared
is equal to the lambda, which is actually
the same thing as the mean, interestingly.
Now, the Poisson distribution is also a special case.
It's the limiting distribution when n goes to infinity,
of the binomial distribution, in this special case where
we let n go to infinity and the probability go to 0,
holding their product fixed.
So in that case, we can show that we recovered the parcel
distribution.
And an example of where we could apply it numerically
as a useful distribution-- because the binomial
distribution is pretty hard to compute
with all those factorial when n gets large.
So this is an easy thing to compute.
Remember the k is typically going to be a small number.
But n going to infinity going to 0
or n very large, p very small, we can just take their product,
hold it fixed, and get a good calculation,
a good approximation from the Poisson distribution.
For example, if we have a classroom that has,
let's say 65 students and we ask who has a birthday on a given
day, if we assume birthdays are equally likely to be
on any day of the year, an approximation, 1/365,
65 students, we would compute lambda as n times p.
We could ask is 65 close to infinity.
Well, let's take a look.
If we compute n times p for this particular values,
we get the lambda is 0.178.
And if we compute the exact Poisson probability
and compare it to what we would get
from the exact binomial formula, we compare it
to the Poisson approximation, we find out
for 0, 1, and 2, that these approximations are pretty good.
They're good to three decimal places at least.
And that's only for an n of 65.
The Poisson distribution does have different qualitative
behaviors depending on the value of lambda.
So when lambda is small, the values
are always decreasing in k.
When lambda gets to be above 1--
and here, I've taken this upper graph
is the value that we used in our previous birthday example--
down below, I multiplied it by a factor of 10.
And now we see that when lambda is greater than 1,
it's a skewed distribution with the long tail off to the right.
And here is our mean value, is lambda.
And we notice that we said that our mean value was
going to be lambda.
If lambda is less than 1, then that's
why the whole distribution is bunched up
on the left-hand side.
When lambda is greater than 1--
in this case, lambda is 2.
And we see that the p value is around 2.
There are a bunch of combinatorial formulas
if you want to play around with those.
I've just put these in here for completeness.
And you can check.
But as I said, we've got a couple of tricks
up our sleeve that will save us from doing
a lot of combinatorics for computing moments in a bit.
Finally, I want to say that when it
comes to looking at distributions,
that not all distributions are as well behaved.
And some of them are going to be exceptions to our rule
about being able to only look at moments.
And the problem is, the thing that
happens that's interesting, is that sometimes those moments
don't exist.
And I mentioned before, that we could try to compute the mean
and have the integral diverge.
Well, here's another example of that.
Here's a very nice looking probability distribution
from a distance or at a low resolution monitor.
You might think this looks like a bell curve.
But it's not.
So this distribution is given by this function.
It's a constant times that constant squared plus x
squared.
And asymptotically, as x gets large,
it doesn't behave like a Gaussian that
falls like e minus x squared.
It falls off much more slowly with a power.
So asymptotically as x goes to plus or minus infinity,
this function decreases as 1 over x squared.
And you can see what the problem is right away.
If we want to compute the expectation of x squared,
the integral won't converge.
If we want to compute even the expectation of x
or of x the fourth and x to the eighth,
the integral is going to diverge wildly.
So the probability distribution is fine.
It sums to 1.
There's no problem.
We can compute the probability of being in a given area.
But none of the moments exist.
If we were to see things like this in data,
if we were to look at observations like let's say,
stock returns that were drawn from a distribution,
such as this that had power-law tails.
What would we see?
Well, qualitatively, like a normal distribution,
most of the event, we'd see a single peak.
Most of the events are near the center.
But fat tails means that extreme events
occur quite likely, much, much more often than
under a Gaussian distribution.
They don't occur that often.
After all, the tails that values out
there are smaller than the central values.
But the area under the curve going out from any given point
is divergent.
The weighted averages are divergent so
that the power-law tails are giving us
more and more of the contributions
to analytical quantities of interest.
And if we were to try to estimate the volatility using
our standard metrics, we would get finite numbers
for any finite number of observations.
But as we increase the number of observations,
rather than having convergence, we
would see divergence in the results.
So quick summary-- some common probability
distributions that you've seen before in your probability
and statistics classes.
These are the main ones that are important in finance--
uniform distribution, binomial, Poisson, normal, and Lognormal.
These all have well-defined moments,
or some interesting limits where we can go from one of them
to another.
And they appear in all kinds of applications-- option pricing,
credit defaults, jump processes, lots
of models of asset pricing, and a forecast in future returns.
The Gaussian distribution is the most special
of all because of the Central Limit Theorem,
which we'll see the Gaussian distributions is universal.
It shows up in places, even where we might not normally
expect them.
Picking which distribution to use for modeling a given
problem partly depends on the theory and motivation
behind the problem that we're looking at,
but it always depends on the empirical behavior.
So we can't just postulate that things are normal
and that they are log normally distributed
and assume that all will go well.
We'll need to check that that's how the real world behaves.