PROFESSOR: Now, that's for a special case of a portfolio.
And I said we'd look at a large number.
If we take a look at two random variables
and we want to compute the full distribution,
I said that we could do that, rather than just computing
the mean and the variance.
But it does get complicated pretty quickly.
Let's start with the simplest case.
The simplest case would be two random variables.
And two is not a big number.
And let's let them both be uniformly distributed.
So to compute the probability function--
which is going to have this shape down here by the time
we're done, this is our result--
what I do is I compute the cumulative distribution
function.
I have to do a double integral in dx and dy.
I have to pick particular regions of integration.
And I have to do this complicated integral, which
is known as a convolution.
But I can do it in closed form for two variables.
I get this result here.
And it looks the probability distribution
has this triangular shape.
And it's done.
So we've got it.
So it can be done in this case.
But now imagine doing this for three,
four, five, six variables.
Each one is going to look different.
So that's more work than we want to do,
and it's not going to be necessary.
It's both more work and less intuition.
However, if we just want to check our intuition
and run a quick numerical simulation to take
a look at this, we can do this here,
with this command in the R programming language.
And I'd encourage you to setup and install R and RStudio
and to run this.
The function that we want here that we'll
be seeing when we discuss Montecarlo
is, pick a random variable from a uniform distribution.
So this looks like it says "run if,"
but it's "r unif," from uniform distribution.
So here, I've picked 10,000, excuse me,
100,000 random numbers for X_1 I picked 100,000 random numbers
for X_2 And I'm looking at a histogram that gives me
a discrete approximation to the probability
distribution for their sum.
And you can see that it looks approximately
like the triangular distribution that we
solved for in closed form.
Now, let's come back to the binomial distribution
that I talked about earlier where
we computed the mean value doing a lot of combinatorics
and shifting around the variables in some kind
of mysterious ways.
If we want the mean and the variance
in the binomial distribution the easy way,
we just apply linearity to a sum.
So how do we think of the sum?
We said that we wanted to compute successes
as positive successful outcomes.
And we wanted to count them up versus the number of failures.
So one way we can do that is by having the variable X_1 X_2
X_3 represent the outcome of the first, second, or third
experiment.
And we'll let a plus 1 designate a success,
zero designates a failure.
And then adding together all the axes
is a variable, S, that counts the number of successes.
And notice it doesn't matter in what order they occur.
If I get success, success, fail, fail, fail, fail, fail,
it doesn't matter where those two successes come.
It could be fail, fail, fail, fail, fail, success, success.
Anywhere they are, they get the same value of S
So what's the expectation of S?
What's our mean value?
Expectation of the sum is the sum of the expectations.
And each of these is equal to p, because I
have probability p of getting a 1, probability 1 minus
p of getting a 0.
So the expectation of X_1 is p.
The expectation of X_2 is p.
Each of the expectations is p.
I've got n of them, n times p.
We're done.
OK?
So I've shown that down here.
So the expectation of X_1 is p.
And we're going to do the variance in a moment.
So let's continue the expectation of X_1 squared.
How do we compute it?
We use our rule that the expectation
is the probability-weighted average of the thing
inside the expectation.
So with probability p, I get a 1.
1 squared is 1.
Probability q, I get 0 squared, and that gives me a p.
OK?
So the expectation of any of the X's is p.
The probability of any of the X squareds is p.
And if I take two different X's, the expectation of X_1
times X_2, well, now they're independent random variables.
So they could both be 1, with probability p squared.
p that the the first one is a success, p
that the second one's a success, is p squared.
And then I would multiply that times X_1 being 1 and X_2
being 1.
And then everything else here, success
fail, fail success, and fail fail,
those all have 0's in them.
So those all drop out.
So the only term that survives is this one,
and that gives me this result.
So because these X's are independent of each other,
and because they're identically distributed--
any one of the X_1 is the same as X_2 Or X_3 or X_7--
I have these results and I can apply them.
So now let's apply this for the calculation of the variance.
We're just going to do a little bit of algebra.
It's almost as easy, no combinatorics involved.
Well, a little bit of combinatorics.
But no factorials, not like we had before.
So the definition of our variance
is that the expectation of the random variable
minus its mean quantity squared.
Or it's the expectation of the variable
squared minus the mean squared.
So that's what we use here.
We can expand out this sum into n terms with an X squared.
So these are all going to be identical.
They're going to be n terms.
I'm going to have X_1 squared, X_2 squared, X_3 squared.
I'm going to have n of them.
So let me just take n times the first one.
And then I'm going to have the cross terms.
I'm going to have n choose two possibilities.
But actually, I'm going to get X_1 X_2 and X_2 X_1.
So I'm going to have twice n choose two, which just gives me
n times n minus 1 cross terms.
OK?
And each of the cross terms is going to be the same as 1 2.
So 1 2 is the same as 2 3 is the same as 4 6.
They're all the same.
So I'm going to get n times p plus n n minus 1 times p
squared.
And then I'm going to subtract off my previous result squared,
which is np quantity squared.
And when I combine the terms, I get my final result, npq,
or our final, final result that the standard deviation
is the square root of n, square root of n times p times q.
Remember that p and q, q is 1 minus p. p and q are constant.
So this says that the variance is proportional to n
and that the standard deviation is
proportional to the square root of n.