PROFESSOR: Now, in expanding n, we'll
often want to take a look at what happens as n increases.
And I'd like to show you that in pictures right now
on the computer, doing a simulation in R.
And for the full binomial distribution,
we run into a problem when we put it
on the computer, which is that if we write out
all the factorials, the factorials quickly
overrun the machine limit.
But the combinations are usually well behaved,
so we use a function that's built for this purpose.
We'll use the function in R called choose.
So choose(n,k) is what you would expect.
It's n choose k in a way that doesn't blow up
for moderate values.
And dbinom is the distribution function
for the binomial of k, n, p using the same definitions
that we had here.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to pick
a particular set of values.
I'm going to get n equal 1, 2, and then we're
going to keep going.
I'm going to jump.
We're not going to every single value of n.
But I want to start at n equals 1, 2, 5,
and quickly get to 1,000, and I'd
like to see what happens to the binomial distribution
as n gets large, holding p and q fixed.
And the values I'm going to pick, we'll let p equal 10%
and we'll let q, therefore, equal 90%.
So we have a 10% chance of success.
And remember, the binomial distribution tells us
if I've got a 10% chance of success per trial,
if I do n trials, what's the probability of getting 0
through n successes?
So if I've got 1--
if I run n equals 1, I could either have 0 or 1.
And if it's a 10% chance of success,
I have a 90% chance of failure.
And here they are.
So this is a 90% failure.
Probability of 0.
And here's a 10% chance of getting 1.
For n equals 2, I still have 81% chance of failure.
I have a 1% chance of two successes,
and the rest of the probability distribution
is here that I have one success and one failure.
This is for n equals 5.
n equals 10.
And notice that when we've gotten--
once we get to n equals 10, the largest value
now is not the smallest value.
So instead of the whole probability distribution
being bunched up to the left-hand side,
where's the mean value?
n times p.
p is 10%, n is 10, it's at 1.
That's right here at the largest value in the distribution.
Let's keep going.
This is for 20, 50, 100.
And now by the time we get to 100, take a look at there's
this large tail off to the right-hand side, which
isn't even visible because these are
less than 1 pixel high with the resolution of your screen.
So it's possible in 100 trials, in this case for n equals 100,
that you might get more than 24 trials.
But the probability is so small that we
can't see it on this scale.
Notice something else interesting is going on.
This distribution, where it is active, first of all,
it's peaked around where?
It's around 10.
p times n is 10, and that's about where the peak is.
But notice the distribution for the part of it
that's noticeably non-zero is looking much more symmetric
between the values less than 10 and the values above 10
if we don't pay attention to this big right tail over here.
And this is for 1,000, where we have things centered on 100.
And again, the distribution is getting
very tall and very narrow.
So for fixed p, the distribution initially decreases.
As n increases, the distribution stays
centered near np, which is consistent with what
we computed analytically for the mean value.
The distribution gets narrower and more symmetric.
And this is an illustration of two important limit theorems,
just done in pictures.
We haven't done a mathematical derivation by any means.
The first one is known as the law of large numbers.
The law of large numbers says that as the number of trials
gets large, you're going to see the mean value of the number
of the realizations in experiments
is going to approach a theoretical mean.
Another way to say that is that the probability of observing
the mean deviating from--
the average value deviating from the mean value,
the expectation of the probability distribution
goes to 0.
And that's why the probability distribution is narrowing
around that mean value.
The other one is the central limit theorem.
The central limit theorem says that as we
add more and more variables, the shape of the distribution
approaches a Gaussian distribution,
or a normal distribution.
Now, to see that a little bit more clearly,
let's change variables to what I'll call a scaling variable.
And what I'm going to do is because as n gets large,
the interesting value of k is going to be the one near np,
near the mean, let's pick a value that's centered
right around where we want it.
So I'm going to define this scaling variable z to be--
I'm going to use this to replace k.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going
to subtract off the mean value.
So the numerator, k minus np, says
how far my k is away from the expected
value, which is n times p.
And then I'm going to divide it by the standard deviation.
So that gives me kind of units as to how far away I am so
that that also scales with n.
And let's see what happens if I do that.
And the code is here, which you can take and copy and paste
from the website, or you can retype it--
it's just a couple of lines of code-- and run it yourself.
Or I'm sure you can write better code than mine.
So give it a try.
Let's look in pictures at what happens now.
So starting out, we see the same picture--
n equals 1, n equals 2, n equals 5, n equals 10.
And now what's happening is we've recentered things
so that the whole distribution is staying
on a similar kind of scale.
As we keep going, n equals 20, n equals 50, 100, and 1,000.
And now we've got something that looks symmetric.
It looks Gaussian.
It's our favorite bell curve.
Now, it's not exactly the bell curve, to be sure.
It doesn't go to minus infinity or plus infinity.
It only goes to 0 on the left and the most
we could be is 1,000 on the right.
So the midpoint is centered where we'd expect,
at n times p around 100, but it is not the exact Gaussian
distribution.
It looks like it just because of the scale on the computer.
We don't see the behavior of the tails.
We need different graphics, transfer it--
different plots with different transformations,
such as qqPlot to see the behavior of the tails
or to look more carefully and analytically.
But in the bulk of the distribution
we've recovered, we see the central limit
theorem in action, where adding together
a bunch of non-Gaussian random variables,
non-normal variables, each of the variables
also is very skewed.
It's 10-90%, so it's not equally likely up or down.
Nevertheless, when we add 1,000 of them together,
we get something that looks Gaussian.
So this is what's going on with the central limit theorem.
So the distribution, if we wanted
to write down an approximation for what
the limiting distribution is, we could approximate our function
f of k and n, p by introducing the scaling variable z sub
k as I've defined it.
And in terms of z sub k--
so we could substitute in those values--
this function is approximated by a standard Gaussian
distribution, 1 over square root of 2pi, e
to the minus z squared over 2.
We can see that this is a good approximation in lots
of practical examples.
Here's one that we took a look at it at Sloan
when we were trying to figure out
if there were enough Bloomberg terminals for the students,
back when we used to show up in the building
before the pandemic.
And the class size for a master of finance program
was about 120 students.
We had nine Bloomberg terminals at the time.
I think we may have more now.
And suppose that they independently
wanted to use a terminal with probability 7 and 1/2%.
So we'd want to know, what's the cumulative probability
that nine or fewer students would
want to use it at the same time, if there
were independent demand?
We could have 120 students all show up at once,
but that's very unlikely.
So the binomial distribution lets
us compute, what's the probability of 0, 1, 2, 3,
up through 120, and we can sum that up and get an exact answer
from the binomial distribution.
But in fact, we get an almost exactly
the same answer by using the normal distribution to plug in,
and you can see on this plot where
I've shown in red sort of the integral
up to the point of interest that the distribution looks
Gaussian, and we get a very good result from the Gaussian
distribution.
So let's summarize what we've said
in discussing random variables, because this is our jumping off
point for looking at random processes that describe lots
and lots of behavior in financial markets,
and help us think about financial decision making.
Any set of random variables can be
used to construct a new random variable, their sum,
just by adding them together.
We could ask about the distribution of this S.
If we want to compute it, we need
to do convolutions of the probability
distributions of each of the axes,
and that means n fold multiple intervals
in n dimensional space, which is hard.
But for most of our applications,
we only need the moments, like the mean and the variance,
and that we can compute just from what we're
looking at in terms of the mean and the variance
of the individual random variables.
And that's easy.
So the moments of the new random variable
are computed by linearity.
And if the variables are IID, if they're
independent and identically distributed, that is,
this collection of n variables are not just
n variables from completely different corners of the world
but they're the same kind of variable
repeatedly, then as n gets large,
this sum S is going to have a full distribution that's
going to in limit approach a Gaussian distribution.
So we will know its full distribution in that case.
We still get the moments, of course, but in special cases,
we get the full distribution.
The application we're going to be looking at in our next unit
is the construction of stochastic processes,
and those have exactly the structure we've looked at,
but where the variables are ordered
and they correspond to information
being revealed over time.
So X_1 would be an information that was available on day one,
X_2 would be new information that arrived on day two,
and so on.
So we'll be interested in using this structure, the behavior
of sums of random variables, to see
how information evolves in time to see how valuation
is done when the dynamics of these processes
can be fully described.