PROFESSOR: Let's look at a little bit more detail
at generating functions and central limit theorem.
We'll be doing this using Fourier transforms.
So if you've never seen a Fourier transform
with a complex analysis, you can either skip this part
or just watch and take a look at it.
This is background material, it's
not essential for what we're going to be doing.
But for people who have done this math and who
are familiar with it, it's an interesting way
to see how the central limit theorem emerges
from some simple calculations.
So you may have seen in a statistics or probability
course, the moment generating function, that's
the expectation of e to the X. And here, we're
going to do a slight variation of it.
We're going to introduce i, the square root of minus 1.
So this is going to look like complex analysis.
But don't worry, there won't really
be any imaginary numbers in our financial market.
The only imagination is, maybe, the riches
that we would like to be thinking about getting.
But everything else is going to be brutally real.
Nevertheless, it's a good mathematical trick
because Fourier transforms, as we'll see,
have some nice properties.
So the characteristic function serves the same role
as the moment generating function.
That is, it lets us summarize all
of the moments of a distribution.
So the idea is that we can describe the function
by-- if we look at the expectation of e
to the itX, where X is our random variable,
and we expand out that exponential in a Taylor series,
we get 1 plus itX plus 1/2 i squared t squared X squared,
and so on.
And then we apply linearity, and we
can see we're going to get a term with expectation of X,
one with expectation of X squared, one
with expectation of X cubed.
And each of those has a coefficient, t, t squared,
t cubed, and so on.
And by differentiating with respect to the t's, we
can recover the individual coefficients
or the individual moments of the distribution.
So this is the same thing as a moment generating function,
just with these extra powers of i tucked in.
So this is especially useful if we can do it in closed form.
So for example, in the case of the binomial distribution,
where we can write down the probability distribution here
for each value of k, then we can sum over k equals 0 to n.
It gets cut off, we don't need to go all the way to infinity.
And we can actually do this some in closed form.
Because, notice, that the e to the itk is e to the it
raised to the k-th power.
I just regroup those together over here and do the sum.
And that's where the binomial distribution gets its name.
It's the expansion of this binomial, this quantity p
e to the it plus q raised to the n-th power.
So that's it.
That's in closed form.
That's the characteristic function
of the binomial distribution.
So if I want to get the moments from it, I take derivatives.
So the first moment--
so if I look up here up top, if I pick a value of l. l
equals 0, 1, or 2.
I come down here and I take zero derivatives or I
take one derivative times a minus i.
And that gives me np.
I take two derivatives with a minus i squared,
which gives me a minus 1.
All you need to know is that i is
the square root of negative 1.
And here, I get npq plus n squared p squared, which is
what we saw earlier, and so on.
So this is just a nice way of encoding all
of the moments in one place.
And then we recover them by taking derivatives,
if we can compute that in closed form.
In the case of continuous distributions,
the expectation of e to the itX takes the form of an integral.
And this intergral over here on the left
is known as a Fourier transform, up to some constants
that we sometimes normalize with.
This integral from minus infinity to infinity of e
to the itx p of x dx is the Fourier transfer of p of x.
And it's denoted by this function p tilde of t.
And of course, doing the same rule as before,
where we expand out this e to the itx in this Taylor series,
interchanged the order of the summation and the integration,
we see that this can be written as an infinite sum
of expectations.
And if we want to invert or if we
want to identify a particular expectation,
second the expectation of X squared,
it's the coefficient of t squared.
The way we get it is we take two derivatives
and then set t equal 0.
And then we've got these extra i's that are out in front.
OK?
So that's just an ordinary moment generating function
for discrete and continuous examples.
Why is it useful?
Well, it's really useful for sums of random variables.
And the reason is that when we have
the sum of random variables, say, x plus y,
that the full probability distribution is
a convolution of the two probability distributions.
So if x_1 and x_2 are arbitrary variables, the probability
density function for y is going to be the integral of p
of x_1 times p_2 of y minus x_1, where
I integrate dx_1 to get a function of y.
And that's a complicated interval to do.
And then I do that for more and more sums.
But these Fourier transforms have a marvelous property,
which is that the Fourier transform of a convolution
is the product of the Fourier transforms.
So the Fourier transform for p of y
is just p_1 tilde times p_2 tilde.
We just multiply them together.
And that makes it easy.