PROFESSOR: Gaussians are very special,
because the Fourier transform of the Gaussian
is actually also a Gaussian.
And you can check that by doing out the intervals
or taking a look at your favorite table book.
Notice that if this is our usual friend on the left,
the Gaussian distribution-- notice where the sigma appears.
It appears in the denominator of the exponent.
The Fourier transform over here, is a function of t.
So it's e to the minus t squared times something.
But the sigma squared is in the numerator of the Fourier
transform, not the denominator.
And they both have a 1/2.
So the first one is x minus mu quantity
squared over 2 sigma squared.
This one is t squared sigma squared over 2
in the numerator plus i.
There's our complex value--
i times mu times t for the case mu is non-zero.
But basically, it's a Gaussian form.
It's of the form e to the minus t squared.
What that means is that if we have
a sum of n random variables, what's
the probability distribution of the sum?
Well, the p-tilde is going to be the product of all the p's.
Those are each Gaussians.
So for 1, 2, 3, 4 up through n, I multiply together,
the Fourier transforms, exponential with sigma 1
squared t plus sigma 1 squared t squared over 2, plus i mu 1t.
And the same thing with 2 and the same thing with 3 and so
on--
the product of exponentials the exponential
of the sum of the exponents.
So we can combine these things up in the exponent here.
And these simplify-- you notice that they
take the form of the exponential of minus 1/2 something
times t squared, plus something else times t.
The coefficient of t squared is the sum of the sigma squared.
So we could define a new thing, we
could call sigma hat squared, to be
the sum of the sigma squares.
And we could define mu hat to be the sum of the individual mus.
But the important thing is that we can rewrite p-tilde
in the form of any one of those individual p-tildes.
That is it's a Fourier transform of the Gaussian.
So this shows that the sum of Gaussian random variables
itself, has a Gaussian distribution.
It also tells us what the parameters
of that new distribution are.
If they're identical random variables,
if all of the mu's and sigma were equal for 1, 2,
3 4, 5 6, 7, then when we add together
n identical Gaussian random variables that are all
independent, their mean is N times the mean
of an individual one.
Their variance is N times the sigma
squared for an individual one.
And therefore, their volatility, their sigma,
is the square root of N times the sigma of one
of the individual random variables.
Now because the Fourier transforms multiply,
their logarithms add.
So we define something called the cumulant expansion, which
is convenient when we're taking logarithms.
And here, p-tilde is the exponential.
So before we expanded, that we had
an exponential the other way, this
is the exponential of a sum.
And these C coefficients are particular linear combinations
of expectations.
They just group together in a very convenient way
for certain applications.
And this one you'll see right here.
So here are some examples of where we would apply this
if I want to get the--
so to extract the C's, what I do is I compute p-tilde.
That's just a Gaussian, for example--
in the case of the Gaussian, it could
be any of our other examples.
We take n derivatives of the logarithm of p.
And then we have our pre-factor of the i's.
So the first few terms are C1 is just the expectation of X. C2
Is the variance.
It's the expectation of X squared
minus the square of the expectation of X.
C3 is a bit more complicated.
It's the expectation of X cubed minus 3 times the expectation
of X times the expectation of X squared, plus twice
the mean of X, the expectation of X quantity cubed.
And for C4, we have this other complicated algebraic
expression.
But it's a particular linear combination.
Now, what's nice about these combinations,
is that they take a very simple form for Gaussians--
namely, they're all 0 after the second one.
So in the case of a Gaussian, all of these higher cumulant,
C3, C4, C5, C6 are all 0, whereas the individual moments
take some values that we could compute.
So in this particular grouping, for a Gaussian distribution,
we have C1 and C2 are non-zero.
For a general function, It could be--
these are just some numbers we could
compute using the formulas on the top of our screen.
Now, here's a way to see the Central Limit
Theorem and how it comes about.
If we take a look at the cumulants for sum of N IID
random variables, because they're identically distributed
and because the cumulants add, the nth
cumulant it's going to be N times one
of the individual ones.
So they just add.
So we just multiply times N and that's it.
OK so if we know the C sub n's for one of the variables,
we know what it is for a sum of N of them, big N of them.
We just multiply times the number of random variables
that we have.
Now we can normalize these.
These are going to have dimensions-- remember,
they depended on powers of X. So let's turn them
into pure numbers by dividing by powers of sigma,
same way we did in defining the skewness
and the kurtosis, originally.
But now when we do this, if we want
to relate these dimensionless numbers for our sum,
to the corresponding dimensionless numbers for one
of the individual random variables,
there's a pre-factor that comes from all these powers of n that
are over here and from our sigma.
And it goes as 1 over big N to the n over 2 minus 1.
And when the cumulant is greater than 2, for n greater than 2,
these are positive powers in the denominator.
And that means that as big N goes to infinity,
all of these scaled cumulants vanish.
And that's how we can see that the distribution has
to become Gaussian.
If we had done this in terms of the moments,
it would have been much more complex.
The cumulants group things together very nicely,
so that everything above 2, everything that doesn't
look like a Gaussian goes away.
So in this way, we can see that the cumulant expansion
uniquely defines the probability distribution.
When big N goes to infinity, there's a universal behavior.
And everything greater than C2 vanishes,
and therefore, whatever the original distribution was,
it looks like a Gaussian distribution.
Now there are a whole bunch of caveats.
And let me just mention two--
one of them is that this just tells you
that if N is sufficiently large, the distribution will
approach a Gaussian.
But it doesn't tell you how large and needs to be.
And the convergence isn't uniform.
So for large values of the random variable away
from the mean value, the convergence is much slower.
And it's much faster in the center.
So the rate of convergence is uniform,
and we don't know how big N needs to be for that.
Also, this is subject to the cumulants existing.
So if we have things like the fat-tail distribution
we looked at earlier, then all bets are off.
This scaling argument won't work.
So for nicely behaved functions where the moments exist,
the cumulants will exist.
And the Central Limit Theorem gives us that important result.
Here's an example of a bunch of random variables.
And how large does n need to be close to infinity?
I don't know.
How about 6?
This used to be a poor man's random number generator.
Add together six uniform random variables,
and see what the distribution looks like.
Here's some R code to do that.
And I overlain the results with a exact Gaussian function.
Not bad-- certainly for eyeballing.
Again, there's the caveat that any finite distribution
is going to be bounded.
In this case, if I have six uniform random variables,
values can't be smaller than 0, can't be bigger than 6.
But in the places in the center of the distribution,
we're actually getting close to the shape that we would expect.
So here, I've done 100,000 simulations of adding together
six uniform random variables.
And the distribution we get is anything but uniform.
It looks quite Gaussian.
So let's just summarize.
The characteristic function of a probability distribution
gives a compact formula for generating
all of the moments of the distribution
by taking derivatives.
For continuous random variables, if we computed in closed form,
we find that we're in the domain of Fourier transforms
and complex analysis.
So if that's something that you've seen before,
you know how to do these calculations.
And you know when these integrals converge
and how to compute them.
Gaussians are special in a lot of ways.
First, the Fourier transform of the Gaussian
is also a Gaussian.
And that means that the sum of Gaussian random variables
is always a Gaussian, not just for an infinite number
of terms, but for any number of terms.
The Central Limit Theorem tells us
that if we add together a large number of any IID
random variables, that will get something
that will approach a Gaussian.
So Gaussians really are universal.
When we look at adding together a large number of influences,
such as economic factors and drivers, behavior
of lots of market participants-- when we add together
a very large number of random shocks and influences
from independent sources, there's a good chance
that we might see Gaussians start to emerge,
even if the underlying behaviors have
no connection with the Gaussian distribution at all.