PROFESSOR: All right, that completes problem two.
Let's finish the recitation by reviewing a rather brief
problem, problem three.
Problem three is quite straightforward.
It asks us to explain why a regular European call
option is the sum of a down-and-out European call
option and a down-and-in European call option.
Is the same true for American call options?
Well, first recall that a down-and-out call
option is a particular type of a knockout option.
Specifically, it is a regular call option
that ceases to exist if the underlying stock price reaches
a certain barrier level.
Let's call it H. The barrier level is going to be
below the initial stock price.
The corresponding knock-in version of the option
is called a down-and-in call option.
This is a regular call option that
comes into existence only if the stock price reaches the barrier
level, H.
So in order to solve this problem,
we have to consider two different cases.
In the first case, if the barrier level, H, is reached,
then the down-and-out call option
is going to be worth nothing while the down-and-in call
option will have the same value as a regular call option.
In the second case, if the barrier level, H, is not
reached, then the down-and-in call option
is worth nothing while the down-and-out call
option has the same value as a regular option.
Thus, the payoffs from a portfolio
that consists of a down-and-out call
option plus a down-and-in call option
are identical to those of a regular European call option
regardless of whether the barrier level, H, is reached.
However, a similar argument cannot be used for American
options because American options have an early exercise premium.
Well, that does it for recitation seven.
Thank you everyone for coming, and I look forward
to seeing all of you next week.