PROFESSOR: Hello everyone, and welcome to the fourth
recitation of 15.435x.
In this recitation, we're going to be mixing things
up a little bit.
As opposed to reviewing practice problems,
we'll be reviewing three topics that Professor Lucas presented
in the Week 4 lecture.
In the first topic, we'll be reviewing the mechanics of bull
spreads and butterfly spreads.
In the second topic, we'll see how
we can use risk-neutral pricing to find
the price of a put option in a forward contract.
And in the third concept, we'll see
how we can use the replicating portfolio
approach to price a call option in the multi-period binomial
model.