PROFESSOR: Now we're going to talk about par bonds, discount
bonds, and premium bonds.
So if at the time of issuance, remember the market interest
rate is bouncing around.
But if it so happens that the market interest
rate is equal to the coupon rate,
then market value will be equal to the par value of the bond.
Then we're going to call this a par bond,
or we're going to say that the bond sells at par.
Par is also known as face value.
Sometimes, the market rate is higher than the coupon rate.
If that's the case, then it'll be a discount bond.
And we'll see in a minute why that is.
Sometimes, the market rate is lower than the coupon rate.
In that case, we'll call it a premium bond.
And again, we'll see an example of that in just a minute.
So, for example, if you are buying a zero-coupon bond,
it had a par value of $1,000, which
means that sometime in the future,
it's going to pay you $1,000.
And at the time, the market interest rate on similar debt
was 6%.
How much would you pay for the bond?
Would you pay $1,000 for the bond?
Would you pay more than $1,000 for the bond?
Would you pay less than $1,000 for the bond?
So remember, you're not going to get
the 1,000 for several years or some time now.
So clearly, you'd pay less than this
because of the present value, or the time value of money.
Also, when you lend a firm money,
there's always the chance that the firm might go bankrupt
or default, in which case you would never
get your money back.
So you're taking a risk.
And so you would pay less than $1,000 for this bond.