PROFESSOR: All right, so now we're
going to talk about early retirement of bonds.
And another way to say that, that's
a technical term, but sometimes companies
decide to repurchase their debt in the marketplace.
So they buy back their bonds.
And then once they got those bonds,
because they're no longer outstanding, they retire them.
And just to give us a picture for how this works,
here's Tesla.
It was in the newspaper recently.
Tesla back in 2017 issued a 5.3% bond.
And it was an eight year bond that it issued in 2017.
So it was due in 2025.
As you can see from the picture here,
this is a graph of the market value that bond.
Once they issued it, the market value of that bond
went down for a long period of time, for about two years.
Now, why might that be?
So, over the last couple of years,
there were substantial doubts about whether Tesla
was going to succeed or whether it was going to go bankrupt.
So the bondholders were worried that it
was going to go bankrupt and they sold the bonds.
Just recently, among other things
because Tesla has opened their Chinese factory,
and it looks like they're going to get lots of sales over that,
people have become much more optimistic about Tesla.
And the value of their bonds have gone back up to 100,
or the bonds are trading at par or at face
value for the first time ever.
But the point of this is that had Tesla
wanted to back about six months ago,
they could have bought those bonds back in the marketplace
and paid $80 for a $100 bond.
Bonds are quoted in percents.
So that would mean 80% or $1,000 bonds.
So they could have bought those bonds back for $800.