So we're going to talk about leases
in the second section of our talk
about interest-bearing liabilities.
So in terms of leases, our objectives
are talk a little bit about the rationale for leasing,
learn about under US GAAP, two types of leases, an operating
lease and a finance lease.
We're going to understand the income statement
and balance sheet effects of operating and finance leases
from the lessee's perspective.
So if you lease a car from a dealer, you're the lessee.
You drive the car.
The dealer is the lessor.
We're not going to worry too much about the lessor.
Now just recently, they became a new accounting standard
on leases.
And in the US, under the new standard,
for companies that have fiscal years beginning after December
15, 2018, we're going to put liability for leases
on the balance sheet.
Under the previous standard, as we'll talk about a little bit,
some of those leases were off-balance sheet,
not on the balance sheet.
And because some liabilities or some liability-like items
are off-balance sheet, we're going
to talk about how to estimate a liability for off-balance sheet
items.