INSTRUCTOR: And the way this works out
in a financial statement disclosures,
if we assume that it was Delta's only lease
and we thought about how their footnote would
look at the end of year eight, so after eight years,
we've made eight payments, there are 22 payments left.
The least footnote will show us the next five
years of actual payments, and then it'll
show a thereafter, which is the actual payments not shown,
times 17 remaining payments.
And that gives us our 22 payments.
Total lease payments is 22 times 21, 795.
The present value amount would be
21, 795 times an annuity of 22 years at a 6% discount rate.
The amounts representing interest
are just the total lease payments
minus the present value of the lease payments.
And then this is how it looks like in Delta's actual 2018
financial statements.
So they show their operating leases
in the second to the right column, and their finance
leases in the far right column, they
show five years of payments for each.
Thereafter is the remaining payments in total,
they show you the total minimum lease payments,
they show you the present value of those minimum lease
payments, and the difference between the total
and the present value or the amounts representing interest.
Also here they show how much of these are current obligations,
so how much is delta going to pay within the next year,
and the remainder of it is long-term obligations.