PROFESSOR: Without further ado, let's
begin with the first topic.
Suppose that you have estimated the following binomial model
for one-year interest rates, where the probability of rates
rising or falling equals 50%.
In particular, the interest rate either increases
to 5.5% next period or decreases to 3.9%.
In part a, we are asked, using this model, what
is the theoretical price of a two-year 6% coupon
bond with no options attached?
Assume that the coupon payments are paid annually
and the face value of the bond is $100.
As always, let's move backwards through the binomial tree
in order to solve this problem.
At the end of two years, the holder of the bond
will receive the face value of $100
plus an annual coupon payment of $6.
Since the diagram above shows the evolution of one-year
interest rates --
that is the interest rate between the beginning of one
year and the end of the year --
the appropriate discount rate for the payoff received
at the end of two years is equal to 1.04 for 4% times 1.055
for 5.5% in the up node, and 1.04 times 1.039
for 3.9%, which is equal to 1.08056 in the down node.
Since there is a 50% chance of rates either rising or falling,
the expected discounted payoff received
at the end of two years is as follows: 0.5 times the terminal
payoff of 106 divided by 1.04 times 1.039
for the down node plus 0.5 times 106 divided by 1.04 times 1.055
for the up node, which is equal to 97.35.
Now, the holder of the bond will also receive a coupon payment
of $6 at the end of one year -- remember,
these are annual coupon payments --
which has a present value of simply 6 divided by the spot
interest rate at initiation of 4%,
or 1.04 as a decimal, which is equal to 5.77.
Thus, the price of the two-year 6% coupon
bond with no options attached is simply
5.77, the present value of the coupon payment
received at the end of one year, plus 97.35,
the present value of the face value
plus coupon payment received at the end of two years,
which is equal to 103.12.
In part b, we are asked to consider the same bond
as in part a but with a call option that now allows
the issuer to call the bond at the end of the first year
for $101.
What is the value of this call option?
What would be the theoretical value of the callable bond?
We'll begin by recalling from the week eight lecture
that the value of a callable bond
is equal to the value of a non-callable bond
minus the value of the embedded call option.
We know from part a that the value of the non-callable bond
is 103.12.
So we just need to find the value of the call option
on the bond using the same binomial tree.
In particular, let's let the payoff of the call option
at each node, which can either be up for u or down for d,
at the end of the first year to be equal to C is equal
to the maximum of the difference between P sub i and K and 0,
were P sub i is the value of the non-callable bond in each node
--
which can either be up or down --
and K, which is equal to 101, is the strike price
of the call option.
Well, using the binomial tree given,
we can first find the value of the non-callable bond
in the up node to be the terminal payoff of 106
discounted at the spot rate in the up node of 5.5%, which
is equal to 100.47.
So the call option payoff in the up node
is equal to the maximum of the difference between 100.47
and the strike price of 101 and 0, which is equal to 0.
A similar calculation for the down node
shows that the value of the non-callable bond
in the down node is equal to 106 divided by 1.039,
which is equal to 102.02.
And the payoff of the call option in the down node
is equal to the maximum of the difference between 102.02
minus 101 and 0, which is equal to 1.02.
Since the value of the call option
is the present value of the expected
payoffs of the option at the end of the first year,
we simply take 0, which is the value of the call
option at the end of the first year
and the up node, multiplied by the probability of an up
move of 0.5, discounted at the risk-free rate
of 4% at the initial node, plus the probability of a down move
of 0.5 times the payoff of the call option
in the down node of 1.02 discounted at the 4% interest
rate, which gives us a total value of the call
option of 0.49.
Now, since the value of the callable bond
is the difference between the value of the non-callable bond
and the value of the embedded call option,
we know that the value of the callable bond
must be equal to 103.12 minus 0.49, which is equal to 102.63.