PROFESSOR: We'll now discuss bad that's.
Bad debt basically occurs when you made a sale to a customer,
but the customer is not likely to pay you
for the product you sold.
There are two ways of accounting for bad debts.
The direct method and the allowance method.
In this recitation, will focus on allowance method.
Within the allowance method, we'll
cover two methods, the percentage of sales method
and the aging method.
Recall that the managing principal
is the idea that expenses should be matched to their revenues.
In that spirit, allowance accounts
are used when we estimate future expenses.
We'll focus on allowance for doubtful accounts, or ADA.
Allowance for doubtful accounts is a contra asset account,
associated with accounts receivable.
Therefore, gross accounts receivable, minus ADA
is the net realizable value of accounts receivable.
In other words, when ADA is used,
the company anticipates that some accounts
will be uncollectible in advance of knowing the specific account
or amount.
Bad debt expense is often an estimate
to more closely match the sale, which
in turn, increases relevance, but lowers reliability.
As mentioned, there are two methods for estimating ADA.
First, the percentage of sales method estimates
expected losses as a percentage of credit sales
during the period.
The intuition here is that the more you sell,
the more you're likely to make a loss from some proportion
of the sales.
Second, the aging method estimates expected losses
based on the age of the receivables.
Here, the intuition is that the longer you have not been paid,
the less you're likely to collect that amount.
The exact estimation method that each company uses
is often found in the footnote of the annual report.
Recall the BASE equation for changes
and balance sheet amounts in the lecture.
Every balance sheet uses the same BASE equation,
and this is going to be useful, especially
for calculating ADA, as well as the ending balance of the ADA.
First, there is beginning balance,
the beginning ADA rolled over from the prior year.
From the beginning balance, we add bad debt expense,
subtract write offs, and then arrive at the ending balance.
Note that the percentage of sales method
gives bad debt expense, this allows us
to compute the ending balance.
Whereas, the aging analysis gives the ending balance,
and then allowing us to compute the bad debt expense.
In summary, it's important to understand
the definition of each line item,
and the impact on financial statements
for certain transactions.
I'll go over them one by one.
Accounts receivable is defined as, customer purchases
made on account, i.e. credit.
You'll receive payment later.
This impacts the income statement
by recognizing revenue when earned and not received.
Balance sheet, the accounts receivables account
under assets will be affected.
Allowance for doubtful accounts is company provisions
for uncollectible accounts receivable.
The impact on income statement depends on how ADA changes.
On the other hand, contra asset account,
the ADA account is impacted.
Bad debt expense is future projections
for uncollectible accounts receivables,
assuming the percentage of sales method.
On the income statement, expenses
recognized as percentage of sales.
On the balance sheet, ADA is increased by the same amount.
Write-off happens when it becomes evident that
the customer cannot pay.
It is the accounts receivables that
goes bad in that time period.
There is no impact on the income statement,
and on the balance sheet, it reduces
ADA and accounts receivable.
How are these accounts receivable
related transactions represented in the actual 10-Ks?
In this slide, I show a sample 10-K,
how the base equation can be shown in the 10-K statements.
A second row balance at the beginning of period
shows the beginning ADA balance of 103 in February 1st, 2019.
The next row, provision charged to income statement,
is the bad debt expense, or the additions to the beginning ADA
balance.
We subtract bad debt write offs, which is amount
deemed uncollectible, 95 million in this particular financial
statement.
Finally, we arrive at the balance
at the end of a period, which is the ending ADA balance.