PROFESSOR: Question three, Tootsie
Roll receives royalty revenue related
to licensing fees generated from other companies
using the Tootsie Roll trademark.
Assume that on December 31, 2007,
Tootsie Roll received $4,975 in cash from a European company
to use their trademark for the next two years, i.e.
2008 and 2009.
The legal costs associated with this transaction were $1,349,
and Tootsie Roll paid these costs on December 31, 2007.
Tootsie Rolls accounting policy for this type of transaction
is to record all of the revenue when the cash is received
and match the expenses to the revenue.
the company has a fiscal Year end on December 31.
Part A, use the balance sheet equation
to identify the transaction Tootsie Roll recorded
on December 31, 2007.
Tootsie Roll is receiving $4,975 on December 31, 2007,
and its accounting policy is to record all the revenue when
cash is received and match the expenses to revenue.
Therefore, we recognize $4,975 in revenues
as well as the legal costs that were associated
with this revenue, i.e $1,349.
The balance sheet equations for these transactions
are as follows.
First, we record an increase in cash by $4,975
and a corresponding $4,975 increase in retained earnings
to recognize the revenue.
Second, we record a decrease in cash by $1,349
and decrease in retained earnings
by the same amount as legal expenses.
I suggest to include what exactly the revenues
and expenses were when retained earnings change.
For example, in the legal expenses
you would want to record under retained earnings
the legal expense as the specific expense account.
Part B, suppose instead they decided
to spread their revenue and costs associated
with the Royalty payment over the two year contract, again,
matching the expense to the revenue.
Use the balance sheet equation to identify
the transaction Tootsie Roll recorded on December 31, 2007.
In this case, revenue is not recognized but categorized
as deferred revenue.
Since Tootsie Roll still receive cash, cash increases by $4,975.
In addition, deferred revenue account,
which is under liabilities also increases by the same amount.
Assets equals liabilities plus equity so BSE balances out.
For the legal charges since the company still
paid the expenses in cash, cash decreases by $1,349.
On the other hand, prepaid expenses,
which is an asset account, increases by the same amount
to balance the BSE out.
Part C, assuming the facts in part B,
use the balance sheet equation to identify the transaction
to see recorded on December 31, 2008.
Part B says that revenue and costs are spread out
over the two year contract.
In December 31, 2008, half of the deferred revenues incurred
in December 31, 2007 are realized,
and half of the prepaid expenses are converted to expenses.
Therefore, half of the deferred revenues,
which is $2,487.50 will be realized as revenue and half
of the prepaid expenses, which is $674.50, will be realized.
To express these transactions using balance sheet equation,
deferred revenue decreases by $2,487.50,
and retained earnings increases by the same amount.
Prepaid expenses decreases by $674.50,
and retained earnings decreases by the same amount.
There is no change in cash since no cash
has been flowed out or in.