PROFESSOR: Question four is on accounts receivables.
Refer to Ruddick Corp's 2012 annual report.
Question A, for the year ended October 2, 2012,
how much bad debt expense did Ruddick Corp recognize
on its income statement?
How much accounts receivables did Ruddick Corp write off?
Refer to column C of the fiscal year
ended 2012, the bottom row.
Bad debt expense is shown as $556,000.
On the other hand, column D of the same row
shows that the write off amount is $379,000.
Question B, how does bad debt expense
change from 2010 to 2011?
Assume that Ruddick Corp uses the percentage of sales method
to calculate bad debt expense.
For what reasons might the change in bad debt expense
have occurred?
As you can see in column C of Ruddick's financial statements
shown in the past slide, bad debt expense
decreased from $775,000 in 2010 to $164,000 in 2011.
Why did the bad debt expense decrease that much?
There could be a number of potential reasons
but to name a few Ruddick Corp may use a new lower estimate
of the uncollectible accounts resulting
from improved collections.
It may also have made lower sales in 2011.
We don't know their sales number just by looking at the slide,
so this is possible.
Finally, Ruddick Corps management
could have intentionally reduced the bad debt expense in 2011.