PROFESSOR: We'll continue to use the general procedure you
learned last week to price derivatives on a binomial tree,
but now we can write the risk neutral probability
of an up move q star in terms of u, d, r, and h.
In fact, it's straightforward to prove
that q star will equal the ratio shown here
on a non-dividend-paying stock.
You can verify that it comes from solving for q star
as we did last week based on the equation that
sets the current stock price equal to the discounted
value of the risk neutral expectation of the stock
price on the next time step discounted back
at the risk-free rate.
Well, once we have the price tree and q star,
we can price any European style derivative as before
by evaluating the payoff at the terminal time t
and working backwards.
Then at each time step and on each node,
we can calculate the risk neutral expectation
of the derivative value on the next step
and discount it back to get the value of the derivative
at the node we're looking at.
For instance, for call options, we
start at the n-th time step, which is the last one,
and compute the payoff at each of the j nodes
from the familiar equation for the payoff on a call.
We then can work backwards to find the call value at time i
and know j calculating the risk neutral
expected value at time i plus 1 based on the risk
neutral probability and discounting back
over the time interval h at the risk-free rate.
Going back to the inputs in the binomial tree spreadsheet,
we can specify the strike price of the option.
In this example, we'll assume the strike
price is set equal to 100.
There's also an indicator variable,
which we set to 1 to indicate that we're
looking for a call price.
If that's sent to any other value,
the spreadsheet will treat the option as a put option.
We need to set the time horizon capital
T to be the expiration date of the option, which
we'll take to be 0.1% here.
The output then also includes the risk neutral probability q
star, the same as the stock price
tree we saw before based on an n of 10 steps between time 0
and time capped t of 0.1.
Then the value of the option at each node
is represented on the lower tree and calculated
by working backwards.
For example, at the time 0.1 node,
where the stock price is $112.75,
the payoff on the call option is $12.75.
The time 0 node gives the call option value of 3.787.
That value is also recorded at the top
of the spreadsheet, along with the delta of the call option,
[AUDIO OUT].
The calculations here are based on the same input,
except for the number of steps on the trees
has been increased from 10 to 250.
Clearly, there's too many numbers in a 250-step tree
to show on a single slide.
So what's pictured here is a truncation
showing only the first 10 steps for the stock price tree
and also for the call price tree.
Notice that with the change in the number of steps
and all else the same as before, the output parameters u, d, q,
and q star all have to change too.
Those changes capture the lower stock price variation
and smaller effective discounting over each shorter
time interval between nodes.
The estimated call price now is 3.876.
That's quite close to the previous and less
precisely estimated price of 3.787, which was
based on only using 10 steps.
As we're about to discuss, the limit
taking the number of steps to infinity
gives the Black-Scholes-Merton price, which is 3.88.
With 250 steps, we get essentially the same answer.