PROFESSOR: This week, you'll learn
to use the famous Black-Scholes Merton formula for options
pricing and to understand the main drivers of option price
sensitivity, which are known as the Greeks.
We'll start, again, with a binomial model
and learn how it's typically calibrated
to match stock price dynamics.
By taking the limit as the number of steps
goes to infinity and the step size goes to 0,
you'll see one way that the Black-Scholes Merton
formula for pricing European stock options can be derived.
Next, we'll take a close look at the Black-Scholes Merton
model, the formula, and its inputs,
and the assumptions and intuition behind the model.
Then we'll turn to the Greeks, which
are measures of an option value's
sensitivity to key parameters, including the underlying stock
price, the risk-free rate, time to expiration, and volatility.
Finally, we'll study a financial engineering application,
which is how an insurer can use a dynamic delta hedging
strategy to limit its exposure to losses from the portfolio
protection products it sells.
We'll see that the strategy often works well,
but that it can fail dramatically when there
are large and sudden price changes, such as those that
occur during financial panics.