PROFESSOR: To make it easy to numerically price derivatives
under realistic assumptions about the distribution
of future stock prices.
For simplicity, and because it can often
provide a good approximation, stock returns
are frequently modeled as having a constant expected return, mu,
and a constant volatility, sigma.
That is, over a small interval of time h,
the expected gross rate of return
on the stock is e to the mu times h.
The variance of the gross return is the expectation
of the squared deviations from the mean return, which we'll
write as sigma squared times h, where sigma squared represents
the annualized variance on a continuous basis.
This specification for variance assumes
the returns are independently and identically
distributed over time.
Say now that we want to price an option
with a maturity of capital T.
We can chop the interval from 0 to T
into n equally sized subintervals.
Each interval has a size h of T over n.
And i times h represents calendar time on the tree.
To keep the calibration simple, it's standard
to restrict the evolution of the stock prices on the tree
so that starting at a node s sub i, at time step i plus 1,
the up node is s i times u, and the down node
is s i times d, where d and u are constant.
The probability of an up is q, and the down, of course,
is 1 minus q, where q is also a constant.
Note that q represents here a true, or physical,
or actual probability.
With these restrictions, we have three free variables
to match to the known expected return and the known variants.
The equations here, then, represent the expected return
and variance in terms of those three free variables,
u, d, and q.
Since we have one more free variable
than we have equations to satisfy,
we use that extra degree of freedom
to further simplify the tree by assuming
that u is equal to 1 over d.
Now, with those three equations and a little bit of algebra,
we can solve for u, d, and q as a function of sigma and mu.
The results will also depend on the step size, h.
It's straightforward, then, to program a spreadsheet
to create a tree that's consistent
with these assumptions and a given set of inputs.
The spreadsheet, called binomialtree.xls,
is on the course materials web page.
It's programmed to create a stock price
tree using this procedure.
And it also computes the prices of European put and call
options.
The spreadsheet was used to create the examples we'll
look at on the next few slides.
You'll also need to use it to solve
some of the homework problems.
And it will be available for you to use on the exam.
The procedure that we just discussed also
works for dividend-paying stocks,
but the stock price process has to be slightly modified
to account for the fact that part of the total return
is in the form of a dividend.
JR will go over that in the recitation.
The binomialtree.xls spreadsheet is
programmed to incorporate the constant dividend yield.
Of the inputs and outputs from the spreadsheet
binomialtree.xls and the picture of the resulting stock price
tree, the lighter shaded cells are inputs,
and the darker cells are outputs.
Inputs needed for the tree include
mu, the expected return on the stock,
sigma, the volatility of the stock, r, the risk-free rate,
div, the dividend yield, s0, the initial stock price, and then
capital T, the time horizon for the tree in years,
and n, the number of steps in the tree.
Turning to the outputs used to calculate the stock price tree,
the time step h is defined as cap T over n,
as we defined it before.
The other outputs associated with building the tree
are u, d, and q.
Those are calculated using the formulas on the previous slide.
We'll talk about the option inputs
and outputs in a few minutes.
But first, let's look at the stock price tree
that we get from these assumptions.
Each column represents a time step starting at 0,
going out to n, and it's indexed by i.
Each row is a node number, and that's indexed by j.
Each entry in the tree is a stock price node.
The up move from any node is recorded
in the same row but one column to the right,
while a down move is recorded in the next row
and also one column to the right.
For example, we start with the input stock price of 100
at time 0.
The up takes the 100, multiplies it by u, of 1.030455,
and gives us 103.045 as the up node at the next step.
When we multiply by d, which is 1 over u,
we get the down step, which brings us to a price of 97.045.