PROFESSOR: This week, our main topic
will be volatility, which is one of the most important drivers
of option value and, of course, what motivates
people to trade options and other derivatives
in the first place.
I also want to introduce you to some useful options
pricing models that are variants on Black-Scholes Merton.
Before we turn to those other pricing models
and to volatility, we'll finish up
on our discussion from last week on hedging with the Greeks
and we'll learn to implement delta-gamma hedging.
The other options pricing models that I want to briefly cover
include variations on BSM that are frequently
used to price options on stock indices, options on currencies,
and options on futures.
We won't go into detail derivations,
but it's useful for you to be aware of these models
and understand how to use them.
Then we'll turn to volatility.
We'll start by seeing that the simple Black-Scholes Merton
framework, with its constant volatility assumption,
can't completely explain observed option prices.
We'll get a better read on the market's perception
of volatility through the concept of implied volatility.
We'll also see how implied volatilities
go into constructing the VIX, a widely watched index of stock
market volatility that's also, itself, directly traded
in risk management strategies.
Finally, we'll look at some of the approaches
that have been developed to incorporate
the variation in volatility over time
and how they can be used to create better options pricing
models.