PROFESSOR: So now we want to talk
about temporary differences between accounting income,
or US GAAP, and the tax code.
So temporary differences are items
that are recognized both by GAAP and by the tax code,
but they're recognized in different periods.
We're going to do two examples of this--
first of which we're familiar with,
which is depreciation expense.
So GAAP uses straight-line depreciation,
whereas the tax code uses accelerated depreciation.
So tax depreciation tends to be more in the early years,
and later in the--
and less in the later years.
And then we'll do an example of deferred revenue, where,
remember, with GAAP, we only earn income
when we've both earned it and it's collectible--
so when we've done the work for it.
With the tax code, on the other hand,
because it's a cash system, as soon
as it sees the cash come in, it's going to want to tax that.
So first we want to talk about deferred tax liabilities.
Deferred tax liabilities arise, or begin,
or they increase when there's a timing difference that
leads to pre-tax income under GAAP
being temporarily greater than taxable income
under the tax code.
So the example we're going to look at
is depreciation expense.
So because we use straight-line depreciation under GAAP,
depreciation expense is going to be lower in the early years
under GAAP than it is for tax, which
uses accelerated depreciation.
So what's going to happen is because you get the greater tax
deductions early on, you pay less taxes early on,
and then you're going to pay more taxes later on.
So we're going to look at an example of this, which
this Cooke Company bought a $100,000 asset
at the beginning of 2010.
For financial reporting, the asset life was two years.
The disproportion rate was straight-line
for financial reporting, and the salvage value was 0.
For tax reporting, we're going to assume
accelerated depreciation, so the asset life is one year.
Depreciation rate is we get to write off
all of the asset in the first year,
and then that will leave no depreciation
deduction for the second year, and again, the salvage value
is 0.
So what's Cooke's depreciation expense for financial reporting
purposes?
So this is review.
So the depreciable base is $100,000.
We're depreciating over two years with no salvage value.
So $100,000 divided by 2 years is
going to be $50,000 in depreciation expense
in 2010, and then $50,000 more in 2011.
For tax purposes, we're doing an accelerated depreciation,
so we're writing off the whole asset in the first year.
So we've got $100,000 worth of depreciation in 2010,
which is our first year, and then we'll
have no depreciation in 2011, which is our second year.
So we want to just go through.
In this example, we're going to assume
that Cooke has income, before depreciation and taxes,
of $100,000.
And this is true for both financial reporting
and for tax reporting, and this is true in both 2010 and 2011.
Again, we're going to assume that the tax rate is 35%.
So for financial reporting, what's our income before taxes?
Well, it's $100,000 income minus the $50,000 in depreciation,
so we got $50,000 in income before taxes.
So what's our tax expense, then?
Well, our tax expense is $50,000 times 35%,
or 17 and 1/2 thousand dollars-- so $50,000 income before taxes
times the 35% tax rate.
Now let's do tax reporting.
So how much is income before taxes for tax reporting?
We got $100,000 in income, but we got $100,000
in depreciation expense, so we have
no income for tax purposes.
That means we have no income to tax.
35% of 0 is 0 cash taxes.
Now let's see how this plays out in the balance sheet equation.
So cash we're going to recognize first.
Notice that we pay no cash taxes.
So no cash taxes here.
Again, we're assuming that cash taxes are all
paid during the fiscal year, essentially--
although, in practice, there will be
a little bit of taxes payable.
So we're going to run this all through cash.
What's our tax expense?
Again, for financial reporting, our tax expense
is 17 and 1/2 thousand dollars, and then to balance the balance
sheet equation here, we're going to create a deferred tax
liability of 17 and 1/2 thousand dollars.
So this deferred tax liability estimates
taxes expected to be paid in the future,
and it's kind of like a long-term payable.
So we're recognizing the fact that in the future,
because we didn't pay any taxes this year,
in some future year-- which is going to be next year in this
example--
we're going to have to pay 17 and 1/2 thousand extra taxes.
So let's see what happens, now, in the second year, which
is 2011.
So again, we're assuming the company has income,
before depreciation and taxes, of $100,000,
and that's true for both financial reporting
and for tax reporting.
So for financial reporting, we're
going to look exactly the same in.
2011 so we're going to have $100,000 worth of income,
$50,000 worth of depreciation expense,
gives us $50,000 net income before taxes.
Our tax expense is 35% of this $50,000 worth of net income.
Now, where things are going to change is for tax reporting.
So how much income are we going to have for tax reporting?
Remember, we used all of our depreciation tax deduction
up last year, so we have no deduction this year,
so we're going to have a full $100,000 of income
before taxes for tax reporting.
We're going to pay 35% of that, or $35,000, in cash taxes.
And then when we look at our balance sheet equation entry,
first of all, we want to keep track of cash.
So cash is going to go down $35,000.
We're going to pay the government $35,000 in taxes.
Tax expense is going to be the same--
this 17 and 1/2 thousand dollars.
And then to have the balance sheet equation balance,
our deferred tax liability is going to go away,
and is basically telling us we paid an extra 17 and 1/2
thousand dollars in taxes in 2011.
And in some sense, these were taxes
that we "owed," in quotation mark, from 2010.
So that's our example, in two periods,
of a deferred tax liability.
Now, obviously, assets' lives are not always two years.
Two years makes for a neat example.
Here's an example where we buy $200,000 worth of equipment.
We got a full tax deduction on it--
so that's similar to the current tax law in the US.
So we got a full tax deduction on it,
but we're in a straight-line depreciation for financial
reporting purposes--
$50,000 a year over the next four years.
So the first column shows our $200,000 tax deduction
in the first year.
Second column shows straight-line depreciation
over four years.
And if we subtract the second column from the first column,
we'll get a tax versus book difference
of $150,000 in the first year, and that's a cumulative tax
book difference at that point.
And then moving down into the second panel,
if we multiply that cumulative tax book difference times
our tax rate-- and we're assuming a tax rate of 25%,
here--
that tells us what our deferred tax liability
is at the end of the first year, and that
tells us what our deferred tax expense is
at the end of the first year.
And then continuing on in the second panel,
over time, that cumulative tax book difference goes away,
so the deferred tax liability gets smaller and smaller,
so our deferred tax expense reverses
from $37,500 in the first year to a negative $12,500,
or a tax benefit of $12,500, in the second, third,
and fourth years.
So now let's look at some tax disclosures.
We're going to look at Goldman Sachs company, which
is the big investment bank and bank,
and we're going to look at their tax footnote from 2016.
So remember, companies use different vocabulary here.
So we see, here, the words "current tax expense."
What that actually means is that Goldman owed about $2.4 billion
in tax to the tax authorities for 2016.
Second item at the bottom of the table,
here, is the provision for taxes.
That's Goldman's income tax expense.
And so when we look at that in the balance sheet
equation for 2016, Goldman paid cash taxes, again,
of about $2.4 billion.
They had a provision for taxes of about $2.9 billion.
And again, to make the balance sheet equation balance here,
we're going to put $551,000,000 in deferred tax expense,
and you see that deferred tax expense
at the second-to-the-bottom line at the table, there.