PROFESSOR: So now we're going to--
we talked about deferred tax liabilities,
which live on the liability side of the balance sheet.
Now we're going to talk about deferred tax assets, which
live on the asset side of the balance sheet.
So they're just the same as deferred tax liabilities,
except the deferred tax assets either begin or rise,
whatever word you want to use there, or increase when there's
a temporary timing difference that causes GAAP pretax income
to be lower than taxable income on the tax code.
And here we're going to use our example of deferred revenue.
So, remember, when we get income,
we don't recognize revenue until we've actually
provided the service or deliver the goods.
So if we get deferred revenue, that's cash that comes in,
but it's not income for us under GAAP
because we have to wait till it's earned.
But when the tax authorities sees cash coming in,
they're going to tax it, so that revenue
is revenue for the tax authority as soon as we get it.
So with deferred revenue, we're going
to pay more cash taxes early, and we're going
to pay less cash taxes later.
So this is going to be the opposite of a deferred tax
liability.
So as an illustration of deferred tax asset,
we're going to look at a company that rents property out.
So imagine you're a landlord, and you
rent units in your building.
So in 2010, let's pretend that we collected
$100,000 worth of rent, but $50,000 of this rent
was paid in advance for next year, which is 2011.
So, again, we're going to compare financial reporting
with tax reporting.
Again, our tax rate is going to be 35%.
So for financial reporting, even though we got $100,000,
we only provided the service, which
was running the apartment for 2010 for $50,000 worth of that.
So we're going to recognize $50,000 worth of the rent.
The other rent is deferred income, which
we'll recognize next year.
So $50,000 times the 35% tax rate
gives us a $17,500 tax expense.
So for financial reporting purposes,
we got $50,000 income and $17,500 of tax expense.
Now, for tax reporting--
remember, the tax man-- as soon as the tax authority sees cash
coming in-- they're basically a cash system--
So they see that $100,000 come in,
they're going to want to tax all of that.
They're going to tax it at 35%.
So $100,000 coming in, you're going
to pay $35,000 in taxes on this.
And in terms of the way this works in the balance sheet
equation, cash taxes are going to be $35,000.
Our tax expense is $17,500.
And to balance the balance sheet equation,
we're going to create a deferred tax asset,
and you can think of this as sort of a prepaid expense.
So we paid an extra $17,500 of tax this year,
and we expect, therefore, not to pay so much tax next year.
So next year, in 2011, we also assume the same facts.
So for financial reporting purposes,
we actually earn the other $50,000.
Our tax expense on those earnings
are 35% times $50,000, which is $17,500.
For tax reporting purposes, we've already
paid tax on the whole $100,000, so we have no new cash taxes
this year.
And then what happens in terms of the balance sheet equation,
we got no cash taxes.
We've got rent expense.
We've got-- I'm sorry.
Tax expense is $17,500.
And then the difference to balance the balance sheet
equation is going to be the reversal of the deferred tax
asset.
And kind of what this is saying to us
is that we paid $17,500 in some sense in advance in 2010,
and this is the accounting that shows us
that we don't owe any further cash taxes in 2011.