PROFESSOR: So, now, let's just look at some examples
of these ratios.
So Walmart's return on assets, net income divided by ending
total assets, is 7.4%.
Amazon's return on assets, net income
divided by ending total assets, is 2.8%.
Walmart's ROE, net income divided
by ending stockholders' equity, Walmart's return on equity
is 18.2%, whereas Amazon's return on equity is only 12.3%.
And, in a few minutes, as we wrap up these examples,
we're going to examine exactly why Amazon's return on equity
is lower than Walmart's return on equity.
But, first, let's run through some checks
of our understanding of these ratios.
So Amazon's return on equity, net income of 2,371
divided by total stockholders' equity of 19,285,
so their return on equity is 12.3%.
What would happen to their ROE if, at the very end
of the year, Amazon issued stock for cash?
Would that have an effect on net income?
No, it's at the very end of the year.
What would it do to stockholders' equity?
Stockholders' equity would go up.
So return on equity would go down.
Notice that I formulated this question
at the very end of the year because,
if Amazon issued stock for cash during the year,
presumably, it would have income on that cash, which would
cause net income to go up.
So, just to keep things simple, we
assume the transaction happens at the very end of the year.
Now, let's look at another example.
So, at the very end of the year-- again,
for the same reason, we're going to look at the very end
of the year--
Amazon pays a cash dividend.
Does that have an effect on their net income?
No.
Remember, income is not affected by dividends.
Does that affect their stockholders' equity?
Yes, it's going to cause their stockholders' equity
to go down.
So, as a result of that, because stockholders' equity goes down,
the ratio ROE is going to go up.
Now, what would happen at the very end of the year
if all of our customers-- and this
is sort of an extreme example, but let's just pretend
all of our customers paid off all of their receivables.
Would that have an effect on net income?
No, it's at the very end of the year.
Would it have an effect on stockholders' equity?
No.
So there's no income here.
So, this example, ROE is unaffected.
Now, let's suppose it's the dreaded accounting error.
Let's suppose that, at the end of the year,
Amazon finds out it has an error.
It forgot to make the entries for an additional $100,000
in accrued compensation.
Now, when it corrects that error,
what's going to happen to net income?
So net income is going to go down because
of the additional expense.
What's going to happen to stockholders' equity?
Stockholders' equity is going to go down because we
have less net income.
And so our ratio is going to go down
because we're subtracting a negative number
from the numerator and a negative number
from the denominator of a ratio that's less than 1.
So you can sort of check that by calculator
or by using the ratio facts that I showed you earlier.
A similar example is, what would happen
if Amazon, at the end of the year,
increased its expense on estimated returns?
So, again, similar to the previous example,
income would go down.
Because income is going down, stockholders' equity
would go down.
And, again, our return on equity would go down as well.