So as takeaways for class, this class,
we introduced financial statement analysis and ratio analysis.
So this is a huge topic.
I wanted to give you an introduction to it.
You'll find that it's really, really useful.
One of the uses of this is that in professional settings,
many people are paid bonuses based
on their financial performance, their return on equity,
their asset turnover.
So I forecast that when you get out of school,
you're going to be paid this kind of bonus as well.
So it's important to understand how these ratios work
and what you can do to affect the ratios.
And then those of you that are going
to go off and become professional investors, you're
going to use this type of analysis
all the time to help you compare companies
and to help you pick stocks.
Those of you that go off and become investment bankers,
these are techniques that you're going
to use to value companies.
And we also, finally, introduced the Dupont model, which
is really a powerful way to think of return on equity,
decompose it into profit margin, asset turnover, and leverage
to give you a sense of what drives profitability.