PROFESSOR: Lecture, we saw two ways
of solving the Black-Scholes equation.
One of them was by doing integrals.
Where we had a kernel, a probability density function,
we could multiply times the desired payoff,
do the integral, and get a solution.
But I mentioned, then, that there was another way
that we could do it by using directly
the formula for expectations and the fact
that certain expected values satisfy differential
equations in general, and in particular,
the Black-Scholes equation.
So what I'd like to do is just show you a little bit more
in detail here.
But I'm not going to write the code.
I left that for you to do.
And the steps are pretty easy, though.
What I want to show you, I've written a function
here, MCprice, and behind me are a set of Monte Carlo paths
that I generated before you came in.
And I did this using code that's very similar to the code we did
at the beginning of the class when we first
talked about Monte Carlos, except that it's
been adapted for the specifics of an Ito process.
So what do I mean by that?
Well, we have-- our idea is going
to be to find the value of a derivative at time t
to be the present value in the time remaining to expiration
of the expected value of the function at expiration.
And we're going to replace this by an approximation.
So this is going to be computed as the average
over a bunch of Vs that could have come
under different realizations.
But we said that this was under the Q-measure.
So Q is economist speak.
Q-measure, or risk-neutral measure,
simply means that we're going to pick
a drift rate r, the risk-free rate,
to replace mu in our formulas.
Now, what is it we want to do?
We wanted to start with an underlying,
so we have an underlying price process.
And remember, we're going to discretize things.
So we want to do an approximation
to a continuous time world, but we're
going to go back to discrete.
So remember when we talked about discrete processes,
we said that we could define changes recursively
in terms of return, logarithmic returns,
over a given time period.
If we rewrite this, of course, this
is the same as saying that rt is the logarithm of St
over St minus 1.
And we didn't specify how far apart t and t minus 1 were,
and here we'll think of them as being
some small but finite distance dt, or delta t, if you prefer.
And you notice that this is the same thing as log
of St minus log of St minus 1.
Now, if you're a nitpicker, you would
say that you can't take a logarithm of something
with units.
So we could divide this by $1, let's say,
and just have it be--
I could divide this by, say, some S star equal to $1
just so that those are dimensionless,
and that obviously cancels out.
But the important point is that, in terms
of this dimensionless variable, this
is going to be what we mean by d of log S.
So this r over here is just the return over the time step.
That's not the risk-free rate.
So what we want is, we'd like to build up
a series of iterated values.
This is S minus 2, e to the rt plus rt minus 1,
and so on, so that we can say that St
is going to be equal to some initial S0 times e
to the sum r1 plus r2 plus all the way up to rt
where these rt's are things that themselves
are described by d of log S.
So what does d of log S look like?
Well, we know that S is an Ito process.
So what we need to do is consider
that if dS/S is given by the risk-free description
plus sigma dB, this is what we'd like to do to have our Monte
Carlo, but not dS/S, but we want to simulate
a sequence of random variables d of log S.
And you'll write out what this is in terms of dt
and what it is in terms of dB.
And then those will be in the same format that we had before.
But we need to get the coefficients right
to get the right answer.
So the idea is that we're going to generate
a particular sequence of random variables that
are consistent with the Ito process
that we have, but with the special drift rate
where the drift rate is given by the risk-free rate,
not the actual drift rate on the stock.
And then to compute our option values, what we're going to do
is at the end we're going to take--
well, put in a discount factor in front.
That's not too hard.
But our main idea is that we're going to,
instead of computing this mathematical expectation
by doing Gaussian integrals, we're
going to generate a whole bunch of price paths of S
and then compute V of S and just evaluate it at the endpoints.
So finally, it's going to look like e to the minus
r T minus t expectation of V evaluated at the final time
T and that final price ST.
So let's make that really concrete.
Let me just show you what the pieces are,
and then you'll put them together.
I promise you, it's not more than a page of code.
So if we take a look, what I've done
is I've generated a bunch of paths here.
And I've got my parameters already on the side.
Now, I have these parameters which are associated
with the stock price.
S0 is 100, mu is 5%, and sigma is 30%.
I have these parameters associated
with the option itself.
So let's run those.
So I have the strike price is $100.
You can pick your value.
T is equal to 1 year.
One thing to watch out in R is R assumes that capital T stands
for true or false.
I always redefine it, but be careful.
You can pick a different letter if you
want because it's reserved until you overwrite it the way I did.
And I'll take a risk-free rate of 10%.
And then finally, I have a set of parameters
that are purely related to my simulation, where
I have two choices.
I can pick the number of time steps
into which I'm going to divide my macroscopic period here
of 1 year, and I have the number of paths in my simulation.
So I like to start with around 10,000,
the typical size of the error is close of the square root of NP.
So that's going to give me a starting
point with a ballpark in the area of around 1% errors.
But you should try it and see how things behave
when you take a look at it.
So let's run those parameters.
Now, take a look at the sample paths.
I've already run this expression on the right-hand side.
And you can see behind me a whole bunch of sample paths.
Now, these are all drawn from exactly the same distribution.
I haven't told you which process I have to generate them,
but you could guess.
And I haven't told you what random variable I'm using,
but I wrote everything out in terms
of a standardized random variable Z.
One of the questions you should look at when you try
is to ask how much of a difference does it make.
For example, if you take Z equals plus or minus 1,
or you take Z to be drawn from a normal distribution of mean 0
and variance 1, or you pick something
else an exponential variable, anything else that's
been rescaled, how much of a difference
does it make in your simulations?
And how does it depend, for example,
on the number of time steps before, say, the central limit
theorem kicks in, as we would expect it to do over
a long period of time, over, say, a few hundred steps?
It is worth noting that, if you add even
as few as six uniform random variables,
that you can get a fairly decent approximation to the Gaussian
distribution.
So here I've got a bunch of paths,
and you'll notice this gives me the stock
price all the way out.
And I've drawn only 10 of them, not 10,000,
because the graph would look rather a mess otherwise.
OK.
So that's what some of the paths look like.
What do the option values look like?
Well, remember, the value of a call option on a stock
is equal to the stock price minus the strike price.
So it's equal to the price minus 100
provided the price is above 100.
But it's equal to 0 below 100.
So if I take a look at my expression,
now looking at call values where I've computed in that way,
here's what they look like.
So you notice these price paths never go below 0.
They're not as big as the others because I've basically
subtracted off 100.
And a large number of them are really
invisible because they all hug the bottom of the curve.
But this is what I want.
So I went from my underlying S to my derivative V,
or in this case, I've called it C.
I've got another one called P for doing the put values.
And all that's left to do is to take
the average of the terminal values and discount it,
and then we're done.
But it might be interesting to see what happens,
because these are not evenly distributed.
So remember that the histogram for, let's say,
the terminal values of S--
so let's take the last time step, which would be Nt plus 1,
in this case 253, and if we look at a histogram of the values,
we see that we get something that
looks like a typical kind of log-normal distribution.
If I do the same thing in terms of the call values,
though, I'm going to get something
that's quite different.
Oops, let's try capital C, definitely case sensitive here.
And what I see is, I have a huge spike at 0.
A lot of my paths finish below the money,
and they don't contribute.
And then for the ones that do finish above the money,
they're actually decreasing more or less monotonically.
There are a couple bumps there, but those
are artifacts of the simulation and some of the bidding
in the histogram.
And that makes sense.
It makes sense because it's less and less likely
that a stock is going to greatly exceed the strike
price if it started at the strike price
and these are random walks.
The more likely thing is it's going
to be closer to the original value,
depending on what the drift rate is, in this case,
set by the risk-free rate r.
So that's part of what the distribution looks like.
This also tells us ways that you could make a much better Monte
Carlo than the one I've suggested.
Since a lot of the paths, a large chunk of them,
in this case almost 60% of the paths, finished with a value,
with a contribution of 0 to my final sum,
then perhaps we could find a way to spend less time simulating
paths that aren't going to contribute to the final answer.
So those are our steps.
We needed to first simulate the paths and the underlying.
Second, we take those and we compute
the value of the derivative over its entire trajectory.
The third step is we then take an arithmetic
average of the terminal values that are out here.
I showed you the histogram, but you just
need to compute an average of those values.
So they're either S minus K or they're 0.
We compute an average.
And then we have a discount factor in front.
And that's what goes into my function right here, MCprice.
So let's run it and see what we get when I run my function.
I have a function that gives me put and a call.
And I've enhanced this a little bit to give me an estimate
for standard errors as well by analyzing the dispersion
of the results that I have.
But let's focus on the first two numbers.
So I have that for my set of parameters,
the call value should be worth $16.65.
The put value should be worth $7.35.
So that's it, right?
Well, maybe.
Let's consider two things.
One of them is we can check with the exact results
from Black-Scholes.
This is an approximation method, after all.
So if we compare with the exact results for Black-Scholes,
one way that we can do it is with a library
called R Quantlab that includes functions.
Or you can code them up yourself just from the Black-Scholes
formula, very easy to do.
And what we find is for the call,
the exact value is $16.73 against our value of $16.65.
So is that close enough?
At least for a ballpark.
But one of the things to think about
is, what is it that would make the answer precise?
Or if I told you that you needed the answer to be within $0.10,
within $1, within a penny, would you know what to change
in the simulation to get it to sufficient accuracy?
How about the put value?
Well, $7.22.
It looks like the exact value is $7.35.
So it looks like our call option is a little high.
Our put option is a little bit low.
So-- excuse me.
Our call value is a little bit below the true value.
Our put value is a little bit above the true value.
And one of the things that you should consider
when you do this is whether or not,
if you're computing different contracts
on the same underlying, should you re-run the random numbers
or not?
Should you re-run the same simulations?
There are two arguments, and I'll let you think about it
and decide for yourself.
One of them is that the whole point of this
is the random numbers need to be random.
They can't be biased.
So of course, every new thing you do,
you should do a new draw of random numbers.
The other argument says no, there's only one underlying.
And although we might be biased in a particular ensemble
and a particular set of paths might not
be exactly representative of what could happen in S,
it's very important in the marketplace
that we price puts and calls consistently with each other
in order to avoid arbitrage.
So what we could do in that case is generate one set of paths
for the underlying and then use those to price
puts and calls, different options with different strikes
and the same maturity.
Or if we want different maturities,
we could go out to simulate paths out
to our longest maturity, but then use that same set of paths
to use a subset of those for things that would expire
potentially sooner.
So finally, we might also remember that in addition
to comparing to the known true value--
and you should do that because now you've
got a great test case for your code.
You can check your code against the actual values.
So any numbers your pick, any parameters you want,
compare them to a Black-Scholes calculator.
And you'll know when you've got the right answer.
But remember, it is a random number generator.
So if I run my function again, I'm
going to get some different values.
This time I'm high, $16.85.
I run it again, $16.80.
So there's some scatter in the values I have.
You might think that I could compute
an average of these values.
One question I would ask you is, is there
any difference between averaging different runs of my Monte
Carlo pricer versus doing a single run with more
simulated paths inside it?
In any event, have fun with it.
This is your chance to do it and run a Monte Carlo
and see if you can reproduce the Black-Scholes results this way.
And keep in mind that this is not only an easy thing
to code and much easier than solving differential equations
or doing Gaussian integrals if you like
being around a computer at all.
You don't need to do it in R. You can do it in Python,
you can do it in Java, you can do it
in Visual Basic, anything you want.
And they've all been done.
They're all widely used.
But the other thing about the Monte Carlo method
is that it generalizes to cases where
we don't have closed form analytical solutions
to the partial differential equations.
So we might have a different process
for the underlying for which we don't have the closed form
answer, but we could still use this and put it
on the computer.
So it's always a good idea to take your algorithms,
to take your code, test them against known
cases like the pure Black-Scholes model,
and then you'll be ready to face more complicated problems that
show up in the real world.