PROFESSOR: Let's look at operating efficiency.
Define inventory turnover as cost
divided by ending inventory.
Sears ending inventory turnover is 26,231 divided
by 5,335, which is 4.92.
Assume that Sears uses LIFO.
Would inventory turnover be higher or lower under FIFO?
In order to solve this question, we
need to look at each component comprising the inventory
turnover.
First, what is the effect on COGS?
Under normal circumstances, this means rising prices.
So using FIFO would have lower COGS than using LIFO.
On the other hand, ending inventory value
would increase if FIFO is used.
Therefore, using FIFO would result in a lower inventory
turnover.