PROFESSOR: Now let's calculate profitability ratios.
Let's first look at the net margin.
For Walmart, net income is $8,039 million.
And revenues is $246,565 million.
Since that margin is net income over revenues,
the net margin for Walmart in 2003 is 3.26%.
Sears's net margin is $3,397 million divided by $41,124
million, which would give us 8.26% for Sears's.
Net margin.
ROE, on the other hand, is calculated
as net income divided by ending total shareholders' equity.
$8,039 divided by $39,337--
ROE for Walmart will be 20.43%.
Using the same calculation, Sears's ROE
is $3,397 divided by $6,401, which equals to 53.07%.
Walmart's ROE was 20.43% in 2003.
In 2003, how would the following transactions affect its ROE?
In 2003, Walmart paid a dividend.
In this case, ROE would increase because net income is not
affected, but shareholders' equity decreases.
If Walmart wrote off receivables, what would happen?
ROE is unaffected because write-offs would not
affect net income and equity.
If Walmart sold one factory and gained $2,000 on sale,
what would happen?
ROE would increase because net income would increase,
and shareholders' equity would also
increase by the same amount.
Since ROE is smaller than 1, the same amount increase
in denominator and numerator would result in an overall ROE
increase.