INSTRUCTOR: Our next topic is DuPont decomposition.
DuPont analysis decomposes ROE into ratios of solvency,
profitability, and efficiency.
Using this analysis helps us to analyze
what aspect of the business is doing a good job.
First, recall that ROE is net income divided by equity.
Second, we could rewrite the first equation
to net income divided by assets times assets over equity.
This is equivalent to ROA times leverage.
Going a step further, we could rewrite the equation once again
to net income divided by sales times sales
divided by assets times assets divided
by shareholders' equity.
This is profit margin times asset turnover times leverage.
Note here that leverage is defined as assets over equity,
not liabilities over equity.
Be sure to check the exact definition for each ratio
when solving problem sets or exam questions.
The definitions will be given to you there.
Let's go back to the Walmart and Sears example.
Walmart's ROE is 20.4% and is comprised
of net margin of 3.26%, turnover of 2.6, and leverage of 2.41.
On the other hand, Sears ROE is 53.1%, which
is higher than Walmart's ROE.
Now let's decompose this and see what
exactly is triggering Sears's ROE to be higher
than Walmart's ROE.
Sears's is net margin is 8.26% and has
an asset turnover of 1.48 and a leverage of 4.33%.
What are the differences here?
Sears's net margin is much higher,
indicating higher profitability, and asset utilization
or asset turnover is lower.
And Sears also has a higher leverage than Walmart does.
In other words, Sears's business in 2003
was more profitable but probably less solvent.
Hence, Sears has a higher ROE than Walmart.
What happens is Sears pays out cash dividends
at the end of the year.
First, assets decrease because cash goes down.
Equity also decreases because retained earnings goes down.
Therefore, asset utilization or asset turnover
increases, and leverage also goes up.
Finally, ROE increases using all these changes
that were in play.