PROFESSOR: Let's solve some example questions.
Let's take a look at Walmart and Sears back in 2003.
Suppose at the end of fiscal year 2003,
Walmart and Sears had the following balance sheet
numbers.
What would the current ratio and leverage
ratio for Walmart and Sears be?
First, let's calculate Walmart's current ratio.
Current ratio is current assets divided by current liabilities.
Walmart's ending current assets and current liabilities in 2003
are at 30,483 million and 32,617 million respectively.
Dividing the current assets into current liabilities
would give us 0.93.
Sears's current ratio on the other hand, current assets
is 18,196 billion, and current liabilities is 13,759 million.
So the current ratio is 1.32.
What about the leverage ratio?
Leverage ratio is defined as ending total liabilities
over a total shareholders' equity.
55,348 million is divided by 39,337, which equals 1.41.
Sears leverage ratio is 3.33 since total liabilities
and shareholders' equity for Sears in 2003
is 21,322 million and 6,401 million respectively.
We've calculated Sears debt to equity ratio or the leverage
ratio in 2003.
Now in 2003, how would Sears leverage ratio
change if the following transactions were done?
First, what if Sears paid more dividends in 2003?
Leverage would increase since shareholders' equity would
be lower.
But liabilities would not have been affected.
What if Sears writes off more receivables in 2003?
Debt to equity or leverage wouldn't
change, since write offs doesn't affect liabilities
and shareholders' equity.
What if Sears issued $1 billion of long-term debt?
Leverage would increase because liabilities would increase
following the $1 billion issuance of long-term debt,
but shareholders' equity wouldn't change.
What if Sears issued $1 billion in long-term debt and $1
billion of stock in 2003?
Leverage would decrease.
Recall the changes in the ratio slide a couple of slides back.
Since Sears leverage is greater than 1,
and both numerator and denominator
increase by the same amount, the leverage ratio would decrease.