PROFESSOR: Question 1 is on temporary differences.
Part A-- ABC Company buys new production equipment,
costing $10,000.
The equipment has a 10 year useful life and no salvage
value.
Under current tax rules, the machinery
may be fully depreciated in a year.
Suppose that ABC Company generates revenues up
of $50,000 and has expenses of $30,000.
Assume a tax rate of 30% and a straight line depreciation
method for accounting purposes.
What's the effect on deferred taxes?
Express this in the balance sheet equation.
In order to assess what the deferred taxes would
be in this situation, we first need
to obtain depreciation expenses for both accrual accounting
and tax accounting.
Calculating depreciation expenses for accrual accounting
is fairly straightforward, assuming a straight line
depreciation method.
Cost of $10,000 with no salvage value
and a useful life of 10 years give us a depreciation expense
of $1,000 a year.
For tax purposes, depreciation expenses $10,000 in year 1.
The question tells us that the machinery
is fully depreciated in year 1.
So we used the forecast as depreciation expense in year 1.
This difference in timing results
in ABC Company recognizing a lower taxable income
for tax purposes.
For both accounting methods, we have
$50,000 in revenue, $30,000 in operating expenses.
The depreciation is $1,000 and $10,000
for accrual accounting and tax accounting, respectively.
Therefore, using tax accounting lowers the earnings
before taxes, or EBT, by $9,000.
This $9,000 times 30%, which is the tax rate,
equal to $2,700, which is the lower amount of taxes
paid in the current period, but needs to be paid in the future.
Therefore this $2,700 number is deferred tax liability.
How do we express this with the balance sheet equation?
First, we know that we pay $3,000 in cash
to the IRS in this period.
So cash decreases by $3,000 we also
know that from book income, tax expense is $5,700.
The difference of $2,700 increases DTL
and balances the BSE out.
Part B-- what would happen next year?
The year after, tax expense for book accounting
remains the same, because the firm employs a straight line
method over 10 years of useful life.
For tax accounting purposes, however,
since the asset was fully depreciated in year 1,
there's no depreciation expense to report.
Year 2 EBT for book accounting is $19,000,
which is the same as year 1's EBT,
whereas year 2 EBT under tax accounting
is $20,000, which is now higher than the book income.
Assuming the same 30% tax rate, $300 of DTL will reverse.
To express this using the BSE, cash decreases by $6,000,
because cash taxes paid is $6,000.
Retained earnings decreases by $5,700
to account for the book accounting tax expenses.
The difference of $300 decreases the DTL
we originally had in the books.