PROFESSOR: Question 2-- more taxes.
Refer to Pfizer's tax footnotes to solve
the following questions part A-- what is Pfizer's 2009
effective tax rate the footnote tells us
at the bottom row the ETR for Pfizer
is 20.3% Part B-- what is the major reason
why Pfizer's effective tax rate is different from the US
statutory rate of 35%?
The biggest difference against the statutory rate
stems from earnings taxed at other than US statutory rate.
This decreased ETR by 9.3 percentage points.
Part C-- assume that in 2010, Pfizer
reports book depreciation of $20,000 in millions,
like the financial statements, and tax depreciation
of $40,000.
What is the effect of this transaction
on Pfizer's deferred tax liability for 2010?
As statutory tax rate of 35% for this question.
Book depreciation was $20,000, and tax depreciation
was $40,000 this would tell us that tax income is
lower than book income.
And this tells us that Pfizer will have
to pay more tax in the future.
Therefore, DTL will increase by 20,000 times
the tax rate of 35%, which we assumed
in this question, or $7,000.