PROFESSOR: In our discussion on capital structure
in the previous lecture, we have established the MM result.
That is, in absence of imperfections
in the financial market, a firm's value
does not depend on its capital structure.
A major interpretation of MM's insight
is that capital structure may matter if there are frictions.
In this lecture, we are going to extend the basic MM framework
by relaxing its assumptions.
In particular, by introducing market
frictions into our analysis.
We proceed in two steps.
In the first step, which is this lecture,
we introduce two of the most basic frictions.
The first is taxes, which will occur at two levels.
At the corporate level and also at the personal level.
As we will see, taxes at both levels
can have major impacts on the firm's financing choices.
The second is the cost of financial distress.
When the firm takes on debt it may face financial distress
when default risk becomes substantial.
This situation can bring non-trivial costs
to debt financing.
In the second step, we briefly consider
several other frictions in later lectures.
Which include transaction costs for issuing debt and equity,
asymmetric information about the firm's investments,
capital structure may influence managers investment decisions.