PROFESSOR: We want to illustrate the points
above through an example.
415inc is a fintech company.
It's currently 100% equity-financed.
The value of its asset is given by
the following binomial process.
Its current market value at year 0 is $100 million.
Next year, which is year 1, the asset value can go up to 120
or stay at 100 with equal probabilities.
The risk-free rate is 5%.
415inc learned from its investment banker
that you can issue a one-year bond
with the principal amount P equals 80
at a reasonable promised yield y.
When 415inc fails to pay the interest in full,
it incurs a cost of default. The cost is given by c times yP
minus capital Y squared, where yP is the promised interest
payment and capital Y is the actual interest paid,
where capital Y is no greater than yP and c equals 1/320.
The cost is positive only when capital Y
is less than y times P.
Since P equals 80, and the asset value is 100 in the bad state,
415inc will never default on the principal.
415inc's tax rate is tau equals 30%.
As the CEO of 415inc, you need to answer the following
questions.
Should you issue the bond?
Why?
If you decide to issue the bond, how
should you choose y, which is the promised yield?
How much can you increase the value of 415inc today
by doing this?
We consider the situation in two steps.
First, suppose that 415inc wants to issue
bonds that's risk-free.
Then in a down state the asset value is 100.
In order to guarantee both the principal and interest payment,
we have 1 plus y times P no greater than Vd,
the value of the asset in a down state,
or 1 plus y times 80 no greater than 100.
This will give y no greater than 0.25.
That is, the promised yield cannot exceed 25%.
Therefore, if 415inc issues the one-year bond with principal P
equals 80 and promised yield y, the promised interest payment
will be yP.
That's 80 times y.
The tax shield is tau times yP in both states in year 1.
Its present value is then PVTS--
that's Present Value of Tax Shield--
equals 0.3, the tax rate, times the promised interest payment--
that's 80 times y divided by 1 plus 5%, the discount rate.
And that gives 22.86 times y.
This is positive and increases with y.
The value of 415inc now becomes VL,
the value of the levered home equals
VU, the value of the unlevered firm,
plus PVTS, which is a function of the debt level D.
That equals 100 plus 22.86 times y.
It is maximized by setting y equals 0.25 without default,
which gives 105.72.
This is higher than the value of the unlevered firm, which
is 100.
Can we do better than this?
Next, we consider when y goes beyond 25%.
Increasing y will further increase the tax benefit.
However, there will be default in the down state.
Here, we will assume 80 times y is no greater than 40,
or y is no greater than 0.5, so that there will not
be default in the up state.
Now in the up state, we will get more tax shield,
which is tau times yP, and increases with y.
But in a down state, the actual interest payment
is Vd, the value of the asset in the down state,
minus P, the principal, which equals 100 minus 80,
and that's 20.
It gives a tax shield of 0.3 times
20, which is fixed and independent of y.
The default amount in the down state is 80 times y minus 0.25.
It leads to a default cost given by the default cost, which
depends on y, the promised yield, that equals c times 80
squared times y minus 0.25 squared.
Therefore, we have the value of the firm with leverage
to be VL equals VU plus the present value of tax shield,
which depends on y, minus the present value of default cost,
which also depends on y.
That gives 100 plus the two additional terms,
namely the present value of tax shield
and present value of default cost.
How do we value tax shield and default costs,
which are now both risky?
In order to value the risky tax shield and default cost,
we need to find the risk-neutral probabilities for the two
states in year 1.
Given the binomial process for the value
of the underlying asset, we should know how
to do this pretty well by now.
From the price of the asset, we have
100 equals q, the risk-neutral probability
for up state, times 120, the value
of the asset in a good state, plus 1 minus q,
the risk-neutral probability for the down state,
times the value of the asset in a down state
that's 100, divided by 1 plus the risk-free rate.
Solving for this equation, we'll get q equals 1/4.
Then the present value of tax shield is given by PVTS equals
0.3, the tax rate, times 1/4, the risk-neutral probably
for the up state, times 80y--
that's the interest payment in a good state--
plus 3/4 times 20, and then divide
by 1 plus risk-free rate.
Finishing the calculation, we get 6.86.
The present value of default cost is given by PVDC.
That equals 3/4 times 1/320, the coefficient of default cost,
times 80 squared times y minus 0.25 squared,
and again divided by 1 plus the risk-free rate of 5%.
Finishing the calculation gives 0.57.
In the above, we have also solved for the optimal y
to be 0.45, which is less than 0.5 Indeed,
and substituted it into PVTS and PVDC.
At y equals 0.45, the default cost is 0.8.
The value of the levered firm, which
is maximized at y equals 0.45, is
given by VL equals VU plus PVTS at y equal to 0.45 minus PVDC,
also at 0.45.
That gives us 100, the value of the unlevered firm,
plus 6.86, which is the present value of tax shield,
minus 0.57, which is the present value of the default cost.
That gives us 106.29.
The market value of the debt is given by D equals q,
the risk-neutral probability for the up state,
times 80 times 1 plus 0.45--
that's the total payoff in the up state-- plus 1 minus
q, the risk-neutral probability for the down state, times 100
minus 0.8, which is default cost.
And then divide that by 1 plus the risk-free rate of 5%,
the calculation gives us 98.48, which is at a premium,
because the price is higher than the par value of the debt.
What to do with the proceeds from the bond issue then?
Well, we can use the money to buy back shares.
We will discuss the mechanics of share buyback in lecture 20,
when we consider payout policies.
The market value of equity after the share repurchase is E
equals the value of the levered firm minus debt,
which is 106.29 minus 99.48.
And that gives $7.81 million.
The above refinancing has increased the shareholder value
by 106.29 minus 100, which is $6.29 million.
The above example, although simple,
has shown the following.
First, how leverage leads to a firm's tax benefit and distress
cost; second, how to value the tax benefit and cost
of distress; third, how to optimize a firm's capital
structure knowing the value of these two pieces;
and four, how much value the optimal financing
choice can bring.