PROFESSOR: We now consider another example
in interest rate risk management in the context
of asset liability management.
Suppose an insurance company issues a guaranteed investment
contract, also called GIC, which are basically zeros.
It has a par value of $10,000, it
has a maturity of five years, and a guaranteed interest
rate of 8%.
Therefore, at maturity, the insurance company
pays the par value plus total interest,
which is $10,000 times 1 plus 8% raised to the power of 5.
Suppose that the insurance company
chooses to fund this obligation by investing
in a six-year Treasury bond with a par value of $10,000
and coupon rate of 8%, trading at par at this point.
This implies that the current interest rate is also 8%.
Therefore, after issuing the GIC,
the insurance company incurs a fixed-income liability of L0
equals $10,000 in the form of a five-year zero.
This liability is then funded by a six-year coupon bond
as an asset with 8% coupon rate and a market value of A0--
also equals $10,000.
If interest rate stays at 8% for the next five years,
the value of the asset will perfectly
match the value of the liability.
That is, A5 equals 10,000 times 1.08 to the power of 5,
and that gives us L5.
But what if interest rate changes?
The value of the asset, which is a six-year coupon
bond, and the liability, which is a five-year at zero,
will both change where interest rate changes.
But how much?
We can easily compute the following.
First, the duration of the liability is DL.
That equals five years.
The duration of the asset, which is DA--
and that equals 4.9927, also in years.
Since the asset and the liability
have almost the same duration, the liability
remains close to be fully funded for small interest rate
changes.
That is, delta A minus delta L equals minus 10,000
times 4.9927--
the duration for the asset--
minus 5-- the duration for the liability--
divide by 1.08-- the yield--
times delta r, the change in the yield.
And that's approximately 10,000 times 0.006759 times delta r.
And that's approximately 0, if delta r is small.
What about large interest rate changes?
The table on the slide shows the changes
in the value of asset and liability.
The second row gives the values of asset in liability at r
equals 8%.
They are matched.
The third row gives their values when
interest rate increases to 9%.
The match is close, but not perfect.
Clearly, for large interest rate changes,
the mismatch between asset and liability
becomes more substantial.
In this case, it is $1.79.
This is because, as we have learned
in the fixed-income lecture in part 1 of this course,
we have different convexities.
We can compute the convexity for the asset and liability,
respectively.
The results are as follows.
The convexity of the liability is CXL.
That equals 12.86.
The convexity for the asset is CXE.
That equals 14.02.
Including the second-order terms in values
of asset and liability, we have the following equation.
Delta A minus delta L is approximately 10,000 times
0.006759 times 1%--
which is the change in yield--
plus 10,000 times 14.02 minus 12.86 times 1% yield change
squared.
And that gives us 1.84.
This approximately explains the mismatch
between asset and liability in the previous table.
This example demonstrates two points.
First, for asset liability management,
we can properly choose the asset to greatly reduce interest rate
risk by matching their modified durations, especially
for small interest rate changes.
Second, for large interest rate movements,
however, matching modified duration still
leaves an interest rate risk of the second order.
To further reduce the second-order risk,
we may need to consider further matching convexities
between the asset and liability.
Interest rate risks can be easily hedged
using interest rate forwards or futures.
We consider, in our last example on risk management.
Suppose that we have $1 billion invested in the portfolio
of government bonds, and are concerned
about volatile interest rates over the next three months.
We have decided to use three months Treasury bonds forwards
or futures to protect the value of this investment.
The modified duration of the bond portfolio is 6.80.
Forwards and futures on 10-year treasury bonds
are actively traded, and we have the following information
on that.
The T-bond to be delivered has a modified duration of 9.20.
The T-bond pays no coupons over the next three months.
Let the current T-bond price be B10.
Each contract delivers $100,000 of face value of T-bonds.
The forward and futures price is F equals $93.50 for face value
of $100.
The forward and futures price for one contract is $93,500.
The three-month interest rate is r
equals 1%, which is not annualized.
By no arbitrage, we have the following equation
for the forward and spot prices of the bond.
F equals 1 plus r times B10, and that equals 1.01 times B10.
The first question is, in order to hedge the interest rate
risk of our bond portfolio, should we
long or short interest rate forwards and futures?
Of course, short, given that our original position is long
in bonds.
The next question is, how many contracts to short?
We need to properly match modified duration.
Let's work this out.
If yield curve shifts by delta y,
the value of the bond portfolio changes by delta VP.
That's approximately minus 6.80 times Vp times delta y.
The current price on the 10-year T-bond changes by delta B10--
approximately minus 9.20 times B10 times delta y.
Forward price changes by delta F--
approximately minus 1.01 times 9.20 times B10 times delta y.
And that equals minus 9.20 times F times delta y.
Gains and losses on the forward contract
are realized in three months.
Matching the gain/loss in present value terms,
we have the following equation--
minus the number of contracts times 1/1.01 times 93,500 times
9.20 times delta y--
the left-hand side-- equals minus $1 billion--
that's the portfolio value--
times 6.80-- its modified duration-- times delta y.
That's the right-hand side.
Therefore, the number of contracts to short
is given by the following equation.
The number of contracts should equal to 1.01 times 1 billion
divided by 93,500, then times 6.80 divided by 9.20.
That gives us 7,905.14.
Hence, we need to short 7,905 contracts.
One important point to note is that, in this hedging strategy,
the hedge ratio is based on the modified
durations of the portfolio and the hedging vehicle.
Both of them will change over time.
Therefore, we need to rebalance the hedge accordingly.