PROFESSOR: Summarizing our analysis
we obtained several important points.
First, the naive discounted cash flow analysis
tends to underestimate the value of strategic options embedded
in real investments.
Next, projects often contain various types of options.
Follow-on projects are like American calls.
Abandonment options are like American puts.
Scale options are like conversion options or calls
and puts.
Timing options are like American calls.
It is in general difficult to apply this kind of cash
flow calculations to value real options.
When the underlying asset is traded,
however, we can value real options
by using market prices of the underlying asset.
The examples we considered in this lecture
all fall into this category.
More generally, instead of thinking
about a firm's investments as a process of acquiring
and disposing assets, we can think of them
as a process of acquiring and disposing of options
and exercising the options optimally.