PROFESSOR: In this video, let's use the same approach,
but instead of constructing an arbitrage strategy that
generates $100 right now, we will construct an arbitrage
strategy that generates $100 in year 1 and 0 in years 0 and 2.
In our system of equations, the only thing that changes
is the desired payoff.
Right now, instead of $100 in the first equation in year 0,
we have $100 in the second equation, or in year 1.
Now let's go back to Excel and solve this system.
Let's change our desired outcome vector
by putting 0 dollars in the first cell in year 0
and $100 in the second cell, or in year 1.
And since everything is soft-coded in my spreadsheet,
everything automatically changes.
So you could see that our positions are recalculated,
and you could see that the net payoff--
now I have 0 in year 0 and 100 in year 1, exactly what I want.
Let's look at the positions.
We are going short r1, short f1, and we're going long r2.
And although the numbers change, the logic does not change.
We're still going long r2, just because r2 is a higher
rate relative to r1 and f1.