PROFESSOR: Now, there is an alternative way
of thinking about this problem.
And it may be easier for you to think in these other terms
because our liabilities are in the United States dollars.
So in this case, what we would do
is that, to satisfy these liabilities,
that, again, we have one year from now,
we notice that this is how much we will get in Japanese yen
in one year.
What we can do is that we can convert this amount
that we'll get in one year in Japanese yen
to United States dollars.
And we can do that by locking ourselves
into the one-year forward exchange rate that,
again, currently trades at 106.
Now in this case, then, our income, one year right
now can be expressed in the United States dollars
by doing the following.
So taking this Japanese yen amount and dividing it by 106.
Now let me also show you that if we
were to express our future income in United States
dollars, we'd have gotten, of course, the same answer
at the very end.
So if our liabilities are x times 1 plus 1% USD,
then our income expressed in United States dollars
would be the original amount divided by 106 because this
is us locking in the forward exchange rate when we take
this Japanese yen and converted it into the United States
dollars using this 106 forward exchange rate.
So, and then, in this case, again,
equating our income with our liabilities
would give us this equation right now.
So this is the original divided by 106,
and this would equal to x times 1 plus 1%.
And now you could see that this is,
of course, the same equation as we had before.
And so if we were to solve it, we
would have gotten exactly the same result at the very end.
So therefore, of course it doesn't
matter whether we express our income and our liabilities
in either Japanese yen at the end of the year
or in the United States dollars.
The end result is the same.