PROFESSOR: In the previous video,
we built an arbitrage trading strategy
to exploit a situation when the forward was overpriced.
Now, consider the converse situation, when
the forward is underpriced.
Let's assume that the price of this two-year
forward is $1,015.
How do we exploit this?
Consider the following trading strategy.
Since the forward is underpriced,
we will engage in one long forward contract.
Next, we will short-sell the following number of shares,
e to the power of negative yT.
We will invest the proceeds from the short sale
of the stock, which will be e to the power
of negative yT times S-naught dollars at the risk-free rate.
Notice that the initial cost of setting up this portfolio
is zero.
Let's see what happens two years from now.
First, let's figure out how many shares of stock
we need to return.
The answer is one share.
Recall that we borrowed e to the power of negative yT shares,
but the share pays continuous dividend y,
and therefore we need to return both dividends
and the original amount of shares to the owner.
If the dividends are continuously reinvested,
the original borrowed amount would grow to one share.
Second, our initial investment at the risk-free rate
is now worth $1,020.20.
Next, you take $1,015 out of this
$1,020.20 that you have in your bank account,
and you pay the seller of the forward contract, who
in turn delivers one share of stock to you.
You use this share of stock to cover your short position.
As a result, this trading strategy generates $5.20
in profits per one forward contract bought.
The reason for this arbitrage profits
is, again, the fact that the forward contract
was initially underpriced.