INSTRUCTOR: Let's use an alternative way
to solve this question.
Recall that for a swap that has a term of capital T years,
the fixed rate on the swap rs is given
by the following expression where these are
prices of zero-discount bonds.
In our case, given that our swap has three-year term,
the fixed rate on the swap should equal to the following
expression--
1 minus the price of a three-year, zero-coupon bond
divided by the sum of the prices of one-year, two-year, and
three-year zero-coupon bonds.
Given spot rates r1, r2, and r3, we
can rewrite the previous equation
in the following terms.
Plugging in the numbers, we will get rs equal to 4.185%.
This is exactly the same result as we
obtained in the previous video.