INSTRUCTOR: Finally, let us construct an arbitrage trading
strategy that generates $100 in year 2 and nothing
in years 0 and 1.
Again, the only thing that changes
is the right-hand side of the equation 3
where instead of 0, we have $100 right now.
So we're getting $0 in years 0 and 1 and $100 in year 2.
Let's go back to Excel and solve the system.
Recall that in my spreadsheet, everything is soft coded.
So all I have to do right now is I have to put 0 in year 1
and I have to put 100, my desired outcome, in year 2.
And therefore, this Excel spreadsheet
will recompute the positions that I have to take in order
to achieve this outcome.
So I have to go short R1 in this exact amount,
short F1 in this amount, and go long in this amount in R2.