PROFESSOR: So what does random walk model consist of?
It's a sum of IID random variables.
IID means independent and identically distributed.
By independent, we mean that the z1, z2,
z3 are independent random variables like two
different dice, two different flips of a coin,
or two different coins entirely.
So the individual z's have nothing to do with each other.
But we are putting them together in a particular sequence.
Identically distributed means that they
each are drawn from the same probability
distribution no surprise there.
What are the attributes of this sum ST where I take
it to be z1, plus z2, plus z3?
Because the variables are independent,
the values that we have don't depend on--
the new values that get added don't
depend on the previous history.
So each new increment can be added independently
of what came before.
The other thing is the importance
of the identically distributed part
is-- it means that the evolution in time is uniform.
And we call this property stationarity.
It doesn't mean that the model is static.
It doesn't mean it's deterministic.
All it means is that if we look at the values between any two
points in time, the properties depend only
on the differences in the point in time,
not on some absolute point in time.
So any given three-step period is going to be equivalent.
One of the things we're going to see
that's fascinating about the random walk model
are some of its aspects of universality.
There are a lot of features of it
that are really independent of the micro-level.
And that's going to be interesting
for us starting out right now.
And it's going to be something we'll
take advantage of when we take the limit of this model
to go to continuous time a little bit later in the course.
So it's easy to generalize for financial applications.
This bare-bones model is going to be a little bit simple.
But hang on a very short time, and we'll add in two parameters
to make it useful for finance.
The random walk appears in many other contexts
in applied mathematics, and physics, and engineering.
And it's the building block for more complex models.
So we're going to start to get to know it well.
Then we'll see how to build it.
Although this model doesn't have any memory of the past,
we'll see that models that do have
interesting non-trivial causal structure
can be expressed in terms of building blocks
that do come from what we'll see in the random walk model.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to start with the simplest of all random variables.
We'll call these standardized random variables,
and we'll denote them by the letter z.
And they've got these properties.
First, they're mean is 0.
So these are unbiased.
They're equally likely to be positive or negative.
The average value is 0.
Their variance is 1.
So they have a standard amount of randomness, a standard step
size for these given increments.
And for our independence part, the correlation
of any two random variables taken at different points
in time is 0.
So we can summarize these three properties symbolically
in this box.
We've got that the expectation of z is 0.
The expectation of z squared is the variance.
Remember that the variance is the expectation
of the square minus the square of the expectation.
The expectation is 0.
So expectation of z squared is the variance.
It's equal to 1.
And, because z of t and z of t prime,
if t and t prime are two different times,
are two independent random variables,
the expectation of the product is equal to 0.
And this is the same as their correlation
when they have mean 0.
And remember for independent random variables,
the expectation of a product is the product
of the expectations.
Each of the expectations is 0.
0 times 0 is 0.
So what are some examples z's that we could use?
This is all we need.
We only need the things that we have here in this box.
So one example, the classic random walk,
is something like a coin toss.
We take a step to the left, to the right.
We go up.
We go down.
We move plus 1 or minus 1 with equal probability.
So we can model that with the discrete random variable, zt.
zt takes values plus or minus 1 with equal probability.
Obviously, it satisfies these properties in the box above.
Another example is a continuous z, a Gaussian random variable.
This one is also going to be normalized.
So zt is drawn from an N 0, 1 distribution with mean 0,
variance 1.
And it's probability distribution
is the usual Gaussian form normalized.
So e to the minus z squared over 2 is the probability density.
The expectation is 0 because this is an even function.
And to show that its variance is equal to 1
involves doing a definite integral.
So everything that we're about to see
would be true with either of these variables.
Notice that they're quite different in detail
that the first one, the discrete one,
will only allow our sum to have discrete values.
The second one is continuously distributed.
Our trick-- and we're going to be coming back to this again
and again--
is that, when we're interested in a sum of random variables--
this is our S of T--
we're not going to ask for the full probability distribution.
We're only going to ask for the mean and the variance.
We're only going to ask for the individual moments.
And the detailed distribution could
be complicated in the case of the plus or minus 1.
We have a binomial distribution.
It's easy to work out the combinatorics.
It's a lot more work than what we're going to do.
And we're not going to need the more fine grained detail
of all the higher moments.
For the Gaussian random variable,
it's kind of a special case because, as you may know,
the sum of Gaussian random variables is Gaussian.
So there's some special results there.
But any z that satisfies these properties
will work for what we're about to see.
So what's that?
Let's take a look.
We'll consider the sum of random variables.
ST is z1 plus, z2, plus z3.
And we're not going to ask about the distribution of S of T.
But we're going to ask about its mean and its variance.
So what about the mean?
For the mean of the sum, ST, We have a very simple result.
Remember that expectation is a linear operator.
That means that the expectation of a sum
is the sum of the expectations so the expectation of ST
is the expectation of z1, plus the expectation z2, plus da,
da, da, da, up to the expectation of the final one.
Since each of these expectations is equal to 0,
your sum is equal to 0, no surprise
there really if you think about it.
This is unbiased.
We add together a bunch of unbiased random variables.
The mean value is the same as the value of each of them.
It's 0.
What about the variance?
The variance a little more interesting.
So for the variance, we have the expectation of S squared.
Again, we're able to simplify this because S has mean 0.
So let's just plug it in.
Expand out this quadratic.
So the term in parentheses z1, plus z2, plus zT,
all the way up is S of T. We take the square.
Let's expand that quadratic, and we get two kinds terms.
And then we apply linearity.
That is, for each of the terms, the expectation of the sum
is the sum of the expectations.
So we have two kinds of terms.
We have these squared terms whereas z1
gets multiplied times z1.
And I have these terms here, which
are the expectation of one of z's with itself, z1 squared,
z2 squared, z3 squared.
And I have T of these.
And I could have the cross terms,
where I have z1 with z2, z2 with z3, z4 with z7, and so on.
Each of those appear twice.
There are T choose 2 of those terms.
But wonderfully in this product, each of these is equal to 0.
So every single term in this second sum is equal to 0.
And the first consists of T terms, each of which
is equal to 1.
So the result is the variance of ST,
the sum of the random variables, is equal to T.
So here's our basic result. The mean of the random walk is 0.
The variance of the random walk grows linearly
with the number of steps.
And the standard deviation, which
is the square root of the variance,
grows with the square root of T. Let's summarize.
The random walk model is constructed
as a sum of IID random variables.
We take a bunch of z's.
We put them together.
And S1 is z1.
S2 is z1 plus z2.
S3 is z1, plus z2, plus z3, and so on.
It's a simple example of a discrete time
stochastic process.
Rather than asking for the complete distribution of ST,
we ask about the moments.
We ask about the mean and the variance.
And those are computed very easily by linearity.
The mean is 0.
The variance is proportional to the number of steps.
And we've done this all using standardized random variable z.
They could be continuous, discrete.
They could be anything that satisfies
these basic standard properties.
Namely, the expectation of z is 0.
The variance of z is 1.
And the expectation of two different z's
taken at two different times is equal to 0.