PROFESSOR: Let's generalize the random walk model now
by adding two parameters.
So what we'll do is we will take our basic standardized random
variable, z, and we're going to multiply it times 1
constant called sigma.
And that's a scale factor.
And then, we're going to add another constant, mu.
So it's very simple-- just a linear generalization
of our previous z.
So we'll call this linear combination sigma z plus mu.
We'll give it a new name.
We'll call it r.
We still have the property that the steps
are independent in each time period.
That follows from the independence of the z's.
So the z's are our same old friends the z's we had before.
And the new random variable, not surprisingly,
is going to have a different mean and variance.
The two parameters that we have, sigma and mu,
are going to be interpreted in financial applications
as parameters that describe risk and return, which are the two
basic elements we need of course, for understanding
investments, for understanding financial markets.
And this is the simplest non-trivial model
that we've got.
So let's see where that takes us.
If we want to match this on-- just to give you a heads up
for where we're going--
consider stock prices.
Observe regularly, say daily--
P1, P2, P3 are different stock prices.
And we can think of the return from one period to the next
as being possibly modeled by a random variable.
We don't know in the future what's
going to happen from one day to the next.
We can ask what's the distribution from which
these variables are drawn.
And if they are drawn from an IID distribution,
if they're independent and identically distributed,
what would be the consequences of compounding these returns
over a long period of time?
The identification we typically make
is to identify r sub t, which I've denoted with a little r,
to be the logarithm of the price ratio.
And this is close to the simple return numerically.
But we'll see that this is a better
model both empirically and theoretically.
We can go backwards from these returns
to the prices in the same way that we mentioned before,
that we can add and iterate the process if we
have a recursive idea of what the returns are
and the prices are.
And we can build up the price series
by looking at a compounded sum of returns.
Because we've taken the logarithm
to get the little bars, we exponentiate to get the prices.
So this is how we can think about where
these r's in this generalized random model,
these r's are going to fit in to a model for asset prices.
Now, since the expectational operator is linear,
we're going to generalize our previous results.
It will be almost as easy as what we did before.
So we have that the return is just a constant time z plus mu.
We know that the expectation of a constant,
and we know the expectation of a sum
is the sum of the expectations.
So the expectation of the sum is mu plus sigma times
the expectation of z.
And we remember that the expectation of z is 0.
So very simply, the expected return of r sub t is mu.
What about the variance?
The variance is defined as the expectation of the square
of the variable minus its mean.
We just computed the mean on the line above.
And r minus mu is sigma z.
We take that squared.
The constant, sigma squared, comes out of the expectation.
The expectation of z squared is 1.
So we're left with the variance of r is sigma squared.
And then our last relationship among the z's translates here
as well.
And this gives us the covariance of two
r's taken at different periods of time.
The definition of the covariance is the expectation
of the product of two random variables,
relative to their means.
Because rt and our rt prime have an arbitrary time index,
they have the same mean.
And this is just the same thing as the expectation value.
It's proportional to the expectation
value of the zt equals zt prime at two different times.
And that's equal to 0, as we've seen before.
Now, here's where it gets interesting.
Let's take a look at what happens when we
add a bunch of them together.
So let's look at defining a new thing I'll call X big T
to be r1 plus r2 plus r3.
And what we're interested in is the dependence on time.
So the r's are independent of each other.
But we'd like to know how the distribution of X
depends on the moments of the individual r's,
and in particular how it depends on how many of them
we have-- that is what's the time dependence.
So once again, we use linearity.
We take expectations of both sides of this equation,
and we expand out.
What do we find?
First, for the mean, the expectation of XT
is the expectation of r1 plus expectation of r2 and so on.
Each of these expectations is identical.
This is mu plus mu plus mu, T times.
And that gives us T times mu.
So remember that our standardized,
our pure random walk standardized, just
the sum of the z's had been 0.
Now we have a slightly different result,
because each of the r's has a non-zero mean.
The result is T times the individual mean.
How about the variance?
The variance is only slightly more complicated.
We just need to do a little bit of algebra.
The variance, as always, is defined
as the expectation of the square of the variable minus its mean.
We just computed the mean.
It was T times mu.
Now, here's a convenient trick.
Let's write it out.
Let's write T mu is mu plus mu plus mu plus mu.
And let's expand out X. So that we
can group this together in these suggestive and interesting
groupings, as the expectation of r1 minus mu plus r2
minus mu, plus, and so on up to rT minus mu.
So each of these things--
r minus mu as a unit, is the random component
of our process.
We can think of mu as being a deterministic piece.
It's the amount that gets added in every single period.
And we're also getting a random component.
That's our sigma zT term.
So these are the sum of these random variables.
Since each of these r minus mus is a sigma z1, sigma z2, and so
on, we have a sigma squared that pulls out of the expectation,
because it's a constant multiplier.
And then, we got to use our previous result--
that we have the expectation of the sum of z's quantity squared
is just T. So, now we have this scale factor of sigma squared.
And that's our basic result for this generalized random walk.
So to summarize-- the generalized random walk model
is constructed as a sum of IID random variables,
r1 plus r2 plus r3.
Each of these generalizes our standard z
by multiplying it times 1 constant, sigma,
and adding another mu.
We can think of these as being related to volatility,
the risk associated with an investment,
and mu, the constant deterministic return
that we would have if we turn volatility off.
The mean and the variance are linear in time.
So as before, we apply linearity and compute expectations.
Notice that we're not computing here, the full distribution
of x.
And we haven't used the full distribution of the individual
r's.
We've just used the mean and variance
of r's to get the mean and variance and covariances,
and those properties for x and T.
Our basic result that's going to be
important for financial applications
and for our intuition about randomness
and financial markets, is that the mean
is proportional to time.
And the variance is proportional to time,
which means it's square root, which we associate
with the volatility grows as square root of T.
That is the volatility, the standard deviation of x sub T,
is sigma times the square root of T.
And square root of T, as it gets large,
grows more slowly than T.