PROFESSOR: Let's generalize further by looking
at linear time series models that go beyond the random walk.
We want to capture correlation across time.
And we saw that one of the things that
was a property the random walk model,
the generalized random walk model,
was that the increments were independent, they were IID.
And simply, multiplying by constant
and adding a constant to our zs didn't change that.
So in the generalized random walk model,
we can have a non-zero mean, we can have a non-zero volatility
or randomness.
But the increments are still independent of each other
over time.
For many things, so we do want to have dependence over time.
We'd like to have causal influences,
we want to be able to propagate information across time.
So we need more complex models.
The great thing is, that we can build them out of the pieces
we've already seen.
Our main friend here is going to be linearity.
And let me just give you a couple of examples.
One of them is the so-called MA 1 model, where
MA stands for moving average.
And the idea here is that the return in a given period
or a realization of a variable--
let's be general.
Let's say that r is something that looks like the random walk
model, mu plus sigma z t, plus I'm
going to add a new term on the right hand side.
And the new term on the right hand side
is going to be a constant phi, just
some other constant parameter, some scalar
times a previous value of z sub t minus 1.
So notice that by the time we get to time t
and we're waiting to see what new realization,
we're going to have this random variable z sub t.
This variable will have already been observed,
it will be in and constant.
And that means that over different periods of time,
the rs are not being drawn from the same distribution.
So the model is not IID.
We can get into more complex examples
as well by letting other features vary with time, not
just the constant offset to a random variable,
but the size of the randomness itself.
And this is an attribute of the so-called GARCH models.
And in a GARCH model, it's really a two component model
with two random variables.
It looks deceptively simple, so let
me show you because you'll get the intuition right away.
The idea is that in the model, that the return is
a random walk form mu plus sigma times z sub t.
The difference is, that the coefficient sigma now itself
has the time dependence.
We then need an equation to specify
how sigma evolves with t and that's
what defines the GARCH model, and there
are different possible dynamical models.
But you could think of this as saying,
that within each period say each day or each month,
there's a generalized random walk process.
But the parameters of that random walk change from one day
to the next.
The sigma's change.
Another way to model causal influences,
is to have other terms on the right hand side
not just previous values of z, but we
could have previous values of the variable of interest
itself.
So we could generalize, and have this model of this form.
This is called an autoregressive model,
and it's of order P, which simply
means that the coefficients c 0, c 1,
c 2 up through c P that at least c P
is non-zero, that these has this non-trivial structure.
But the idea is terms on the right hand
side are now lagged versions, they're
referring to previous values not of the zs,
but of the variable in question.
In this case, R sub t.
And the right hand side I have, 1 period before all the way
through t periods before.
Again, those are telling us that the present value
is going to depend on what happened in the past.
So there will be a causal relationship.
Plus it's not deterministic, it is random.
Plus in each time period, we're getting a new kick--
a new kick from z, which is going
to z is going to be a standardized random variable,
identical and independently distributed with mean 0,
variance 1.
But we have a scale factor sigma,
that lets us generate the size of the kick.
And although z has no mean, the c 0 and potentially other
terms do.
So this is a generalization and it
will have some causal structure, and we'll take a look at this.
We can go further and combine both of the two
that we had before.
And this is known as an ARMA model
for AR autoregressive moving average of order P, Q, where
we've got a bunch of terms.
All I've done is I've combined these two
forms, on the top line I've got c 0 through c P,
adding lagged values of the past variable R,
plus I've got Q terms with past values of the variable z.
These models have in common that they have a linear structure.
So what we're doing is we're just adding a bunch of stuff
to the right hand side.
That means we can apply linearity.
The terms have are all of the form
a constant, times a random variable.
And whether that variable depending
on when we take the expectation, whether it's
conditional or unconditional expectation,
we'll either treat those as being unknown or being known.
But the causal, the time ordering structure
is clear, the things on the right hand
side all refer to times before time t that's on the left hand
side with one exception.
There's one term the sigma z t term it's new,
it's sometimes known as a shock or an innovation that
occurs in each period.
So we have that basic linear structure,
we have the past values on the right hand
side that are going to determine subsequent outcomes.
They're going to be part of the evolution
of future random variables.
And the coefficients need to be specified or determined,
and we'll see that they often have natural interpretations.
How do we solve such a model?
Well, we take a look using our old friend linearity.
We use the recursive structure of the definitions, that
is that each period in time t refers to previous periods
from the past.
And we use one new property that's called stationarity.
Stationary means time and variance.
It doesn't mean that the process is static.
What it means is, that the probability distributions
don't change over time.
So think of going into a Casino, you
would like the games to be stationary,
the probability on the dice, it should
be the same every day on every roll that it was before.
The probability on the roulette wheel,
should be the same on every turn that it was before.
The probability on the decks of cards
in a poker game or a blackjack game,
should be the same as they were before.
All right.
Blackjack, we would have to assume
that we're reshuffling after each turn for that to be true,
for that to be stationary.
Otherwise it would be a non stationary process.
So stationarity means, that the probability distribution
is the same.
It does not mean that the outcomes are the same.
Now where stationarity is a strong condition,
and we don't need anything that strong necessarily.
We're going to use a weaker condition that is appropriately
named weak stationarity, and we're
going to say that a process is weakly stationary, if just
the first and second moments are stationary, that is there
time translation invariant.
And that's good because we're going to play our usual game,
instead of finding out the entire distribution
of our process.
The whole probability distribution,
we're going to ask about its mean and its variance,
we're not going to know what the fourth, eighth, tenth,
and in moments are to all orders.
So to see this, let's take one case and do it in detail.
And the case, we're going to do in detail, is the case of AR 1.
The AR 1 structure looks like this.
It's got one term has just two coefficients.
There's a constant, plus c 0 plus another proportionality
constant c 1, times the previous values observation, plus well
our old friend sigma.
So a third constant actually, times a random shock
that occurs in each period.