PROFESSOR: We solve the AR 1 model
by applying the expectation operator
to both sides of the equation.
So doing that, we use linearity.
We take expectations term by term,
and we see that the expectation of R sub t
is c times the expectation of 1, which
is just 1 plus c 1 times the expectation of R t minus 1,
which we don't know.
Plus 0, 0 trend expectation of the standard variable z t.
So what we're left with, this interesting expression.
We have the expectation of R t as a constant
plus another constant times expectation of R t minus 1.
Now here's where we used stationarity.
It says, that the two expectations
on the left and the right, are the same as each other.
We don't know what they are, but we
do know that they're the same.
So we can solve algebraically for them
by rewriting on the right hand side.
c 0 plus c 1 expectation of R sub t, and solving for R sub t.
So we substitute, and what do we find?
We find that we now have an expression
for the mean, the expected value of R sub t in terms
of the basic parameters of the model.
c 0 over 1 minus c 1, and sigma doesn't appear.
So we've solved for the first moment of R t
by using stationarity, and this is
a trick we'll continue to use.
We take things, we plug in our basic equation for the Rs,
we expand out the things inside the expectation.
And then as needed, we apply stationarity.
Now for convenience, instead of this handful of symbols,
it's the mean value of R t.
So let's give it a new name, let's call it mu.
And for interpretations for physical and financial
interpretations later on, I'm going
to take the innocuous and boring sounding c 1.
And I'm going to give it a new name,
I'm going to call it minus lambda.
So in terms of these variables, we can rewrite our AR 1 model.
And you can check this, by checking the variables.
In terms of an expression on the left and the right hand side,
that both are written in terms of this combination R minus mu.
And on the left hand side, it's a time t and the right hand
side it's R t minus 1.
So we have the usual typical recursive structure
that we've been seeing.
Plus the shock term, the sigma z t.
So how do we want to interpret this,
this is a model that's often used
for modeling mean reversion.
We think of mu as being the mean of our process and R
t minus mu or t minus 1--
R sub t minus 1 minus mu, are the variables difference
from the mean value from mu.
So if R at each time were exactly equal to mu or minus mu
would be 0.
However, and it would stay 0 for the recursion, if for example,
if sigma were equal to 0.
But because there's randomness, there will be changes.
So the real driving variable here, the real thing
to keep an eye on, is R minus mu,
that's what's moving things.
So what does it say?
What about the minus lambda?
And why have they written it this way?
Well, let's think of lambda as being a positive constant,
we'll see in a few moments the only requirement is
that the absolute value of lambda be less than 1.
So lambda can be negative, but the usual applications
it's positive with the sign convention, where I've written
minus lambda on the right hand side.
So here's how we can think about it.
We can say that for a positive value of the coefficient mu,
the first term on the right hand side says,
that if R in the previous period exceeded its mean,
if it was larger, then we multiply times the negative
constant --
minus lambda.
And that pushes it in a negative direction.
What is it pushing in the negative direction?
Well, the thing on the left hand side,
which is the subsequent periods change in the value
relative to its mean.
So this says, that if we overshoot
the mean in one period, will we push down
toward it in the other.
If we undershoot, if R period t minus 1 was less than mu,
then multiplying the term in parentheses times
c minus lambda, will give a positive number,
and that will tend to increase the value towards its mean.
And in each period we get a random shock,
we get a new sigma z t, but that's symmetrically
distributed.
It's just as likely to be positive or negative.
Now that we have that structure, we
can solve the rest of the model 2 for the remaining moments.
That means that we can solve for the variance,
and it's square root, the standard deviation.
And we can solve for covariances.
And in this case, in the times series context,
these are called autocovariance.
Auto, because we're computing and R with an R,
just the two different periods in time.
Instead of computing the covariance
of two independent random variable to random variables,
maybe not necessarily independent x and y,
where we compute covariance of x and covariance
with-- the variance in x and y, is taking the expectation
of the product of each random variable
relative to its own mean.
We do the same thing here but, where the two variables
are taken at two different points in time
within the same time series.
OK so how does that work?
Well, we'll start with the variance,
and we'll give it a name.
We'll call it gamma 0, and you'll see why in a moment.
So the variance of R is defined as usual
as the expectation of the square of R t minus mu,
where R t is taken relative to its means,
so we take the expectation of the square.
Now for R t minus mu, we're going
to substitute in our equation of motion.
We're going to substitute in, the expression
for R t minus mu, in terms of the previous values
on the right hand side.
And will expand it out, take expectations term by term
and what do we get?
Well, one of the terms we get, we recognize this first term
here, is lambda squared or properly minus lambda quantity
squared, times the expectation of R t minus 1
minus mu quantity squared.
And this expression taken as a whole from stationarity,
is also gamma 0.
It's the thing that's on the left hand side.
The term over here from the z squared,
gives us a sigma squared down here,
this should be a sigma squared up here.
Apologies for the typo.
And the cross term vanishes.
So at the end, we have the gamma 0 can be written,
because we solve this equation algebraically for gamma 0,
and there's a gamma 0 on the right.
And we get the gamma 0, the variance of R,
is sigma squared over 1 minus lambda squared.
So what we see is first of all, that it's
proportional to sigma squared, which we would expect.
This is the variance of the process.
The bigger sigma is, the bigger gamma 0 is.
We also see the special case, the random walk.
If we set lambda equals 0, we should
get our usual generalized random walk result, and we do,
we get the gamma 0, the variance of R, is sigma squared.
But now look at the denominator.
We notice the denominator blows up
if lambda gets to be larger than 1 or less than minus 1.
So this will only be defined for values less than that.
How do we know it doesn't make sense
for values larger than that?
Well, there's an easy interpretation.
Remember that lambda is telling us
how much of the previous periods result
is going to contribute to the next periods result.
And when that's less than 1, it means
that affects that shocks tend to die off
over time in the absence of the new shocks that
are arriving via the new z ts in that's reasonable.
However, a case for lambda greater than 1 into the shocks
get amplified, they get bigger and bigger.
So that once a shock enters the system, it runs away
and it takes over the system.
So the result would not be convergent.
So even though it's a formal recursion,
the recursion doesn't actually exist.
So the most typical case as I said,
is going to be lambda positive.
But in any event, we're going to have lambda less than 1
in magnitude.
Now we don't need to stop there.
We can now extend our result to look
at what happens, when we consider R is
taken at two different times.
And we'll use the notation gamma sub
K to denote the autocovariance.
That is the covariance of R t with an R t at lagged
by K times steps.
Remember that because it's stationary,
that means that this doesn't depend on t
it only depends on K.
So the correlation between R 1 and R 3,
is the same as the correlation between R 21 and R 23,
it doesn't matter.
All that matters, is how far apart they are in time.
So we can think of K as being a delay, or a distance,
or a length of time, over which information propagates.
How do we solve?
Well, we use our same friend, plugging in and applying
linearity and stationary, the difference this time is.
That instead of substituting the equation of motion everywhere,
we do it in one of the two terms.
So it goes like this gamma K is defined
to be the expectation of R t minus mu and R t
minus k minus mu.
We'll leave the first--
works for me.
We'll leave the second factor alone,
and the first one will apply our equation of motion
for recursion.
So we'll plug in just for this.
So we have the lambda term minus lambda,
times R t minus 1 minus mu.
And then there will be another term with z,
which vanishes, because as we saw in the cross terms vanish.
And here by stationarity, this is
just dependent on the difference in times between these two Rs.
And that's K minus 1 steps apart.
But that's just our with minus lambda
at times, our expression for the autocovariance gamma sub
k minus 1, where there was one time step in part.
So we've got is recursion by substituting
in the equations of motion, we can relate gamma K
to gamma K minus 1.
And the rule is, for every K that you increase, you multiply
times a factor of minus gamma.
So we would expect to see a function of minus gamma raised
to the case power, which we do down here in our final result.
And we're able to tie off this series,
because if we think about doing the recursion backwards.
When we get to gamma 0, we can stop.
We know what gamma 0 is in closed form.
So our final result for any K, any finite K
is that, gamma K is minus lambda to the K-th power
times the variance.
And explicitly, that's minus lambda to the K-th power,
1 minus lambda squared times sigma squared.
So this is the lag-K autocovariance,
and if we think of this now not as a function of lambda,
but is a function of K, we see that-- remember lambda
is less than 1 in magnitude, this tells us
that the influence is dying off as K gets larger and larger.
OK, but it does persist over time.
Therefore, this model allows for there
to be a causal connection between observations
and one period, and observations in all prior periods.
And we have a very specific way, that they're related
that the information dies out.
So let's summarize what we've done
in looking at our structure of time series models.
We've seen that we can construct time series models by building
a bunch of linear terms, that generalize the pieces we
saw from the random walk.
The pieces that show up in our recursive definitions
on the right hand side.
Include shocks, that is sigma z t terms,
we're adding new and new random information
at each point in time.
They can include past observations of the zs, that
is previous period zs.
And they can include past observations
of the variables themselves, and everything can have
an independent coefficient.
So those are the basic ingredients
of this class of models.
As long as they are linear in terms of the random variables,
we have a good chance of solving them using the techniques
that we worked out in detail for AR 1.
These models have temporal correlations that's
built into their structure.
So they're written recursively, which
makes a compact definition, it means
that we can solve them and think about them one period ahead.
But it also means that when we make assumptions
about stationarity of the series,
that we have good tools for solving them.
And understanding how to interpret
that as the propagation of information
forward in time and the decay of the influence of shocks
over time as well.
The example we looked at in detail
was AR 1, which we used for mean reversion.
And this model, this structure shows up
in many areas of finance econometrics
and in other areas of applied mathematics.
The model is for where we have randomness that
enters through this noise term.
But where there's an influence--
where the influence of new information
tends to die out over time.
So the way in which we model this and describe
it is in terms of the relative displacement from a long term
mean average.
And the minus lambda says, that when
we see shocks in one period, they
tend to get damped out, in the following period,
in the absence of a correction.
OK, so we apply weak stationarity,
that gives us the first and second moment.
It doesn't tell us everything about the full distribution.
Fortunately, for us, that's what we're usually interested in.
One last detail to keep in mind is that the lag variables--
will sometimes think about in two different ways,
and mathematically we'll treat it in two different ways.
One of them is as in the equations we wrote down,
we think about them as the different periods is all
being unobserved, they're all random variables
that have not yet been drawn from their distribution.
There are no observations that have yet been made.
And those expectations that we took
are called unconditional expectations.
But we'll see that sometimes when we actually
want to look at data, or if we want
to use Monte Carlo techniques to generate simulated data.
Well, think about these a little bit differently,
we'll ask, what's the expectation for the future
given that we're currently at a particular time t,
and that everything at earlier times has already transpired,
has already arrived.
And in that case, we take the values of the earlier
realized numbers to be constants.
And the things that are unrealized
are things that are in our future.