PROFESSOR: Monte Carlo simulation
means we use computers instead of our pen and paper,
to work out consequences of probability models
and stochastic processes.
What we do is, we simulate stochastic processes
by drawing random numbers using the random number
generator on a computer.
And this can be found in most programming languages.
This provides us with really an idealized test
lab for exploring some of the ideas
we've talked about and for much more advanced
financial applications.
The reason is, that because we're
doing the simulation ourselves, because we're
deploying the random number generator that we're
parameterized, that we're coding,
we know where the data comes from.
In the real world we don't know the true data generating
process, that's part of the subtlety and art in model
building as we try to infer that, that's
what we're trying to solve.
In the Monte Carlo lab, we assume that that's known,
and we'll see it still gives us our hands
full of a lot of things that we need to check out.
But if we can't understand and do the analysis with data
that we've generated ourselves, we
have no hope for doing it in the real world.
On the other hand, doing things thoroughly in a test lab,
gives us great idea about the abilities and limits of some
of our analytical tools.
So we'll find out how much accuracy and precision,
we can have in different kinds of simulation settings.
So the idea is, that we're going to assume a particular model,
we're going to assume that we know the way the world works,
and we're going to generate data that is consistent with that.
So those properties will all be true self-consistently
because we built the model that way.
We can then for some purposes, forget
that we knew where the data came from
and analyze it as if it were real world data.
But typically, one of the applications that we'll do,
is we'll generate a large number of possible outcomes.
So think of doing a simulation for the evolution of a stock
price, or an entire stock market, or some other asset
price.
In the real world we only get to see history once,
and when we look at actual historical data,
we only have one history.
We can't redo the experiment.
We might be able to get more data,
by looking at different time periods
or going further back in time.
But that's not the same thing, as repeating everything
under the same conditions.
So here will be limited only by our computers
abilities and the time we're willing to commit to it.
But the usual process, involves taking a large number
say, 10,000 or a million different simulations.
And constructing what we'll call an ensemble
a set of possible hypothetical paths that might have
happened, each of which typically being equally likely.
And then, instead of what we've done so far,
where we've computed properties of a distribution.
Like moments in the distribution, mean,
and variance by doing mathematical expectations
against a known probability density,
here we're going to do statistical calculations
against the empirical data set that's been generated
through our Monte Carlo data.
And what we'll see is, that the results typically
become more precise as we look at more and more data, which
is only limited again by our computational resources.
So I'll show you some examples, and I'll you
should run them yourselves.
So I'm providing some code here, and you
can take a look at in the R programming language.
And you can play around with all the parameters.
And you can take a look at what happens
as we increase the number of simulations,
or as we change some of the parameters.
So it's a great chance to try some things out
in a different setting apart from the pencil and paper
things that we've done before.
To build applications that we have
are going to include asset price dynamics
that we'll look at now.
Option pricing, which we'll look at a little bit later on.
And many applications in portfolio and risk management.