PROFESSOR: So most computer languages, including R,
have functions that generate random numbers.
Now in R, the main ones to take a look at,
are the function sample, which returns discrete values.
So if you want to pick from a list,
0 and 1 could happen with probability p and 1 minus p
or values 1 minus 1, values 1, 2, 3, 4, 5--
if they're discrete, we can use the sample function.
And we can sample with or without replacement.
For Monte Carlo applications, we typically
sample with replacement.
We're not exhausting lists.
We're generating things consistently over time.
Two other functions-- the runif--
that's not run if, which looks like it
could be a reasonable command--
returns random numbers with a uniform probability
distribution.
So these are real numbers bounded between 0 and 1.
And rnorm generate things drawn from
a normal or Gaussian distribution, with mean 0
and variance 1.
There are a bunch of parameters that you can use to tune this,
such as setting the mean and variance
of the normal distribution to something else.
Now we have to keep in mind that the random number generated
by a computer are not truly random.
These are approximations.
And there are a lot of limitations.
So you need to keep in mind what the real world limitations are
in our hypothetical world of Monte Carlo simulations,
namely what are the limitations of computers.
So a few things to keep in mind include--
we can't do real numbers on a computer.
We can only do finite precision.
Now double precision, 15 decimal digits, is pretty good.
But it's not infinitely divisible.
So some of the things that means are
that if we're looking say, at a uniform distribution,
we can't get every possible number.
And in a true uniform distribution,
the probability of getting any particular number
is measure zero, and that won't be the case.
We'll have some finite probability.
When we think about not only the find greatness
for real numbers, we also should think about their boundedness.
So a Gaussian random variable could go from minus infinity
to infinity.
We knew that it's very unlikely that it
goes outside of say, plus or minus 3 or plus or 6,
but we could get a value that could be arbitrarily large.
And computers don't do arbitrarily large.
They have very large numbers.
So we need to keep in mind that anything that we generate
is going to be truncated and finite.
And that's particularly important in risk applications,
where we're studying the occurrence of rare events.
Because there may be events that the computer's actually not
generating that are very, very unlikely.
So we need to keep that in mind.
That's part of the limitations which will qualify our results.
And we can take account for our approximations.
So there are many subtleties here,
which we won't be going into.
But I do want to mention them so you
can do further reading if you want to apply this
to more advanced applications.
So here are some basic functions that I commonly use in R,
and that you might find helpful as well for getting started,
for generating some random numbers.
And we'll take a look at some examples.
In just a moment.
The first example that we have here
involves taking a look at generating a matrix
of independent random numbers.
So let's think of z as being our typical standardized random
variable, or actually in this case, not standardized.
This is going to be a uniform distribution.
It will be standardized in a moment.
But z is some random variable, drawn from some distribution.
In this case, a uniform distribution--
so it's uniformly distributed on 0 and 1.
Now what I'd like to do is I'd like
to pick Nt, the number of time steps,
and I'd like to think of orienting
this as a matrix, where I typically think of time series
on a computer as column vectors.
So I think of aligning the successive elements from top
to bottom, from oldest to newest--
1 2, 3, 4, 5, all the way up to Nt.
And for efficiency, we're going to run many simulations
in parallel.
And I'll think of Np as a number of sample paths
that we're going to generate.
So as far as the computer is concerned,
Nt times Np, they're all independent random numbers
anyways.
It hardly matters.
How I choose to arrange them for convenience is it a matrix.
And these are the conventions I'll
use always for time series.
So time goes down.
Each column represents an independent time series.
And in this case, the columns represent
different possible realizations of our price paths.
So the first line gives us a matrix
of Nt times Np independent, pseudo-random draws
from our distribution.
The next example right here, shows a way
that we can turn things into discrete random variables
if we have a uniform distribution.
And of course, the sample function I mentioned earlier--
there's an easier way to do it.
But there are simple sometimes to code things using
continuous distributions, and take the discrete case
as a special case, rather than writing different functions.
It doesn't make any difference.
You can do whatever you prefer.
But in this case, what I've done is
I've shifted it so that with probability p,
I get a positive number.
With probability 1 minus p, I get a negative number.
And then I take the sign of that.
Notice that there is a small problem, potentially here,
with 0, which shouldn't be allowed.
And the sample function won't run into that trouble.
But rather than making the function complex
with lots of parameters, it's easier
to do simple linear transformations
on the variables to move them into a range we want.
So typically, we want to shift the endpoints
and re-scale things.
For example, instead of plus or minus 1, I might want 0 and 1.
And these are related so that the x on the line
above gives me new variable i, that just shifts the values.
So when x is 1, u is 1.
When x is minus 1, u is equal to 0.
The next line right here, gives us--
this looks a little bit more complicated.
But this is an example of one way,
among many, that you can generate data, which
is normally distributed with a given mean, mu, and a given
standard deviation, sigma, and again, arranged in matrix form.
And then finally, this is our specific--
but it isn't required.
We can do this iteratively, but it's very convenient--
is way of applying a cumulative summation
function to aggregate our returns.
And this is typically what we look
at when we're doing asset price dynamics and price simulation,
we're going to add up successive returns.
So we'll have r1, r1 plus r2, r1 plus r2 plus r3, and so on.
So this is r-specific.
And this will generate-- typically,
what we have if r is our matrix of returns,
this will do a cumulative sum in the time direction.
That's what the second argument here is, 2.
And this applies it across the entire matrix.
And then we exponentiate, as we'll see--
if we're simulating log returns, we'll
typically want to exponentiate the cumulative sums and returns
to get the actual asset price paths.
So let's look at some examples.
In this case, this is code that generates
a simple 20-step random walk with equal probability
for going up and down.
So notice-- I define up top what the probabilities are.
And it's conventional sometimes, to call with a probability, p.
And the probability of the opposite outcome, q.
1 minus p-- it's not required.
You can code it any way you'd like.
And the number of times steps is 20.
For simplicity, I'm picking only one sample path in this case.
Here's my assignment to z of a set of random numbers
that are drawn.
Here, I'm mapping them to the range I want.
I initialize a set of partial sums, s, to be 0.
And it's important to keep in mind that we usually
want to start at time 0, with a fixed value.
So in order to have N sub t steps and returns,
we need Nt plus 1 placeholders for the actual values
of our state variable.
So if we want to have, let's say, 252 daily returns
for a stock price, which is typical
for an annual simulation, then we
need 253 values for the price.
Because the first one will be p0 will be initial price.
And then we'll have the next one.
So it's always one less return than the number of prices
that we have.
So, now that we have it initialized,
let's just run a simple for loop.
And at each step, we'll say that the value at step k plus 1,
at the next step, is wherever we were
in the previous step plus the random value that we had.
Where I've written this with the argument having comma
and then a blank in R, is the syntax meaning
do it for this row and for all of the columns.
In this particular case, we have N sub p is 1.
There's only one column there.
But in general, this is going to be the format that we'll use.
And then we can take a look.
And behind me, is an example of what a 20-step random walk
looks like.
When you run it-- each time we rerun it,
we'll get some different value.
,
Now, let's take a look at how we might do this
if we want to get a little bit closer to finance.
One of the things we'll do is let's
pick a particular number of time steps.
I like 252.
252 is the standard convention for modeling daily returns.
The idea is that we have approximately 21 trading days,
excluding weekends and holidays on average in a month.
12 months-- that gives us 252 trading days.
And we're going to treat weekends as being nonexistent.
So we'll assume that everything is homogeneous from Friday
to Monday, and that we keep going.
The number of simulations I'm going to run
is going to be 10,000 simulations, which
is a good starting point.
It's kind of a handy number, a good balance between being
tractable and being accurate.
Just as a rough rule of thumb--
the accuracy of our results typically
is going to scale with 1 over the square root of the number
of simulations that we do.
So 10,000 means that we can get things that might be roughly 1%
accurate to a range of 1%.
A million would be better.
A billion might be even better.
But that would take a very long time to run on most computers.
So I like to start at around 10,000,
And then work from there as far as needed.
So now I've got a bunch of random numbers.
I'm going to treat these again, as discrete values,
plus or minus 1.
So this is a random, discrete random walk,
where we're going by discrete steps up or down.
And then I'm going to run this, but now, over many paths,
over time.
And I have each location is the previous one.
And what does that look like?
Well, now I can get my ensemble of paths.
I have 10,000 of them.
That would make for a pretty cluttered diagram.
So I've drawn three of them here.
And you can see that if these were stock prices,
you might feel very differently about them but.
These are all three paths drawn from the same distribution.
OK, in this case, the distribution
is equally likely to go up or down.
So the fact that one of the paths went up, one of them
ended up at 0, and one of them ended up very negative,
is just quite literally the luck of the draw.