PROFESSOR: Now, how do we apply this
to real world modeling for asset price dynamics?
So, a typical model and kind of the most common model
in finance and in applications like option pricing,
is to start with the idea that returns are lognormally
distributed.
That is the logarithmic returns are normally distributed.
And of course, whether or not this is a good model,
is an empirical question.
We need to look at actual data.
But let's start here for a simulation process,
and see what some of the paths look like
and see what some of the consequences are.
So we draw our returns from a lognormal distribution.
And of course, this is the same thing as our random walk model
that we've seen before, except so I have returns drawn
from a normal distribution with mean mu and variance
sigma squared.
And that's the same as writing rt equals mu plus sigma
zt, where z is drawn from a standardized normal
distribution.
Now these are logarithmic returns.
And the returns are defined in terms of the logarithm
of the price ratio of a day.
And this is approximately equal to the simple return
for small values.
And we can invert this.
So if we look at the recursion, we
see that the price today is yesterday's price
times the next return.
And if we keep iterating backward farther and farther
in time, we get this result, which
we'll use as the basis for our Monte Carlo,
namely that the price at time t, is
equal to an initial price, P0 times the exponential
of the sum of returns.
And these individual r's are drawn in each period.
We take their sum.
We exponentiate, and that will give us the price.
So here are the steps that we use for generating Monte Carlo
simulations.
We first decide what the parameters
are for the underlying distribution-- like what
are mu and sigma?
Where should they come from?
What units are they in?
We need to scale them appropriately for the sampling
interval.
So typically, for example, we take mu and sigma
to be our given annualized units.
For example, a stock might have a 10% annual return,
with the volatility of 30%.
But if our individual time steps are on a one day level,
then we need to change the parameters in order
that they make sense for the one day period.
Then we draw numbers from our distribution.
We use the scaled parameters to simulate our distribution
and how it evolves over time.
We construct the ensemble of paths.
And then once we've got this at say, 10,000 possible paths,
we're going to compute analytics based on it.
So if we want to know what the variance of the terminal
returns is, we just compute it by taking
the statistical calculation of the variance on the values
that we've generated on our actual sample data.
So here's an example of how we could do that.
So let's take the parameters I just mentioned.
The sigma of 0.3 has annualized volatility
of 30%, an annualized return of 10%.
Now how should we scale these?
Well remember, we want the annualized return to be 10%.
So that means since we know that if we do a whole bunch of time
steps, we know that the mean scales linearly with time.
That means that the return on each day
should be mu, 10%, divided by 252,
which we can write as mu dt.
This Is our constant term.
So we've re-scale the constant in our r equals
mu plus sigma z, to be mu delta t.
That's going to be 10% over 252.
So over a year, we'll get the right number.
And then for the coefficient of z,
we need to scale by square root of t.
So in the Monte Carlo simulation,
we're going to take our normalized z--
this is just drawn from a standard normalized
distribution.
And we multiply it times sigma times the square root of 1/252,
which is about 15.87.
The square root of 252 ends up showing up a lot in Monte Carlo
simulations and in conversions.
So it's good to get that number in mind.
So I've written down two different ways that we could do
this in R. One of them is simply,
we start with normalized z's.
And then we scale them.
We add a constant, mu dt, plus our normalized variable z,
times sigma square root of dt.
Or you can use the parameters in R.
But this ends up again, being more language-specific,
because there are optional arguments
for the normal distribution, where
the first argument is the number of random numbers you want.
The next one is what's the mean.
The default is 0.
The next one is what's the standard deviation, sd.
And again, the default is 1.
So either of these lines will produce the same numbers.
Then we take the same thing we did before.
S is an initialized matrix to hold
our partial sums, our partial cumulative sums of results.
We work through iteratively step by step--
t from 1 up through Nt.
And then we take our result and we exponentiate
it to get our price paths.
And again, I've shown you a couple of sample paths here.
And if I told you that these were three stocks, what
do you think?
You might think gosh, that one in red--
that looks like one that went for a really wild ride.
Maybe it showed up on Reddit somewhere.
And it rose, and it crashed and burned.
And the green one is some company that's struggling.
But in fact, all of these came from exactly
the same data-generating process.
Now, let's take a look at some of the results
that we have from our distribution.
One of the things we can do-- remember
that P holds our price paths.
And the terminal values of the price paths,
we started with an initial value of 1. ,
Remember the initial return was 0.
So we exponentiated the initial value, P0 was equal to 1.
We could have multiplied it time some other constant.
So the terminal value minus 1--
the terminal value here minus 1 is the simple return
on the stock over a one-year period.
And we can see right here, the histogram in blue of the data.
This is showing the distribution of one-year returns
under our model.
So we notice that this distribution is not normal.
The red line is showing a normal distribution.
But we can see that there's a positive mean.
And there we go.
So we have the center of this is positive.
There's a certain width to it.
But it's not symmetric.
You notice that the distribution is definitely skewed,
with a large right tail.
And of course, the lowest value can't be below minus 1
for what we've done.
Because the price can't go below 0.
So what I've done and the red line, is I've
compared this to a normal distribution
that has the same empirical observed
mean and standard deviation.
So we can obviously see by looking at it,
that this is not normal.
Now remember, these are the simple returns.
And they're not expected to be normally distributed.
If I take the logarithm of the returns and compute,
then things would match up rather nicely.
But again, we could ask how nicely should they match up.
What level of variance would I expect?
If I had done less than 10,000 simulations,
this would be a more ragged plot.
If I were to do a million simulations,
we would find it would fit quite nicely under the curve.
So depending on our application and our patience,
that will dictate the number of simulations that we might do.
Now in this particular case, we do have closed form numbers.
So we can compare, we can compute
what the mean and standard deviation or the variance
are with the results that you would
get if you did a whole bunch of Gaussian intervals.
I don't know about you, but sometimes Gaussian integrals
can be tedious.
Certainly, look at the answers in a book.
But if you want to do the Gaussian integrals,
you can do that.
Monte Carlo simulation can be very quick.
And we can add numbers.
So let's see how they compare.
And this is helpful for cases where we'll often
apply Monte Carlos, where the closed form
solutions are either too difficult
or they don't even exist.
So for example, I compute the mean empirically
of the R's as 1.547869.
And the theoretical result, which
is written down below by doing the actual expectation
and doing a Gaussian integral, the expectation in fact
is e to the mu plus sigma squared over 2 minus 1.
That's because the little r's are logarithmic,
and the big R's are not.
This is approximately-- we can expand this out
in a Taylor series.
But this is the exact result. And we
can see that we're pretty good two and almost three decimal
places--
0.156.
And if you run it, you'll get of course, a different number
for the first one.
And you can try this here.
How about the variance?
Well again, there's a particular result for the exact value.
And the numbers that we get here for the standard deviation,
I've taken the square root of the result for the variance.
And again, these look pretty close.
So that's the idea.
We have two different ways of computing the same thing.
One of them is doing a bunch of Gaussian integrals
in closed form.
The other one is we do a whole bunch of simulations
on the computer, and then take.
Some averages and standard deviations.
You notice that compared to the doing
a Gaussian integrals, which is fun
if you like doing integrals.
But here, we have a little bit more
when we do some visualizations, a little bit more idea as
to what's going on.
Like here's the spread.
These are all the things that could have happened.
Sometimes the individual price paths can look really striking,
and we can learn some things by looking at our data.
We can keep going.
This is the empirical cumulative density function,
which can be done in R. It depends
on how we do it as a plot of the cumulative distribution
function, which is equivalent to integrating up
the integral from the left.
And another quick and dirty way of looking
at the data, sort of a transpose the previous one,
is to plot the sorted returns.
So I've done that here this command
will work in R, that we can use do a bar
plot or any plotting package you want in R or another language,
where I sort the returns in order--
remember that the Monte Carlo, the 10,000 paths
we're not ordered in a particular way.
Let me sort them in the outcomes from lowest to highest.
And this is a different way of visualizing the distribution.
This is actually an interesting way
of looking at actual financial returns.
So we see that we go from smallest to largest.
And we get a characteristic kind of S-shaped curve.
And we can see there are big outliers on the upper end
of the distribution.
We can also take a look at things
to compare to a normal distribution.
A Q-Q plot-- in this case, Q-Q norm is a special case in R.
But a Q-Q plot typically lets us visualize a comparison of two
probability distributions.
And the idea is that if in this case, where
we're comparing with the normal distribution,
if the data were normal, it would lie on a straight line.
Q-Q plots are especially helpful if we're
looking at deviations in the tails of the distribution.
A histogram is not so great for looking
at outliers in the tails, because the tails are small.
Rare events are rare.
And visually, they're going to show up as maybe 0 or 1
pixels on our screen.
A Q-Q plot emphasizes the tails and it
keeps the boring stuff in the middle, which
is most of the data, of course.
But typically, the middle of any Q-Q plot
is going to look like a straight line somewhere.
And then the deviations in the tails
tell us something characteristic about how we depart
from normality, potentially.