PROFESSOR: Now, we can also extend our process
to things that are our approach, to things
that are not just random walks.
In fact, the random walk is a bit
of the special case for a bunch of reasons.
One of them is that, because the returns are all independent,
I didn't need to do the for loop.
I could have used some matrix algebra to do everything in one
fell swoop.
And you might have noticed, that because I'm adding together,
in my last case, a sum of random variables,
the sum of random variables of normal random variables
is a normal random variable.
That's very special for Gaussian distributions,
and I didn't need to iterate things at all.
So, just to show you why the method matters more
than the particular example, let's
take a look at an AR(1) process which is defined recursively,
but where the value in each step now does
depend on the prior history.
So it's essential that we construct the simulation
by running forward in time.
So, here are some parameters that we can have.
We can keep our Mu value, again, annualized at 10%.
We'll let the lambda value, which is a pure number,
be the strength of the mean reversion
and I'll set that initially at 40%, to of 0.4.
And this, again, is something I'd encourage
you to try out in the data.
So now, when I run things, I replace my generating function
by the iteration for the AR(1) process.
So here's my lambda and, again, you
can check the special case where lambda equals zero,
it should recover a random walk, and I can generate--
So if I think of these, this is convention, it's Monte Carlo.
We could do it we want, but if I think these
as being simple returns, just how this model is often
applied, I can turn them into logarithmic returns
and then look at some sample paths in their distribution.
So the first thing you'll see on the left and on the right.
On the left, we'll see a bunch of sample paths
that don't necessarily look different from what
we saw before.
It's kind of hard to tell by eye whether we're
looking at something that has mean reversion in the presence
of the significant amount of randomness.
So, looking at it by eye isn't really going to help us.
When we look at the histogram of the data,
we see again a little bit of a departure from normality.
But where things really get revealed
is by looking at serial correlation and coefficient.
So we ask about the correlation between the returns in one
period and the returns in the next period.
And here are two different examples
where, in the case of a random walk,
this left hand graph, we have the, first,
is the correlation of the series with itself, which
by definition is equal to one.
Each of these other terms, which is labeled by a lag variable,
is the correlation of our simulated results
with the same series offset by one-time step 2, 3, 4, or 5.
And one of the interesting things
that we see here is the time one lag
for our auto-regressive process, and that's
exactly what we built in, was the return on one day.
It starts with minus 40% of the previous day's
return plus some randomness, and that's what we see here.
On the right, I've fiddled with the parameters
and you can try this too.
And we can crank up the lambda and we can crank down the sigma
to turn off the randomness and see what the interplay is
between the two.
The Mu is actually not that interesting.
It drops out of all the correlations.
But what we're often facing is, how big
is the randomness in a financial price process compared
to other drivers in the marketplace, other factors,
other correlations, or something like a restoring force
like mean reversion.
So let's summarize what we've talked about
in looking at Monte Carlo methods.
Monte Carlo uses computer random number generators
to simulate data for a given model,
and we can apply this to a wide variety of models
and compare across models.
The simulations give us an idealized testing environment
because we know what the data generating process is
and this is our best case.
Usually, we don't know what it is.
So, this way, we can at least look at the best case
and make sure that we could correctly identify our data.
For example, you could imagine starting.
If we wanted to do model identification,
we could generate some data and then pretend
that someone had just handed us the data without knowing
what model it came from.
Could we correctly identify what the model is?
We also have the advantage that we
can run lots of different simulations,
and real financial market data doesn't allow that.
We don't get to rerun the experiment.
Even if we figure out what happened
and why in the past, that's not-- there's no guarantee
it's going to repeat again in the future.
At least, in the lab, we can do that
and try it and check that our ideas are working
the way that we would expect.
When we apply this to asset price dynamics,
we do it by drawing successive period returns
and then constructing the price process
as it goes forward in time.
And those could be independent or they
could be correlated returns.
When we go to compute analytics like means
and standard deviations and variances and Sharpe ratios
and kurtosis, and so on, we do that
not by doing Gaussian or other integrals in closed form.
We do it by computing statistics on the realized data.
The results are subject to sampling error, of course.
Because they're statistical, they
can be improved by doing more simulations.
But there are also important machine limitations,
some things we can't ever solve like the fact
that we can't exactly represent real numbers
or unbounded numbers on the computer.
And, we also might find that some of these things
are not necessarily efficient if we do them in a naive way.
And there's a very large literature
and a lot of techniques have been developed
for doing Monte Carlos in more efficient ways
and to get better accuracy for the same amount
of computational effort.