PROFESSOR: So there are a few different flavors
of the random walks.
We talk about the random walk model,
and of course the idealized random walk
is a zero parameter model with one step plus or minus one.
And that's kind of boring, and not useful for finance.
The three versions that we might consider,
and that Lo and MacKinlay explored,
we'll only be looking at the first one.
But we might think about different ways
of generalizing things.
So the first one is where the returns
are IID, that is, are independent and identically
distributed.
So X, think of as being the logarithm of the price,
so that Xt minus 1 is a logarithm of the price ratio.
Technically speaking, we can't take logarithms of prices,
only of pure numbers.
But a ratio of prices is a pure number.
So you could think of the Xt as being
the logarithm of the price divided by a reference price.
But here what we have is in each step
that Xt is the previous value plus mu
plus some random increment, which here I'm
calling epsilon T to leave it a bit more general.
And one of the things that we'll see
is in the analysis of Lo and MacKinlay,
they did it in such a way that it doesn't matter
what the distribution is.
So we're going to say that epsilon is required only
to be IID with mean 0 and variant sigma.
So it certainly could be something written in the form
sigma Zt that we wrote before.
But this allows possibly this notation is common
and we might allow for other kinds of distributions.
And we do have the requirement that,
in different time periods, that the epsilons be uncorrelated.
That's what we mean by independence.
So the delta function, delta TT prime, is equal to 1
if T is equal to T prime, and 0 otherwise.
So this says that epsilons in different time periods
aren't correlated, and that the variance
of the epsilon in the same period, epsilon T
squared, as expectation sigma squared.
We can also look at the conditional expectations.
So this says that the expectation of Xt
given X zero--
so we take the expectation of our series--
is going to be Xt plus UT.
That's our result, that the mean return grows linearly
with time, and that the variance conditioned
on a particular starting point X0,
is going to grow linearly with time.
Now two generalizations.
We have the random walk two, where
we can have instead of IID we can have them be independent,
but not identically distributed.
That is, the distribution could change over
different periods of time.
And there are important models in finance that do this,
and an example is a model of time varying volatility, where
we might have something where the returns are drawn
from a log normal distribution.
They look like a random walk within a day.
But then the parameters change from day to day.
So that would be a simple case that would not
fit under the random walk one.
So the returns would be not identical,
but they might be varying in some particular way
that we would specify.
And then we could have things that are not independent.
They could be dependent but maybe
they're dependent at a higher order.
So it's possible to have series where
we satisfy that the increments are uncorrelated,
but that doesn't mean that they're
independent random variables.
So it just means, remember that the independence implies
that the returns are uncorrelated,
but the returns can be uncorrelated
without them being independent.
So an example of this that also shows up in volatility models,
is one where the epsilons are uncorrelated,
but the squares are correlated.
And that would be another generalization.
So for this purpose for our analysis,
we're only going to do the first version.
Now variance ratios are constructed
in the following way.
We start with some base frequency.
And in our case, we're going to think about this
as being daily.
And as mentioned, in the case of Lo and MacKinlay,
they used weekly.
Then we're going to aggregate returns.
And we're going to do it in a very simple way.
So the two day return at time period T
is the return over the two days ending at time T.
So compared to the day returns, it's
equal to the period return plus the previous period return.
And of course, the logarithm using the property
that the logarithm of ratio is the difference
in the logarithm, logarithm of product
is the sum of the logarithms.
You can check that this just drops
out the intermediate value P sub T minus 1,
and gives us the return over a two day period.
So imagine you just looked at the stock prices,
you checked your portfolio every other day,
or possibly every two days.
So in that case, we would construct this
that I'm calling RT.
So ending on time period T, but with this superscript
in parentheses to denote the length of the observation
period, because it matters.
Usually we don't write that down, because we stick
to a convention, like daily.
But here we're going to be changing that.
So q denotes the observation window.
T denotes the particular period.
And for a given period it's the logarithmic return
over the period.
So starting q time steps back, up through the end
of the present period.
All right.
So if the returns were uncorrelated,
then we know that the variance computed from each series
is going to be proportional to its length.
That's the basic result we had from our original random walk
and generalized random walk model.
So if they're uncorrelated-- and that means that in this case,
that the variance of the q returns, the q period, or q day
returns, is q times the variance of the base frequency.
So the way we typically set up the test
is to see if this q dependence is really there.
And one way we can do it is to construct
the ratio of the variance of the q day
periods divided by q times the variance on the base frequency.
And if everything works and the returns are uncorrelated,
that should be equal to 1.
So for any q I construct this quantity down here.
And this quantity should be equal to 1,
no matter what q is.
So I can do it for q equals 2, 3, 17, any number at all.
And the number should be equal to 1.
So we have two questions.
One of them is, let's put it in the data.
Does it work?
And when we put in the data, it's
not going to be equal exactly to 1.
It never would be, even if the model works perfectly.
So how big a departure from 1 is actually significant?
So let's grab some data from Yahoo Finance, throw it into R,
and let's just compute a bunch of variances,
which you can do using the code that I've put here.
And what we see is, I've just plotted
the variance computed over N day observations against N.
And what do we see?
Well, we see this dependence over here,
which looks kind of linear.
It looks pretty good, right?
So we're done.
It actually works.
There's our random walk hypothesis.
Well, maybe we can do a little bit better.
First of all, is it exactly linear?
No.
How close should it be?
Can we say something about what the slope should be?
What about the variation around the slope?
And why does it seem to be getting rougher and more ragged
the farther out we go?
Is there a breakdown here, or is that something
that we should have expected?
So let's get into some details.
And these are some formulas taken from Lo
and MacKinlay's paper, which you can look
at there for the full details.
But let's take a look at what the estimates are,
how we can compute the variance ratio more precisely,
and then we'll take a look at the sampling
distribution for the tests that they actually did.
But we're not going to derive all of the statistical results.
I'd like to go for what the meaning is, show you
how you can implement it yourself,
and then refer you to the original paper
if you're interested in the full details.
So the first thing is we compute the returns,
and we need to match the length of the time series.
So we use our usual estimator, that the mean
is the arithmetical average.
So I take 1 over T times the sum of the returns,
and that gives me mu hat.
Now in terms of the variance, we can use the usual estimate
for the variance.
And we'll see that normally we have a T minus 1.
We'll get to some of the exact bias corrections in a moment,
but let's just work with this for right now.
So what we do is we take the returns relative to the mean,
compute their squared difference,
take the mean square variation over the period.
And we see already that as the sampling frequency gets
less frequent as we coarse grain over more and more days,
there are going to be fewer terms than the sum,
and that could be a contribution to that ragged behavior we
saw for the larger observation windows.
There are just fewer things in the sum.
And we know that we need at least say, 30 points for this
to be meaningful.
And 300 would be better.
3 million would be terrific.
But it's not going to be uniform as we
look over different periods.
What we do have in the Lo and MacKinlay approach though,
is that we're looking at a given historical period,
and by subdividing it at least we're not changing the period.
So if we pick 1988 to 2017, that's the same period.
If we subdivided, at least we're not
looking at things in different market conditions.
So the base frequency, we can look
at this computed with sigma hat a.
Sigma hat squared with a B subscript
is defined as relating to the q period
observations in this way.
So in this case, the returns need
to be taken relative to the mean for a q period return.
And the sampling distribution of this
tells us what we should expect.
So where should this be drawn from.
So it can be shown that we've got a sampling distribution
that these statistics are asymptotically
normal with a particular mean invariance.
We're going to take the square root of T
be here and scale it out, because we
know that's always there.
And we'll take a look for these distributions,
and when we get to the actual data
we'll turn things into normalized
so we can look at typical kind of z-scores and T statistics.
We can account for overlapping returns
and slightly increase the power of the results
by looking at returns that are taken over possibly overlapping
periods, rather than looking at discrete windows.
And one advantage to doing that, certainly,
is that we don't want there to be any arbitrariness in when
we started our series.
But we need to account for multiple counting,
because those returns are obviously
not going to be independent if the windows were overlapping.
So the test that we perform is to see if the variance ratio is
equal to 1.
And when we boil everything down,
or when Lo and MacKinlay do, what we
find is we can define a nice value called z over here.
So this z number is what we're going to compute,
and we're going to compute it because it is normally
distributed with mean 0 and variance 1.
Which means that if, under the null hypothesis,
if the random walk holds, we should
expect z to lie between plus or minus 2, 95% of the time.
In between plus or minus 3, 99% of the time.
And if we get values that are much larger than that,
then that would be evidence for rejecting a random walk.
The things that we have here involve the variance ratio
itself, in this case computed with
this particular combination.
And we'll adjust that again.
But a particular-- this is in the spirit that we had before.
These are just the computational details.
So we take the ratio of the variance
divided by q times the variance over the base period.
We subtract 1, and then this pre-factor over here
adjusts for the overlapping periods for the scaling
with the square root of T.
And we'll see that there are additional bias
corrections that make this a little more accurate.
But the idea is, scale everything so that we can
compare it to N(0,1).
That's easier than just taking this ratio here, and comparing
it to a more complicated distribution.
So it's a choice that we can make.
So to improve things a little bit
we can tighten up the formulas and write them
in this way, where we have the mu.
Obviously, we don't need to compute
the intermediate returns, because we can just
look at the endpoints.
So we can compute the mean return here.
We can compute sigma a variance a, in terms of the base
frequency.
Sigma B is the one that we had before,
which is done with the q period observations.
And C is the one done over overlapping periods.
And you notice that the pre-factor and the summation
are done a little bit differently
for the terms that entered.
But this one is done using overlapping windows, which can
improve the power for the test.
I've put some code here that you can take and run
that implements this.
Where we can take some data, compute
these different variances at the base frequency,
and at any given frequency R.
And we can compute then, this function z as a function of q
for our data.
And then we can get things out.
So we can compute a set of variances
that we could look at for our data.
We can compute these z statistics.
The function z of q, which are T stats for the tests,
and see if they lie between minus 2 and 2,
or minus 3 and 3.
And then if we want, we can get p values that
are the probabilities of observing
extreme results as extreme, or more extreme
than we see from z.
And then finally, we can do some plots of this.
So the idea of building this particular z with this
particular function is so that we can compare it to the N(0,1)
distribution, which makes it very nice.
So remember, it's a normal distribution.
And if the random walk holds, we're
going to see z be somewhere near 0.
The variance ratio should be near 1.
The z statistic, which measures the significance
of the departures just due to sampling error from
our distribution of a given finite length,
is what we want to study to see if a number that's not 1.000 is
exactly meaningful or not.
And if not, we'll see if there are any other directions
that we might choose to go.
Now there are a whole bunch of other technical complications
if we really want to sharpen this,
but I think that we can actually get a good idea just
by doing the variance ratio test on the simple data
that we did before.
But if you want to do it right, there
are additional formulas to get this very precise z
with these additional factors just to normalize everything
exactly right.
When Lo and MacKinlay did this they
looked for individual stocks, and they
looked at different periods, and different frequencies.
And what they found was that nothing obeyed the random walk.
So to pick a particular example, if we
look where they looked at both equally weighted and value
weighted indices, the numbers that they report here,
and here, and here, none of these numbers is equal to 1.
In fact, they're actually all bigger than 1.
If these were due to sampling error
we might expect some to be high, some to be low.
These are the different frequencies
that they looked at two, four, eight, 16.
So they looked at evenly divisible series.
That's not necessarily required, but it is convenient.
And then below the numbers they show the T statistics,
or the magnitude of the z of q.
And you'll see that these are all very large numbers.
So not only are the numbers 1.3, 1.64, not equal to 1,
they're significantly different from 1.
So let's take a look at it with our Tootsie Roll data.
So what we can do is, we can look at our data.
We can get a rough idea of what's
going on by computing the variance or the volatility
at using different sampling frequencies,
and just see if we're in the ballpark.
So if we do that-- you can try this,
running the code I have before--
you get the result that we see here
on this graph, where the volatility is
done over the entire period, but using different scaling
results.
So is it exactly the same over every sampling window?
Absolutely not.
But it's roughly constant.
So you can see why we need these statistical tests.
Is that close enough?
So roughly speaking, it looks like it
might be like a random walk.
It has that general attribute.
This is just another rescaled version
of what we saw earlier on the linear plot.
But how well does this actually hold?
If we want to get a very quick and dirty idea just to eyeball
it and say, are those variations reasonable before we
run any statistical tests, what we can do
is we can do a Monte Carlo.
So let's compute simulated price data that
has the same mean and volatility as the Tootsie Roll stock does.
And then on that simulated data-- pretending
that we didn't know it's simulated--
do the same calculation.
That is, let's compute volatility
over different time periods.
And here we see the same general qualitative behavior
on this plot as we saw in the previous one.
So it's possible that what we're looking at
could just be statistical error, or it's possible
that there could be systematic departures from the random walk
when we do the detailed analysis.