PROFESSOR: In this video will test a random walk.
We'll look at the computational and data
tables that are needed to do an analysis,
perform a variance ratio test, and explore whether asset
prices may be predictable, whether the random walk
hypothesis holds for a given data set or not.
I'm doing this in an R notebook.
And R notebooks are text files that contain code
but they also contain discussion around them.
So on the left hand side of my screen,
you can see the raw contents of the text
file of the R notebook.
And you can load that into your own version of RStudio.
And on the right hand side is the formatted version in HTML
which you can do whatever you'd like with.
And when you hit this preview button
on the top of the screen, it'll regenerate
the preview of the notebook.
But right now what we'll be doing
is mostly working on the left hand side.
And we'll start by loading a few packages.
Now packages in R are installed once
and then they're run many times.
So to install a package if you've never seen it,
you uncomment these lines, it'll grab the package
and run the package to install it on your computer.
Subsequently, packages are loaded into a given session
using the library command.
So for right now I think the only one
that we need here is going to be the tidyquant package that
will help us with the function to fetch some data directly
into R so that we don't need to load it from a flat file.
That's a perfectly honorable thing to do.
So I click here and run this current chunk,
and it will run and load the packages of interest.
We'll get a few descriptive messages that will go away
the next time we run it.
So those are not essential information
or essential reading.
Now let's take a look at some data.
Specifically, we'll take a look at stock for Tootsie Roll
when the longest continuously the companies that's
been around publicly traded for a long period of time
since the beginning of the end of the 19th century
beginning of the 20th century.
And we'll get some data for Tootsie Roll.
And if we do grab data, there are a number
of issues we normally need to be concerned about, which are,
what's the data source?
How do they handle corporate actions?
What's the format of the file?
How are the line breaks handled?
What is delimiters and so on?
So we could start with the CSV file
or we could grab things directly from Yahoo Finance.
So I'll show you the latter here.
So what we'll do is we'll use this one function called
tq_get() which is the tidyquant get function that will grab
a given ticker symbol for a range of dates,
and grab data from Yahoo Finance.
So we'll do that now.
The ticker symbol that will define here
is tr for Tootsie Roll and we'll pick a range of dates.
Now one of the things that we're going to do, so hit the Run
button here and with fingers crossed because we're
running this live.
Will hope that everything looks.
So one of the things that we commonly do
is because we usually are more interested in returns
than in prices, we need to get and we'll always
need extra prices to be able to compute a return series.
So we typically want to start retrieving data few days
at least before the first return that we need to compute.
So here I've done this for the period
from 1988 to the end of 2017.
So this is before the Wall Street Bets era.
So to check that we've got the data, we can go to our console
and take a look at a view data, or we can run and take a look
at any of the lines.
So we can either say head TR to take a look
at the first few rows, or we can say View with a capital V,
to take a look at all of the data.
And what we see is that, we've got here from Yahoo Finance
is data structure where the first column is the ticker
symbol.
Then we have the date open high-low close volume.
And the last column called adjusted is what we'll use.
That's where the prices have been
adjusted for corporate actions.
Tootsie roll was an interesting and unusual dividend policy
which we won't go into, we'll just
be working with these adjusted prices.
So, what does the data look like?
Well, here's what the price chart looks like over time.
So I'm going to click here, and I
wanted to show you some code through example.
I'm just using the base R plot function,
we can make much nicer plots using the GG plot package.
But here we're just doing vanilla plots,
and we can dress them up later on.
So here's the Tootsie Roll adjusted price
over this period.
So it's had a bumpy ride.
But generally if you are invested in toastie roll,
you've done pretty well.
OK?
Next, now notice that as I update this
as we run chunks of code, that on the right hand
side of my notebook up here, and as we scroll down,
we'll get these graphs will be incorporated.
And we can even include formulas by writing things, commands,
and LaTeX.
So we can get formulas here.
So here's what we do.
We defined the logarithmic returns,
as being the logarithm of the price
ratios, the last observed price divided by the previous price,
and we see that can be written as a difference
of successive price logarithms.
So, in code what we're going to do is extract the prices,
get the return series and most of our analysis
really is going to be testing the returns themselves.
Because the returns, when we talk about random walk we
sometimes in finance because the context is usually clear,
we may abuse the language a little bit.
What we're talking about is the return series
for a random walk being uncorrelated random variables
over time.
The price series does have levels that matter,
and it's by taking these differences of logarithms
and we get to the series of interest.
So there are two things we could do.
First, we could just strip off the data and work with that,
or we can also store the data as part of our data structure.
So there are two ways we can do it.
First of all, what I can do is I can
define a variable p that just pulls out the adjusted price
process.
I can say r is diff log p.
That implements the formula that we
see behind me you just move that up the screen a little bit.
There we go.
So for that formula right here.
Sorry, trying to highlight it, there we go.
A little awkwardly, sorry about that.
So anyway this formula here is the formula that we want.
We get that in code by saying diff log R,
you could write a for loop if you like just
to take successive differences, and then we'll
add and be the length of the series.
Then what we can also do, let me just run this chunk
as we're speaking.
What we can also do is we can add a new column to our data
structure.
And when I do that, if I look at tr,
we'll see that now there's a new column here R. At the end,
I don't think I want things sorted by R, sorry about that.
But here we've got this new column.
So let's just see what we did in the code.
What we did was we set a new column here for our TR.
We added a column r, and we had to include a leading
NA for the simple reason that we're always
going to have one less return than we do prices.
So if we want things to line up, the return corresponding
to our very first price is not available
because we don't know the price before that.
But all the others will line up with their corresponding dates,
and then that first date of interest we'll toss it out,
so that everything is lined up starting on the first trading
day of 1988 in this example.
Now we can take the returns and then
we can plot those, and see what those look like.
And if we do that, we get a graph
that you can see over here on the side,
where we see the daily return series.
Now, the daily return series is noisy.
And the mean return is not really visible on this scale.
And this is typical of a lot of financial return data,
that on very short time scales like a day or less,
it's almost impossible to see the mean return.
But you certainly can see the risk.
You certainly can see the fluctuations in value.
So we'll use some statistics to get
at the heart of what's going on to both characterize,
to describe the data, and then look
at what we can say about the relationship across time
and about any predictability that might
be present in the data series.
So let's just compare this picture
with what it would look like if it were a pure white noise
series.
So what I'm going to do here, is I'm
going to generate using the rnorm function.
A set of random variables drawn from a normal distribution
that are scaled to have 0 mean and the same standard deviation
as the Tootsie Roll data does.
So we can see at a glance this is hardly a statistical test,
but we can see that they don't exactly look the same.
That is the white noise process is noisy,
but it's much more uniform over time.
Whereas the Tootsie Roll process has not only some pretty big
spikes that come along, but there
are periods of intense fluctuation
and some periods of quiet.
So what this might suggest is that volatility
itself can vary over time.
And then when we talk about the volatility of a process,
maybe that's something that we would eventually
need to generalize.
OK?
So that's just in pictures for looking at our data.
We can get some summary statistics for the data.
So we can use the summary command in R
to give us a look at our data set.
And it tells us for each of our data fields
open, high-low, close, and the return.
What's the mean?
What's the max?
What's mean?
What's the median, interquartile range, and so on.
So we've got 7,500 observations which isn't bad,
and we can see a range of the numbers.
Now these numbers in particular, if we look at the returns
are pretty small because their daily numbers.
So the convention is that we annualize numbers
when we're looking at return and risk data.
And that means that for our annualization conventions,
that when it comes to returns, we're
going to multiply by the number of time periods.
And when it comes two standard deviations,
we're going to multiply by the square root
of the number of time periods.
And this is just a convention for scaling
our descriptive statistics.
It would be natural if, in fact, we
have random walks, because we know that the variance scales
with the square that with time linearly,
and the standard deviation with its square root.
We don't know how this data behaves,
but by convention when we report descriptive statistics,
we typically use these conventions.
Why 252?
It's the typical number of trading days in the US equity
markets.
Now, if we look at what that would correspond to, let's
run this, and let's take a look at how
we would get the numbers.
So if we take the mean return and multiply by 252,
and we take the standard deviation
and we multiplied by the square root of 252,
we find that we get a return, annualized return of about 8.3%
with a volatility of about 24%, which
is not unusual for US stock.
Now let's take a look at the histogram of the returns,
and see what their distribution looks like.
Now the histogram is very sharply peaked in the middle.
So it doesn't look Gaussian, it's not rounded over the top.
It's kind of squished in the middle, which is interesting.
But it is single peaked and if you remember,
our discussion of the attributes of a random walk, and of time
series models generally use primarily the moment
of the distribution not the full distribution.
So when we're interested in the sum of the random variables,
whether the individual random variables are
drawn from a Gaussian or a log normal distribution,
or whether there binomial coin flips
doesn't make a difference in terms of the large time scale
properties when we add together a large number
of random variables, and we ask about the mean and variance
of the sum.
But it's always a good idea to look at your data.
So Lo and MacKinlay asked about whether the variance
of a sample of returns, in fact, grows linearly
as a function of the observation interval?
So the difference is, what they did
is instead of letting the time and just adding
more and more days where the market conditions might
have changed, they ask about taking a fixed number of days
and looking at different course screening.
So we can look at daily observations,
then we can go to two day periods.
We can go to four day periods.
We can go to one week, one month, and so on.
So they did powers of 2.
Here we'll just run a for loop and do different numbers
of days from two days through 100 days,
and let's take a look at it.
What we're doing here is, we're looking
at the variance, of the difference, of the logarithms,
of the price.
And the price what we're doing in our
we're looking at taking steps but of size n.
Now that's going to leave in the event
where n does not evenly divide 7,561 or 7562 observations
that we have.
That will leave a few points left over at the end.
So this is just to give us a rough idea.
It's not as precise as making sure that we divide things,
but we can see at a glance that we've got a generally
linear behavior.
And now we could ask, so does that settle the matter.
Does that say a yes, the variance
grows linearly with time.
Well, we don't know what the slope
is, we don't know it's exactly linear,
and after all, there is some scatter around
and the scatter gets worse as we go further out.
Now that could be because we have
a breakdown of the hypothesis as we get to larger values.
And then, on the other hand, it could just
be that as our observation windows get larger,
there are fewer of them and we're
going to have less statistical significance
in our observations, and we would think that things
would be somewhat noisier.
So let's take a look at some of these metrics.
Now this is the code.
And let me move this over here.
So you can see the code.
So this is the code that's in the Lo and MacKinlay paper,
and that I discussed in lecture where we can construct
a variety of different flavors of variants,
where we might have overlapping windows,
we have some scale adjustments, some removal of bias factors.
But the basic idea is that what we're going to do
is construct an adjusted variance for our data,
get all the scaling and all the pre factors
right on our Lo and MacKinlay.
And then, we're going to compute the sampling statistic
for the variance ratio.
So remember that in the ideal case,
the variance ratio where we take the variance
divide by n or q times the, if q is the number of days
that we're aggregating, that if we take the variance
and take the ratio to the day variance,
and we include a factor of q to scale out
the obvious overall dependence, that variance ratio should
be equal to 1 if there's a random walk.
But the question is not do we get.
One, we're going to get something
in the neighborhood of one this would be what we'd expect.
But how significant are the deviations from one.
And to do that, we have the Z statistic.
And the Z statistic is constructed
so that it is sampled from an n zero 1 distribution.
That is it should be Gaussian distributed with 0 mean
and unit variance itself.
So a Z that falls in the range of between plus or minus 2
or maybe even plus or minus 3, could
be consistent with a hypothesis being true.
Large values of the Z, outside of plus or minus 2
would be considered a significant departure.
And if we were to do different tests
we'd expect the Z's to be uncorrelated with each other.
So let's take a look.
So we can run this now that we've got our data,
and we have our return series.
We define this function variance.c for a function
and we'll run it on our data set.
OK, so let's run this chunk.
And let's take a look at some of the results that we get.
Now again if I want to update things on the right hand side,
I click the Preview button just above my window.
And now things will be update on the right hand side as well.
And here's a bar plot of the results of our variance ratio
test.
So what we can see is that all of the values
have the same sign.
These are all negative.
Of course, each of these windows these are not independent
data samples were doing different levels
of aggregation, but what we see is that a lot of the values
are greatly in excess of minus 2.
In fact, almost all of these are.
So that means that in our Tootsie Roll data
set that we can reject the random walk
hypothesis for this range of values,
and for this time period within the data set.
OK?
So what you can do is certainly you can go back and take
a look at rerunning this or you should run it first yourself,
but you can go back and change pretty much everything.
You can pick a different stock, and you can pick the same stock
in a different range, or you can change all of this,
rerun and take a look and see what you get.
I'd encourage you to take a look at it
for a couple of stocks of interest to you,
and also to take a look at stock indices.
We might expect stocks and stock indices
to behave differently after all stock index has values that
are generated by a weighted sum of a bunch
of different companies, which may have
low correlation to each other.
So some of the noise may average out.
So I would encourage you to take this code, or even better
to write your own, and to run the tests
on some data of your own.
So just one final thing to take a look
at a, what this means in terms of volatility
is, if we were to go back and construct the returns
and scale them.
So if we take the variance and we now multiply times
square root of q or square root of n
to the appropriate numerator denominator.
So that we get things normalized.
If we take a look here what I've defined
is sigma n to be scaled with 1 over square root of n
times the standard deviation.
And instead of looking at is the plot linear,
let's take out that expected dependence
and ask if our results are constant.
After all, that's what we're looking at in our Z statistic.
The idea of something that is a random walk
by the variance ratio test is, that no matter what aggregation
scale we look at, we should always
get the same value for the variance.
So if we do that, we find that we
get kind of a bumpy ride for different values,
but we wouldn't expect it to be exactly flat.
And the values are all in the 20 to 30%
range, which are reasonable for a stock.
If we want to get a rough idea without the precise statistical
analysis, then what we could do is
we might want to compare that again to simulated data,
and run a Monte Carlo to generate
data that could have come from a white noise random walk
process.
And we could ask what we would expect
to see for its variance just due to sampling error.
So this is just a visualization to help give us an intuitive
sense of the statistical test on the one hand,
and we have an intuitive pictorial sense,
and I think both that reasoning might be helpful.
So in this case you've got some code
that implements a variance ratio test,
you've got some code that will go grab data from Yahoo
Finance, or if you can put it in yourself manually from any data
source that you like.
You can run the test and take a look
at the behavior of the variance as you
run through the different aggregations.
And you can take a look at the detailed statistical analysis
for Lo and MacKinlay carefully normalized Z statistic,
and see for your data set whether you can reject
the random walk hypothesis.