PROFESSOR: Let's talk briefly about multivariate time series
when there's more than one variable.
We didn't do that in lecture this week.
But there is a question on the P set.
So I'd like to make sure everyone's ready to tackle it.
Now, when there are many variables
and they're interconnected, there are pretty much
three things that could happen.
One of them is you can solve it with the same techniques.
You can do things recursively.
And you certainly can do that with this problem.
And maybe by brute force, you're fiddling around.
You might see some interesting symmetries or simplifications.
The second category of things that can't be solved at all.
They're just complicated.
And there's no special insight for them.
And some phase like that, like the GARCH model,
which I mentioned earlier, don't have simple solutions in terms
of elementary functions.
But the other category is when there are symmetries.
And there are multiple variables to come in on an equal footing.
And in that, there are some ways that we
can reframe the equations that not only help us solve it,
the numbers we got will be the same
as with any other valid technique.
But they give us a little bit of insight as to what's going on.
So let me just remind you for the structure,
I think we've got a problem here from this week.
Let me just grab that.
And let's expand it a bit--
shall we?
So we have two equations.
We've got xt is lambda y.
Oops, I'm sorry.
We should have t minus 1--
minus 1.
And this should be minus 1.
So we've got xt is lambda times t minus 1 plus sigma z.
And then we have the same thing basically
with x and y reversed.
And we've given z and w.
They're all independent of each other.
But we've given them different letters.
So we have x is related to a past y.
Y is related to a past x.
And certainly, we could substitute that
and look at it recursively.
But what's really going on in the dynamics?
What's really going on is these equations
say that x and y are jointly influenced
by their past histories.
Whatever happened in the past in x influences.
Y, whatever happened in the past of y influences x.
And, of course, then they cross over in the next time step,
they go back and forth.
So what it's saying is these two variables
are really jointly working together.
And they're processing information together
as they go forward in time.
So it's fine.
And the z's and the w's are independent.
They're just noise terms that show up
new in each period of time.
But what often happens when we have linear equations like this
whether they're linear time series models like this one,
whether they're linear differential equations,
whether they're statistics for joint distributions
of random variables in certain case,
like jointly normal distributions,
it turns out that we can analyze this
to identify certain linear combinations
of our basic variables in terms of which the model,
the dynamics all simplify.
And it reduces to a bunch of uncoupled equation.
That is to say if we start with N equations of this type--
and maybe they're more complicated
on the right-hand side.
But the basic point is suppose we have N variables, not just
two, x and y.
So we've got x1, x2, x3.
We've got a whole bunch of variables.
And we have a linear structure where
we have the x's at time t are related to the previous value
plus some noise term.
And maybe we could generalize from
this autoregressive structure which
is known as a VAR or vector autoregressive
model to a more general ARMA type model or ARIMA model.
But it's a linear structure that's of interest to us.
So when we have this linear structure,
one of the things we might look for
is, is there a way to reduce N coupled equations
down to N independent univariate equations
with only one variable where that variable is
a well-chosen linear combination of the starting variables.
And then we are down to a problem
that we've already solved.
We solve it, and we transform the variables back.
Now, this case is particularly easy.
And I don't want to give away the answer.
You can do it either by inspection and playing with it
or by taking a look.
But let me show you the general way that we can analyze this.
So the first step is we'll define vector variable
in terms of the old variable.
And then at the end, we'll invert.
we'll turn them back.
Or you will.
I'll just show you the general structure here today.
So let's take a vector, xt, yt.
And let's give it a new name.
Instead of primes or other things,
let me try some Greek letters.
Let's just call it xi sub t.
And I will sometimes put arrows.
But often, I'll drop my arrows.
So I hope-- that's one reason I went
to pick different letters that from the context
is clear which are vectors.
And let's combine our noise terms zt and wt.
And let's put them in a vector that we're going to call eta t.
So in terms of these, what is our equation look like?
Well, our structure of our equation
is going to be such that we have xi_t,
the vector, is going to be some matrix M times t,
t minus 1 plus sigma times eta t.
And what is the matrix M?
Well, in this particular example, M is going to be a 2
by 2 matrix, which has the form 0 lambda, lambda 0.
When this matrix M here acts on this vector,
you can see that it interchanges the x and y.
It gives lambda-- excuse me-- x goes down.
Y goes up.
And then we have our basic equation.
Here, this gives us the right-hand side
of our original equation.
So in terms of this structure, all we've done
is we've used linear algebra notation.
To rewrite it, we haven't done anything at all yet.
We notice that M does have a particularly nice and symmetric
form.
But our task when we want to decouple things
when we want to separate them and see what
the real independent drivers are is
to diagonalize or orthogonalize that.
So diagonalize we can do in general
by doing an eigenvalue decomposition.
And in the case of a symmetric matrix,
the eigenvectors that we find will be orthogonal.
And what are these eigenvectors before we get there?
What we're looking for is the eigenvectors
are going to be particular combinations of x and y--
our original x and y in terms of which the equations simplify
and actually can be written as two
independent one-variable equation.
So we can do this if we had six variables,
if we had 16 variables.
We could take it and reduce it to that same number
of independent linear equations.
So let me just remind you of what those features are.
So in general, we can diagonalize a matrix.
We can diagonalize M, writing it in the form of v.
And normally, I would call it lambda.
But I've already used lambda.
So let me call it gamma for our matrix
of eigenvalues v minus 1.
So v is a matrix whose columns are eigenvectors.
And gamma is a diagonal matrix--
eigenvalues.
Now, take a moment--
just look at the matrix M for a moment that we have right here
and see if you can figure out what the eigenvalues
and eigenvectors are.
And then I'll write them down, and we can compare notes.
So pause the video here, go take a look, and then come back.
So the eigenvectors are 1, 1, and 1 minus 1.
And they have eigenvalues lambda and minus lambda respectively.
So to formalize that, what we do is we put them into a matrix.
And we will normalize because they're orthogonal.
We will normalize them with a Euclidean metric.
Let's write that we have v is going to be the matrix
1 over square root of 2 times 1 minus 1, 1, 1.
It's inverse.
It's an orthogonal matrix.
It's just equal to the transpose.
V minus 1 is going to be 1 over square root of 2.
And that's just in this example.
In general, it might be so much more complicated
and by a matrix.
1, 1.
So this is just a nice 2 by 2 example.
And gamma is going to be the matrix, the diagonal matrix,
lambda 0--
0 minus lambda.
So this matrix V encodes each of the columns
is an eigenvector of M. And you can check that.
If you multiply M times that, you'll get lambda.
If you take the M times the first column,
you'll get lambda times the first column.
If you take M times the first column,
If you take M times the second column,
you get minus lambda times the second column.
So this is exactly what we need.
And how do we use it?
Well, let's just substitute it into our equation.
So well, so here's our equation.
And what we're going to do is we're going to write this M.
We're going to substitute this eigenvalue decomposition-- v
gamma v minus 1.
So let's do that.
And we will write that xi_t vector is going to be v gamma v
minus 1 times t minus 1 plus sigma eta_t .
And now, let's multiply the equation through by v minus 1.
So we write v inverse xi_t on the left.
And that's going to be equal to v inverse times v is just
the identity matrix.
So this is going to be gamma, which
is a diagonal matrix times v minus 1,
xi_t minus 1 plus sigma times v inverse times eta of t.
So this is actually all we need.
So now we're basically done.
So we have two equations--
the first and second components of this thing.
Let's call-- let's give it a name.
If we define-- now, I will use a prime.
Let's call it xi_t prime to be v inverse times xi_t.
Then we have two equations.
We have the first component is going
to be xi prime 1t is going to be lambda times
xi prime 1 at t minus 1 plus sigma times eta
prime 1, the first component.
And our second component is going
to be xi 2 prime at time t is going
to be minus lambda, xi 2 at time t minus 1
plus sigma times eta 2.
So if you take the equations for v and you solve it
and you plug it in, you can find that you can decouple
these equations or other ones.
And you can solve them that way.
So this is a more general approach.
Now, just so a recap and one further comment.
So the first thing is that what we did is we looked for a way
when the variables enter in such a way
that the dynamics, the multiple equations-- but they're
really doing is they're all the same kind of equation.
They all have the same general structure.
In this case, this vector autoregressive model
is component by component.
Each line is a AR type model.
And the multiple equations just reshuffle the variable.
So what we're going to do is unshuffle them,
solve the equations, and then reshuffle the combinations back
to get our final answers.
So very straightforward.
That way, we don't need any new or magical tricks.
One thing that did make this particularly easy,
however, was in addition to the way
in which the variables entered and the coefficients were all
very simple in this case, again, more generally,
we'd have a general matrix, general eigenvalue
decomposition.
But also, it was full rank.
And therefore, the M was invertable.
So that was important.
And also, the noise terms all entered
with the single coefficient.
So their coefficient was basically a diagonal matrix.
And everything went through.
When we look at other settings where
we look at linear models in finance,
for example, factor models of covariance in portfolio
management and risk management-- we
have two things that differ quite significantly.
The first one is that the matrices we use in a factor
model may be of lower rank.
In fact, that's the entire benefit of factor models.
What we want to do in that setting,
unlike this particular setting, is
we want to eliminate degrees of freedom.
We want to describe the important risk
drivers of a set of financial instruments
in terms of common factors, which might
be an overall market factor.
It might be industry exposure.
It might be other economic or financial variables.
But the idea is to simplify to say
that we have some common factors affecting many assets.
Let's simplify the description.
So we would expect to have matrices that
are of less than full rank.
On the other hand, the noise terms
do need to have a matrix, which is full rank,
because the noise terms are idiosyncratic.
They are independent.
So we may have these two differences,
which is we may see that the matrices have different ranks.
And we may see, in fact, that a lot of the way and the factor
model setting and some of the structure that we
see in the covariance matrix really
is driven more by the noise terms
than by the nonnoise terms.
Here, they come in more or less on an equal footing
and in this example where one matrix was
the coefficient of the noise terms must diagonal.
It made it rather simple to take a look at.
So I hope this was helpful.
And however you solve the problem,
I hope you're always on the lookout
for new ways and multiple ways to solve a problem not only so
that you have multiple techniques, because generally,
each new technique brings some different insights into what's
going on with the underlying functions, data,
and random processes.