PROFESSOR: Ito processes are generalized Brownian motion,
and Brownian motion is a continuous time random walk.
We've looked at how to describe the evolution of a random walk
in differential and in integral form,
and now, let's consider an ensemble,
a whole set of paths and random walks,
like those you can see behind me.
We start at a particular point, and each of these paths
is an equally probable realization
of what might happen.
These are paths simulated on a computer,
where I have taken the expression for an Ito process,
discretized it, and in this case,
we can see that, from the same data generating
process with the same drift rate and volatility,
some of our paths go up.
Some of them go down.
None of them are straight for any period of time.
But if we think about this as time evolves, as we go from
left to right, and we think of considering cross sections
at a particular point in time, what does the distribution look
like?
What is the probability of a random walk
appearing at a given distance from the origin?
Well, from this picture, we can see a few things.
First, we can see that the outcomes are indeed random,
that whether we're up or down or where
we are depends on which paths.
So many, many outcomes are possible at any given
point in time.
We also can see that the width of the distribution
grows over time, and there's no surprise.
We know that the variance grows linearly,
that the standard deviation grows
with the square root of time, and that
means that individual random walks tend to diffuse away
from the origin.
The longer time goes on, the greater chance
they have of reaching a larger distance
and the more improbable it is they're found near the origin,
even though the center of the distribution
remains the most probable place.
So let's think about-- keep this picture in mind,
of random walks.
We want to think about, for a given
point in time, what the distribution of outcomes
that is.
What the probability distribution function is?
What's the likelihood, at a given point in time,
that I end up here versus here versus right
in the thick of things or right down here?
And that, of course, is a function of time,
but typically, we think, of course,
of starting with initial conditions
and letting time evolve forwards.
What we're going to see and take advantage
of is that, for a given initial condition,
we can ask about probabilities of reaching future outcomes.
The probability distribution functions
we have, though, will be a function
of the initial starting point, and the fact
that it depends on both endpoints of our walk--
the initial starting point and the uncertain future outcome--
will be helpful for us for solving the Black-Scholes
equation.
So let's start with basics--
give a random variable, mean mu, and variance sigma squared--
which we write in this way.
We say that x is drawn from a normal distribution of mean mu
and variant sigma squared.
We have the familiar Gaussian probability density function.
p of x is a normalization factor, one of our square root
to pi sigma squared.
e to the minus x minus mu quantity squared--
that tells us that the center of the peak
is when the exponential vanishes,
when x equals mu, divided by 2 sigma squared,
which tells us-- which normalizes the distribution.
Sigma is the width of the distribution,
and that tells us that we can think
about how far we are from the peak in units of sigma.
If our distance from the peak in units of sigma
is the same, when we change sigma,
the probabilities will be identical.
So that's for a single random variable.
Now, a time dependence stochastic process,
x sub t, which we've seen, which we've looked at,
saying Ito process with constant coefficients mu and sigma,
as a generalized arithmetic Brownian motion,
has variants sigma squared t, and its got mean mu t.
That is, the mean grows linearly with time.
The variance grows also linearly with time.
So what does that mean?
That means xt, the end point, the distance we've
traveled from the initial point, is a Gaussian distributed
random variable.
That's true for all time scales t, from dt infinitesimal
to macroscopic time scales, and that
means we know what the probability distribution is
for the endpoints.
We know the probability density function is the same as the one
we had before, but where now, it's a function of t,
and we put in t in the appropriate places.
Mu gets replaced by mu t, and sigma
squared get replaced by sigma squared t.
And you can check that this is still appropriately normalized.
But the picture is now quite different.
This is what we saw on the previous slide.
The peak of this distribution moves at speed t.
If mu is a positive number, it moves to the right.
If mu is a negative number, it moves to the left,
and I've illustrated that up here behind me.
So this might be the peak at one point.
This is at a point mu t.
And as time goes on, the peak moves to the right.
These are subsequent time steps, and as the distribution
moves to the right, we also see that, with the peak,
sigma squared of t broadens out over time.
So this probability distribution describes a time varying bell
curve, the Gaussian shape.
It moves to the right for positive mu at speed mu,
and it broadens out with time.
That also means that if we're to run time backwards, that as t
gets smaller and approaches 0, that we would be moving
in the opposite direction.
That is, that the peaks get narrower--
the curves get narrower and narrower
and get more and more concentrated
at a central value.
So that's our Gaussian distribution.
We've just applied it in a new way.
We've seen it in many settings, and here's one more.
You can check that this probability distribution
function, p of xt, satisfies a differential equation called
the Fokker-Planck equation, and I've written it here.
Partial derivative with respect to t minus sigma
squared over 2.
Second partial with respect to x plus the mu
dependent term mu, partial of p with respect to x.
And you can check that by taking partial derivatives,
and in fact, each of the partial derivatives
is proportional to p itself because
of the exponential nature here.
And the prefactor doesn't change that, so all of the terms
can be written as proportional to p.
If you take the appropriate partials,
substitute them into the equation,
you'll see that this, in fact, is
a differential equation for that probability density function.
So just to recap--
this probability density function
measures the distribution.
If we do this for a Monte Carlo simulation,
the histogram at a given point in time
would be one of these curves, and it
would be an approximation to one of these curves.
And as time goes on, the peaks move out,
but in particular, the curve broadens.
So that was for a random walk that began at the origin
and went to a point xt.
But now, suppose we're specific about starting
at a particular point, x0 t0.
And in this notation, you can read this
as the probability to be at x big T
at time big T given that we started at x0 at time t0.
So it looks a little complicated.
There are for arguments, but the first two
are measuring the probability of being observed
at this point in time, given that we
started deterministically at point x0 and t0.
Now, in this expression, this is just from time and space
translation.
Everything depends on t minus t0 and x minus x0.
So this is the same expression that we wrote down
before if you take the special case where x0 equals 0
and where t0 equals 0.
But it's interesting to note that, having written it down,
even though big T and t0 have very
different interpretations--
one is where we observe a random variable.
The other is where we begin our random walk.
But time t0, we know exactly where we are.
The distribution has to be concentrated at x0.
Despite the fact that they have very different meanings,
as a function, we can evaluate p both as a function
of its first two arguments or as a function of its last two
arguments.
And if I think about it as a function of x0
and t0 holding xt and big T fixed,
then I find that it satisfies a different differential
equation called a backward equation,
and it's backward because we're looking
at the wrong point in t.
That is, this is asking a slightly different question.
It's saying, if I wanted to observe the probability
at a particular value at a particular ending point,
how does that depend on where I start?
The probability will change, obviously.
The farther away I am, depending on the distance
in time or in space, the smaller the probability will be.
So it's a fair question to ask how this function depends
on the two arguments x0 and t0.
Because it's so similar, because everything depends only
on differences, I can replace partial of p
with respect to t by the negative of the partial p
with respect to t0.
And similarly, for the x derivatives, so
this term changes sign.
This term changes sign.
This one would get 2 sign changes
because there are two x0.
So now, where before, we had two relative plus signs and one
minus sign, all three of these signs
are positive in this differential equation.
In this equation, we haven't derived from anywhere else.
All we're saying is, if we plug in this expression,
this Gaussian curve into this differential equation,
that the equation is satisfied.