PROFESSOR: Let's look at how to compute option prices via Monte
Carlo methods.
So here's the rule for applying risk-neutral pricing.
The rule is to get the risk-neutral measure,
then we take the drift rate mu and we replace it by r.
Now, this is beyond the scope of the course,
but there's a larger subject about changes of variables
and changes of measures to ensure
that we have risk neutrality, and,
under the risk-neutral measure, that we don't have arbitrage.
So the origin of this is a no arbitrage argument.
The conclusion of that argument is
that all traded assets, in order to avoid arbitrage,
have to have discounted price processes that
are martingales that helps us construct the Q-measure.
But for our case, for a stock price,
it obeys the rule that I just said.
Everywhere where you see a mu, replace it
by r, use that is your measure.
Let's see how we do computations under that rule.
Well, we saw earlier that the value of an asset,
it's discounted value now, is equal to its expectation
under the Q-measure of the same random variable at expiration.
So for a call option that says the value of a call option
now is a discount factor times the expectation
under the Q-measure, under letting the paths evolve
according to Ito processes, but where we replace the drift rate
mu by the risk-free rate r.
And we take the expectation of what?
So that's the measure.
What's the function?
The function is the payoff at expiration,
which in the case of a call option
is the larger of S minus k, or 0.
So we make a translation to do Monte Carlo pricing
between exact probability measure averages
to compute exact expectations.
And we do numerical approximations.
So instead of an exact expectation,
we use the sum of our paths.
We're going to take an average.
We're going to generate an ensemble of paths.
They're all going to be equally probable.
We'll compute the terminal value for each path realization
of the derivative of a call option,
and then we'll just take an average of those values.
To get the Q-measure, we use r instead of mu.
For V sub T, what we're going to do
is we're going to generate paths,
and then we're going to read off the value in their final time
step.
And then the discounting factor is just
going to be an e to the minus r times the duration
that we have.
It can be generalized for cases where the interest rates might
be deterministic and time varying,
or even where they might be stochastic.
And if they were stochastic, they
need to stay inside the expectation value.
I've moved them in and out because I'm
assuming the case of constant interest rates.
So what we do is we generate an ensemble of risk-neutral paths.
We use a risk-free rate for the drift.
We use a random number generator so that all of these paths
are equally likely.
We look at the terminal values.
We compute the average of the terminal values,
and then we multiply times a discount factor e
to the minus rT for the length of time that's there.
The paths that we generate are the same
as we did earlier in the class, and we
get some ensemble of Monte Carlo paths, maybe 10,
as I've drawn--
10 or so, as I've drawn here, maybe 1,000, maybe 10,000,
maybe 10 million, depending on what
your patient's computational resources desired
levels of accuracy are.
But here are the kind of results we have.
If I pick particular values for S, for K, for mu,
for T for the risk-free rate, if I
take a simulation for a certain number of time
steps, a certain value dt, a certain number of paths,
I can write my function and see price
as a function of these arguments,
including the simulation parameters, number
of timestamps, number of paths.
And I'll get some numbers out in this particular case
where I ran a simulation, 16.9, 7.05.
Now I'll do a recitation, where we'll
discuss this in more detail.
But right now, we can compare that single run of a Monte
Carlo against the exact values from the Black-Scholes formula.
You certainly can take the values
that we solved for in terms of the five functions,
put it in r, and run a calculation just
in terms of the cumulative distribution functions.
Or you can take this library RQuantLib,
and it has functions already for the Black-Scholes
formulas for European options for calls and puts.
And here we find values that we get, 16.7, 7.2.
So first of all, we see we're generally in the ballpark.
It looks like we're doing something right.
Second, we see we didn't get the exact answer,
so we should ask is that economically significant.
How do we improve the accuracy?
Do we change the number of paths?
Do we change the number of time steps?
Do we need to change our formulation of the problem
that we discretized?
So one of the questions is, how do you adjust your algorithm
in order to improve the accuracy of your Monte Carlo option
pricer?
But the pricer itself couldn't be simpler.
We generate a bunch of paths, look at their terminal values,
just at the terminal values, take an average, discount it,
and we're done.
Very easy, no differential equations involved.
When we think about how these paths behave,
of course, the paths themselves are lognormally distributed,
but the shape of the distribution
is going to depend on the risk-neutral measure, therefore
in the risk-free rate.
It's going to be the same thing for every stock,
with the same volatility, regardless of what mu is.
So the option prices would be the same,
and the ensemble would be the same,
but will generate some set of sample paths
like the ones I showed you.
If we look at the--
and the derivative, because remember,
what we're going to do is not take the underlying,
but we're going to take the terminal
value of the derivative.
So if it's a call option, I take the greater of S minus K or 0,
and those paths look like this.
You notice it's cut off below at 0.
For all the paths that we're finishing
in positive territory above the strike price,
they're all going to be included here.
But an awful lot of paths that hit 0, and stay below 0,
or finish below 0 are going to be cut off at this point
because we don't see anything below 0 for the value of a call
option.
If I look at the histogram of the terminal values, what
I see is a giant spike at 0, a large fraction of the paths
never made it above the strike price, and then
a very asymmetric distribution that's decreasing
as a function of price.
No surprise there.
The higher the value that we would gain,
the farther away from the strike price we are, the less likely
it is to occur.