PROFESSOR: Hello everyone, and welcome to the first recitation
of 15.435x.
My name is JR Scott, and I'm a PhD candidate
in finance at the MIT Sloan School of Management.
I'll be writing the recitations for this course.
In our first recitation, we'll be
reviewing some of the mechanics of forward contracts.
Without further ado, let's begin the recitation.
The recitation consists of three practice problems.
Problems will roughly increase in order of difficulty,
and I hope with each problem you gain a better understanding
of how forward contracts work.
In the first problem, it's stated that Southern California
Edison or SCE, will need to buy 200,000 barrels of oil
in 10 days, and it is worried about fuel costs rising.
Suppose SCE goes long 200 oil forward contracts of the April
contract --
it is currently March --
each for 1,000 barrels of oil at the current forward price
of $50 per barrel.
Suppose forward prices change each day
as follows in the table below.
In Part A, we are asked what is the mark-to-market profit
or loss in dollars the SCE will have on each state?
To me, the best way to begin is to define some notation.
So let's define F sub T to be the forward price for day T
and, N to be the number of barrels of oil
in each forward contract.
Thus the mark-to-market profit or loss,
P/L on each forward contract on date T
is equal to N times the difference between FT and FT
minus 1, where FT minus 1 is the forward price
on the previous day for a long position.
And N times FT minus 1 minus FT for short position.
Now armed with that notation, and letting F sub 0
to be the current forward price of $50,
since SCE has a long position in 204 contracts with a size of N
equals 1,000 barrels for each contract.
We can define SCE's profit or loss on day one
to be 200 times N times the difference between F1 and F0,
which, after plugging in values, equals
200 times 1,000 times 49.75 minus 50,
which is equal to negative $50,000.
In other words SCE makes a mark-to-market loss
of $50,000 on day one.
Similarly on day two, SCE's profit or loss
is 200 times N times F2 minus F1,
which, using the values for F2 and F1 from the initial table,
is equal to 200 times 1,000 times 47.25 minus 49.75,
which is equal to negative $500,000.
Thus we can iterate the above calculation for days 3
through 10 just substituting in the appropriate forward prices
into the formula and we can calculate SCE's daily profit
or loss, which is displayed in the table below.
Part B asks what is SCE's total profit or loss after 10 days?
What we're called at SCE's profit
or loss on its long position in each forward contract
on the first day, is equal to N times F1 minus F0,
and on the second day is equal to N times F2 minus F1.
If we sum these two quantities, we see SCE's profit or loss
after two days, is equal to N times F2 minus F0.
If we iterate this logic forward all the way to day 10,
we see that SCE's profit or loss on each forward contract
after 10 days, is given by N times
the forward price of day 10, minus
the initial forward price, which is F0.
Thus SCE's total profit or loss on its long position in 204
contracts after 10 days is, 200 times N times F10 minus F0,
which is equal to 200 times 1,000 times the difference
between 52.50 and 50, which is $500,000.
In the last part of problem one, Part C, we are asked,
explain why this may not be a perfect hedge for SCE.
Now I can think of a couple of reasons
why the strategy may not be a perfect hedge,
and I encourage you to think of some others on your own.
The first one is that the interest earned on the margin
account was not included in the calculations
that we did and will actually affect SCE's payoff.
The second one -- and this sounds pretty obvious --
is that not all oil is the same.
Oil prices differ based on quality and location,
so that the reference price in this forward contract
may not be perfectly correlated with the cash purchase price
that Southern California Edison faces.