PROFESSOR: Consider a stationary process.
xt is epsilon t plus theta times epsilon t minus 2, where theta
is a constant and epsilon is a 0 mean random variable
with variance sigma squared.
So this is a notation you'll often see in the literature,
and you can be tempted in fact, you can just rescale the sigma
and re express things in terms of a completely standardized
random variable z.
They're just simple linear transformations.
But in this notation, we would typically
write that the expectation is 0, that the variance is sigma
squared, and since the mean is 0 the covariance of epsilon t
and epsilon s is equal to 0 unless t is equal to s.
So when t and s are different we get 0,
and when t and s are equal, we get the previous result.
We sometimes write those in a compact notation
using the Kroncker delta notation,
where that's simply defined here.
This delta t sub s just is something
that's 1 when the indices are equal and it's 0 otherwise.
So here's our question.
Is the series x sub d stationary?
And find the mean, the variance and the autocorrelation
function.
So why don't you pause the video, solve these questions,
and then come back and we'll do it together on the board.
OK.
Let's look at solving this problem.
First of all, is it stationary?
It is a stationary series because we have
expressed things recursively.
If we shift things in time, we still
have the same relative relationship
of the axis across different points in time.
How about computing the mean?
Well the mean we can do just by expectation.
We take expectations it's linear,
so we have that the expectation of x--
this is zero expectation, and this
is theta times 0 expectation, so that's equal to 0.
How about the rest of it?
Well I'm going to simplify things a bit
by letting epsilon t be sigma zt.
And then I'm going to divide through by sigma.
I'm going to keep calling my variable--
I'll call it little x, and then at the end
we can switch variables and we can multiply everything
through by sigma if we'd like.
So I'm going to have the defining equation
that xt is now going to be zt plus theta
times z of t minus 2.
And we've seen that the expectation of xt is 0.
The variance is xt squared, and that's just
the expectation of zt plus theta zt minus 2 quantity squared.
Obviously what's going to happen as we expand this out,
the cross term will have vanishing expectation
because zt and zt minus 2 are necessarily two time steps
apart.
So that's going to vanish, and the final term
we're going to be left with is going
to be expectation of zt squared plus theta squared expectation
of zt minus 2 quantity squared, or in other words
1 plus theta squared.
And if we multiply through by sigma squared,
we'll get the answer to our original question
in terms of big X. Is that what you got?
All right, now let's take a look at the autocorrelation function
and things will get interesting.
So the autocorrelation function, or ACF is defined--
and we're just going to do calculations,
so we're just going to use our definitions.
So our ACF is going to be obtained
by just computing expectation of xt and xt minus k.
Now remember, this is a special case when the means are 0.
More generally what we properly should write
is it's the covariance of xt in xt minus k.
But it's the same as this expectation in the case
where the means are 0, and otherwise
as we know we would subtract off the product
of the expectations.
So what do we do?
Let's just substitute in.
So we have this is going to be the expectation of zt
plus theta zt minus 2--
let's change colors here--
times z of t minus k plus theta of zt minus k minus 2.
Now when we do the expectation, what's going to happen?
Well, we know that zt could be paired with--
it can't be the same as this one,
we're excluding the case where k equals 0.
We've already done that, that's the variance.
So we know the t and t minus k have to be different.
And we know that t minus 2 and t minus 2 minus k
have to be different.
So the term with no thetas and determined theta squared are
both going to have varnishing expectations of the z's.
So we're left with two possible terms.
So we're left with theta times the expectation of z
t minus 2 times z t minus k plus theta times the expectation
of zt with z t minus k minus 2.
Now usually, one comment I should make
is that often we do things only for positive k
and we think going forward.
Formally for stationary series--
and it's a property you can check
and you can show from the definition--
that if we take k to minus k, that the autocovariance
functions are the same.
We often don't think of them that way because we usually
want to think about autocovariance and lag
variables because we expect information
to propagate forward in time, not backward in time.
So there's no time travel rule in finance.
But formally we could have either of these, but what
we can see is if we look at the two expressions,
we can see right away that generally they will vanish
except if k is equal to 2.
If k is equal to 2, then the first expression
will have expectation 1, and otherwise it will vanish.
And in the second term, this one here,
this will generally vanish unless k were equal to minus 2,
in which case this would give me an expectation of 1
and this expectation would vanish.
So either way when we put these together,
what we're going to get is that this is equal to theta
if k is equal to plus or minus 2, and it's equal to 0
otherwise.
And of course, if we want to go back and put in our sigmas,
we would multiply this through by sigma squared.
So the interesting thing about this structure
is that it's only a quadratic term, it's very simple algebra
that we've done.
And because of the way the variables get paired together,
there are only certain combinations
that have a chance of meeting.
So we've reduced something that does involve
lag propagation of time, so there
are things that are moving forward two time steps ahead.
But when we express things in terms of the z's, we
need the z's to be coincident, or the same time index,
and that picks out the terms that are going to be there,
and then the result is just what we
get by doing a little bit of algebra.