PROFESSOR: Let Rt minus mu be equal to minus lambda
times Rt minus 1 minus mu plus sigma zt,
that's the definition of our AR1 process.
Now can you show that this AR1 process can be rewritten
as a moving average process?
Let me give you two hints.
Number one is to use recursion, and number two is to keep
in mind what the goal is, is to express Rt on the left hand
side, and something that doesn't have any R's on the right hand
side that only has z's.
That's a general rule that we have.
They can be of different lags, but there should be only
z's on the right hand side and no R's.
So see if you can do that, come back.
Pause the video, see if you can work it out, and then come back
and we'll look at it together.
So I'm going to simplify notation a little bit for me
by removing some of the scaling, let's
get rid of the mu's and the sigmas and boil things down
so they're a little bit easier to follow.
So I'm going to define a new variable
I'll call y sub t to just be Rt minus mu divided by sigma.
So you notice that this looks like a standardized random
variable, but be careful because the sigma is not necessarily
the variance of R. In fact, we know it's not.
It's the parameter that multiplies z.
So this is just a definition, and in terms
of which I can rewrite my AR1 process of the form yt
is equal to minus lambda yt plus z sub t.
Now what I'm going to do is make a series
of recursive substitutions.
So the first thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to leave this zt right here.
And what I'm going to do-- oops, sorry.
This should be minus 1, very important.
So what I'm going to do-- so this is our expression,
let's just compare it and check.
So what I've done up here is I've divided through by sigma,
and then after dividing through by sigma,
this is y sub t, which is here.
The minus lambda stays, this divided by sigma
is y sub t minus 1, and then zt over here
comes from dividing this term by sigma.
So that's just our previous expression.
What I'm going to do, though, is now
I'm going to take this piece here
and I'm going to take y sub t minus 1
and substitute it in this expression.
So it'll be a little bit more convenient
if I put the z on the left hand side.
So let's do it like this.
I'm going to write down that yt is
equal to zt minus lambda times y t minus 1,
but that's the same thing as zt minus lambda times--
let's change colors.
Now y t minus 1 is just z t minus 1 minus lambda times y
of t minus 2.
That is, this expression here just corresponds to this
by using this entire definition.
That is, if I take t and I replace it by t minus 1,
this becomes t minus 1, this becomes t minus 2,
and that's what I have here.
This is z t minus 1 minus lambda times y of t minus 2.
We simplify, and then we do it again.
So to simplify, this is going to be zt minus lambda times
z t minus 1.
And now I'm going to have plus lambda squared times
y of t minus 2.
Let's substitute in for that y of t minus 2.
This is going to be equal to zt minus lambda z t minus 1
plus lambda squared times z t minus 2 minus lambda of y t
minus 3.
And we can simplify that.
Let's expand that out and you can see the pattern coming.
z t minus 1 plus lambda squared z t minus 2 now minus lambda
cubed times y of t minus 3.
So we're going to keep going, and what's going to happen
is we're going to push the y farther and farther off
to the side.
And there there's one thing that's
important to keep in mind, which is that lambda, remember, must
be less than 1 in absolute magnitude, otherwise
this series blows up.
So we can imagine that as we push y farther and farther
back--
because t minus 3, t minus 4, t minus 5--
each time it's being made smaller and smaller,
not only can we run this recursion infinitely,
assuming we could go infinitely far back,
but any residual term that's left over
is getting smaller, and smaller, and smaller.
So finally, we can write this as an MA series,
but the trick is it's of infinite order.
So what do we get?
We write this out and we can summarize our result.
So we continue going down, and finally what we're left with
is an expression that y sub t can
be written as the sum from k equals 0
to infinity of minus lambda to the kz sub t minus k.
So this is our formal result for this expression.
We know that in practice we're not really
going to be able to do infinite sums,
but we expect that it's going to be a good approximation if we
truncate after a reasonable number of terms
because they're all being suppressed by powers of lambda.
So even if this is a formal expression,
it encodes one thing that's actually quite important,
which is that this is not just an infinite sum
in both directions.
It's a semi-infinite sum into the past.
What that means is that this shows that yt,
because it can be expressed as a sum of all of the previous
z's--
and I've eliminated the previous y's,
so we're back to our original variables,
remember that this is in fact the same thing
as Rt minus mu over sigma.
So we can write this for R sub t as just sigma times yt plus mu.
What this shows is that it depends only
on z's of the same time or earlier.
So in particular, it means that if we
take two different times--
if I were to compute, for example,
the expectation of z sub s with y sub t,
this is going to be 0 whenever t is earlier than s.
So if we pick a point subsequently,
this term here, this sum includes
from our starting point, from lag 0
from t, all the way to the past-- t minus 1, t minus 2,
t minus 3, if we pick something that happens after that it
is necessarily uncorrelated.
And that means-- in coming back to our AR1 model--
that we have an interesting result that's
actually important in doing other derivations.
And now that we've shown it, it should
be intuitively reasonable that whenever
we have crossed terms of this form--
whenever we look at the expectation or the covariance
of one of the z's--
one of the noise terms with one of the excess return pieces,
the Rt minus mu, at a different point in time
this expectation is going to vanish.
These have no covariance.
So intuitively, it makes sense that the noise
is independent of the general variable,
but now here, we can see that as a consequence
of the temporal structure, that we can write the AR1 process
in terms of an MA1 process in the semi-infinite past
or in the infinite past.