PROFESSOR: So let's take a look at another kind of optimization
through what's called the calculus of variations, that
is actually behind ideas like dynamic programming,
even though it doesn't always get credited that way.
And it's a global view and often gets
discretized in things like Bellman's principle
of optimality for dynamic programming.
So here's the idea.
The idea is suppose that we've got some function that's
going to represent a kind of policy, something
that we decide over time.
For concreteness, the examples that we're
going to be looking at are going to involve trading policy.
So imagine that you're a trader.
Your job is to trade a large block of shares.
So you've got 100,000 or a million shares of stock,
and you need to trade them over a given period of time.
So the amount you trade at a given point in time
or the amount perhaps, that you have an inventory in a given
amount of time might be a quantity q,
which is some function of time.
And the idea is how should you vary q
as a function of time in an optimal way.
What are the considerations?
Well, if you dump all your shares at once,
you're going to get a worse price.
Because people will know you're there.
There's not enough liquidity in the market.
If you go really slowly on the other hand,
you'll incur a lot of risk.
So if there are different trade offs,
we can capture those in a function that
involves penalties for the different things that
might go wrong, and ask about solving
for a policy as a function of time.
This is very different from solving for a single scalar
variable at a point.
What we're doing is we're asking about something
that we're varying with respect to a function, a function
of time.
And we want to solve for a function.
So how do you differentiate with respect to a function?
This is a classical problem, and I'd
like to show you a simple example in just
a couple of pictures.
And as I said, we're not going to be using this directly.
But you will see the flavor of this
in some of the applied problems if we look at,
for solutions to the problem of optimal trading.
So the first thing is to consider
that we have a function, q of t, which
is what we're going to control and what we want to solve for.
And we're going to let the Lagrangian now, be
a function of q and of its first time derivative,
which I'll call q dot.
So q dot represents dq/dt.
OK, and we're going to construct a function called the action,
but that's just the name.
It's a S. And we're going to integrate
this function across time.
And we're going to consider S as a function of functions.
So S is a function of different q's.
If you pick a different trajectory, q of t,
stuff it into L, along with a time derivative,
q dot, you'll get a different number.
So what we want to ask is, given a particular functional form
of L. And given an arbitrary function of q, I can compute S.
And I want to know what function q,
gives me the minimum value of S.
So here's how we're going to do it.
First, we're going to characterize our deviations.
How do we average over all possible functions?
Well, here's one way we could do it.
Let's start with the particular q
and look at it as a one parameter family of deviations.
So let's let the alpha just be a parameter scalar
that we can vary.
And we'll say that when alpha is 0,
we have our starting function.
And we're going to vary it in proportion
to some other unknown function, x of t.
So x of t is arbitrary, but what we'd like
is at the endpoints of the integration, when
t is equal to 0 or big T, at the initial or the terminal point,
that this deviation part, alpha xt should vanish.
So for arbitrary alpha, we're changing q
in the direction of the function x.
But we're leaving the endpoints fixed.
Now you could say, well, you just move the problem
from an unknown q into an unknown x.
And that's true, but what we're going to see
is it's not going to depend on which x we pick.
So let's just substitute this informally.
Let's see what we get for our results.
And then we'll apply to a couple of simple examples.
So I'm going to substitute, this expression,
this alpha-dependent expression for q into my integral for S.
And I'm going to say that an optimal solution would
be when the derivative of S with respect to alpha varnishes.
That is, at least over this particular direction
for varying q, I'm varying q in the direction
of a particular deviation x of t--
It's a time-dependent function.
I don't know what it is.
But certainly, if this is going to be stationary,
if it's going to be a critical point, then as I very alpha,
this should be equal to 0.
So I'm going to take dS d alpha.
And I'm going to apply the ordinary chain rule.
That's going to be partial of L with respect
to q times partial of q with respect to alpha, plus it also
depends q dot, partial of L with respect to q dot,
times partial of q dot with respect to alpha.
And the whole thing is integrated dt.
And in more general cases, L might be more complex.
And sometimes it's given an explicit time dependence.
We're just going to look at this simple form.
It's just a function of q and q dot.
And we're q and q dot as being independent for the moment.
Now, let's substitute.
We know that the partial of u with respect to alpha.
Here's q.
So I take the partial with respect to alpha.
It's just x of t.
So this first line, I have partial L with respect
to q times dq d alpha, is just partial
of L with respect to q times x.
And in the second term, the partial of q
dot with respect to alpha, well, q dot is dq/dt.
So the partial is just going to be dx/dt.
It's going to be the derivative of x with respect to time,
times this part is unchanged that's in front.
Now let's do an integration by parts.
Let's take the second term, integrate by parts,
and move the t derivative over to the left-hand side.
So instead of t acting on x, I'm going
to get d by dt acting on the first term.
As usual, when I do integration by parts, I have a minus sign.
And I have a boundary term I need
to consider as well, which has this form-- partial of L
with respect q dot times x, evaluated
at the end point the integral, t equals big T to t equals 0.
Now the boundary term for my integration by parts
vanishes, because x vanishes when t
is that either the end points.
That's the condition I add here.
And now this term the remains has
the quantity in square brackets, all multiplied times x of t.
Integrated dt is equal to 0, and in this equation,
has to hold for any function, x of t
that you might choose to consider.
Well, the only way that can be true for any x of t
is if the quantity of square brackets vanishes.
And that gives us what are called
Euler-Lagrange equations.
So the Euler Lagrange equations satisfy the condition
that the action is stationary when q is such
that it satisfies this equation-- partial of L
with respect to q minus the derivative with respect
to time, the total derivative with respect
to time with the partial of L with respect
to q dot needs to vanish.
And this is well known to people who've
studied classical mechanics.
For example, this gives a different way
of formulating Newton's second law, F equals Ma,
force is equal to mass times acceleration.
Here's how we do it.
We take a look at constructing Lagrange here.
We think of q as representing the position of a particle,
q dot is representing its velocity.
And q double dot, the second derivative with respect
to time, as representing the acceleration.
Here is our functional form for L. It looks like the energy.
We'll that V be the potential energy.
But notice, this term looks like kinetic energy--
1/2 m q dot squared, minus some function of q
that's independent of q dot.
If this were the energy, there would be a plus sign here.
And it has a minus sign.
In any event, if you're not familiar with this
in classical mechanics, just take it
as a particular functional example.
Let's apply the rules.
Partial of L with respect to q dot is going to be just--
this is the only term with the q dot in it.
It's going to be m times q dot.
Partial of L with respect to q it's
going to give me minus derivative of V
with respect to q.
And that tells us, when I substitute it
into this equation, that m q dot, which is mass times
acceleration, is minus the prime of q,
which in classical mechanics, is equal to the force.
Specifically, if we take a problem where V of q
is quadratic in q, this represents a harmonic
oscillator.
We have that the force is minus kq.
It represents restoring force.
If q gets large and positive, the force
is in the negative direction.
And I'm going to get this very concrete differential equation
and q double dot minus kq.
And the solutions to this are sines and cosines,
which you can check, satisfy the equation, with the frequency
given by square root of k/m where k and m are
primary for the problem.
K showed up in the potential, V. M showed up
in our original Lagrange function here, as m.
So that's an example as to how we
can get a differential equation out of this general principle.
But what it tells us is not just this
is how a harmonic oscillator behaves.
It tells us that of all possible things that a harmonic
oscillator could do, not the ones that actually does,
all the things that could do, the correct solution--
the one the Newton tells us is the right solution--
also happens to be the one that minimizes
this interesting integral here.
So it turns out that while Newton's equations
are pretty good, that we can generalize this principle
to many, many more problems than the specific differential
equations that Newton came up with.
Here's another example.
This is from the paper from Almgren and Chriss
that we'll look at more, which is
about optimal ways of dividing a trading solution.
Their key idea is to take a look at penalizing both trading
fast, because of the high market impact that
would be incurred if you try to trade
a large block of shares too quickly, and inventory risk--
that is if you hang on to your shares for too long,
there's market risk that they might change in value.
Now in their solution, they end up
with something which is discrete.
They do a multi-period problem.
But if we were to take the continuous time limit,
we could replace their discrete sum
by the integral that would have this general form, which
looks an awful lot like the harmonic oscillators solution
we just saw that looks like Newton's equations.
So they have a term in delta q, which represents
the change in the quantity.
It represents the speed of trading.
And they have a term that ends on q squared, which depends
on the quantity that's left.
So we see we have an action term in this interval.
We have something that depends on q dot squared,
something that depends on q squared,
just as we did in our example from Newtonian mechanics.
So it's very similar, except that the harmonic oscillator
would have the wrong sign.
This would be a repulsive force.
So it wouldn't be a very sensible for a harmonic
oscillator.
But the mathematics goes through almost the same way.
The difference is that the solutions instead
of being sines and cosines, are exponential with a plus
or minus sign.
And when we impose boundary conditions,
we find a particular linear combination of them
that involves a plus sign an a minus sign in this form that
involves hyperbolic functions.
But it's basically a linear combination
of the two solutions.
So in this picture, we have a problem
that was formulated initially as a recursive problem, very
discretely, about what happens over small periods of time.
But we have a trade-off between the desire
to minimize risk and improve speed at a short distance,
with a global problem where we need an optimal global solution
that might not necessarily be an iterated set
of myopic, short-term solutions.
And the calculus of variations tells us how to do that.
It says solve the entire trajectory all at once.
And these are examples of what those solutions look like.