PROFESSOR: Dynamic programming is
the name given to a set of techniques
that help us recursively formulate an optimal solution
to a multi-period problem.
When we looked at our initial portfolio optimization problem,
for example, we looked at it as a single period problem.
But often we have multiple problems.
And it may be the case that the solution
to the multiple problem is not just
a sequence of short-term solutions
to one period problems.
So the idea is that's due to Bellman
and draws on a lot of classical mathematics
that's much earlier, is to think about a sequence of decisions.
And we'd like to minimize some overall objective function
by the time we've completed our assigned task, which
could be on a finite horizon.
As it often is, it might be an indefinite task that goes on.
And then we need to minimize the long range running average.
The observation that's key for dynamic programming
is that we can set up problems recursively
so that in each time period, the decision that
needs to be made, based on the information
set and the state variables where we currently are
and the problem to be solved over the remaining
period of time has the same structural form in each time
period.
So that as we evolve forward in time,
we get to solve the same problem again and again and again.
And a typical solution to that is
obtained by starting at the end where
we have to complete our task and working our way backwards,
taking advantage of this common structure in each time period.
We might think of this applying this is to problem say,
in portfolio re-balancing.
We might have a particular period
where we set up an optimal portfolio,
say for the next month or the next quarter.
At the end of the quarter, we find out
that our portfolio is no longer optimal.
Either our forecasts have changed for future expected
returns and variances.
Or simply, the market prices have moved.
And our weight allocations aren't where
they were initially.
So should we re-balance while there are
costs associated with doing so?
And should we have known better?
Maybe if we knew that the costs were going to move,
we could have taken that into account ahead of time
and managed our positions a bit better so
that we don't incur repeated transaction costs where we're
constantly catching up if some of that
might have been foreseeable.
So what we'd like to do is have a balance
between these short term decisions, where
we could re-optimize step by step in a global perspective.
What we really want to solve is the optimal long term problem.
We're particularly interested in the case
with a solution to the global problem
might differ from taking a short term perspective.
So here's a simple example.
Suppose I have a grid and I want to start at one point
and finish at another.
I want to start at the green point.
I want to finish the red point.
And let's assume that I'm allowed to move along the grid
and I would like to find the path of minimum length.
And in fact, it might not be unique.
So let's see if we could find the number of minimum length
paths that are available on this graph.
And we'd like to do it with a recursive setup.
It's typical of the way in which we'll
set up our dynamic programming problems.
Now let's assume that because we want
to get from S to F, that we probably don't want
paths to retrace our steps.
So let's assume just to simplify that, we're
going to require our paths either to go up or do
the right, that there's not going to be
any backtracking involved.
And you can show of course, it's not hard
in this case see that that should be true.
So how do we set this up/ Well, first of all,
we'd like to think of a one-step relationship that at any given
node on this graph, given by coordinates i and j,
the number of paths to reach that node say a point here--
let's see if we can get our pointer--
our point here let's say, is equal to the number of paths
that enter from below plus the number that
enter from the left.
So there are two ways that we could get to a given point.
So however many ways that we're here, these paths
could all move into the node over here.
And I can get to this point by coming from the left
or by coming up from below.
So that's characterized here as a number of paths
into a given point, is the number
that come from below plus the number that come from the left.
Next we have a boundary condition.
So on the edges of the graph, defined
by my starting and ending points,
there's only one way to get there.
That is by not allowing backtracking.
So if on the left edge, I just came up from below-- not
allowed to come from above from anywhere else,
and similarly on the left-hand side
and on the top of the graph.
So these provide boundary conditions.
So here's the procedure that we have to solve.
First, let's label each boundary node with a 1.
Because there's only one way to get there.
So each of these points has only one path
from the start to get there.
Because they're on the boundaries.
I can only go up, or I can move to the right.
I'm not allowed to go down.
I'm not allowed to go to the left.
So these have only one point to get.
There then for each interior node,
as I move into the interior, I assign
to each node the sum of the values that come from the point
to the left and from the point below.
And as I fill in the graph in this way,
I can find what the total number of paths
is that lead to my terminal point.
And in this case, it's equal to 15.
Here's another example.
Suppose that we want to go from the top of this graph
down to the bottom.
And we can take a path.
At each point, we can move either to the left or the right
as we move down.
Each node is associated with a number.
And like a typical game of this type,
let's assume that we collect a score that's
associated with the number of points on each node.
So let's assume that we have a path that as we traverse
it and go down, we are entitled to collect
the sum of the points along the different nodes
that we encounter.
So here's your chance.
Why don't you pause the video right here,
and see if you can find what's the optimal number that you can
find going from top to bottom.
What's the largest sum that you can find in parts where
you add up the values that you encounter
as you move from top to bottom?