PROFESSOR: Well, one way we could do
it is with a greedy algorithm.
A greedy algorithm is one where we do what's optimally local.
We take a look at the next time step
and we pick the best value.
So for example, I would start at 9.
My choices are to go either to 2 or to 3.
3 is bigger.
So I'm going to take 3.
My next choice, given that I'm at 3,
is I can either get 8 or 10.
I'm going to take 10.
From 10, my choices are 1 or 5.
And I'm going to take 5.
And, here, my final choice is between 11 or 12.
And I'll take 12.
And my sum is equal to 39.
So did you get something higher or lower?
If you got something equal or lower,
take a moment to see if you could do even better.
Pause the video and see what you can find.
There is a better solution.
Let's try this.
Let's take a look now and build in our graph
a set of interior values where we'll start from the top.
Let's at each point on the top--
from the top going down--
let's add each node that we might
be able to encounter the sum of the values
that we would reach if we got to that node.
So you can see that if we're at this point over here,
we would have had 9 plus 3 in the original graph.
If we were to have made this choice,
we would have ended up with 11.
So by proceeding in this way, where we take each node
and we add all the values above that would have led to reaching
this node for getting here the best choice,
we can build a tree with a set of nodes
that represent the best choices we could
have gotten as we go down here.
And then when we reach the terminal values,
we pick the ones that's the best.
And here's one that says 42.
To find out how to get 42, we reclimb the tree.
We say, well, the way we got to 42 was coming from this place
here where we added 11 to get there and then from this point
here where we would have added points
to get there taking this 11 and all the way back up.
And what you'll notice is not only
is 42, special number as being the ultimate answer--
it's bigger than 39.
But, also, you'll notice that what
happened is we did some things that
were suboptimal locally but still were optimal globally.
That is, when we came to this point here at 3,
we chose to go for 8 in this solution,
whereas before we went for 10, which would
have been the greedy solution.
Once we were over here in 10, we no longer
had access to some better solutions.
So this is typical.
We often might take things that are short-term optimal that
lead us to no longer having access
to states that might be much more profitable in the future.
So we'd like to have a systematic way
to avoid that happening and to make sure
that we end up with a globally optimal solution.
But there are a number of aspects
that are common to dynamical programming problems.
And these also show up in modern machine learning methods
as well.
First, we have state variables that tell us how things behave
and where we are given a particular set of evolution
in a particular place.
Usually, at a given point in time
or a given point in our process, we
have a number of actions we can take,
a number of control variables that we have under our control,
such as the number of shares that we might choose to trade.
There are stochastic factors that are involved.
We're typically looking at Markov processes that
are evolving in time so that because they're Markov,
we only need to know the current state
variables not how we got here.
But that doesn't mean we're safe from being trapped or having
different actions cut out from us.
We need to be able to reach things in the future.
The effects of the actions in the environment
might be fully known.
Typically, they are in dynamical programming problems.
That is, we know how the environment works.
We have a complete model for the environment.
Many realistic cases, and certainly in financial markets,
that's not necessarily true.
And methods like reinforcement learning
are able to generalize and deal with cases
where we may have only incomplete information
or a probabilistic understanding of what happens in the future.
And we have boundary conditions.
And, typically, these are terminal conditions
that we have, and they permit us to work backwards.
We often have rewards that are associated
with the optimal value.
We'd like to maximize our rewards.
We would like to minimize our costs.
So there may be penalty functions
for taking suboptimal actions.
And there may be discounting.
That is, in the same way that we discount present value
in accounting and in finance, we might
discount the value of a future reward
relative to an immediate reward.
We might say that a reward that takes place far in the future
is less valuable, not equally valuable,
to a reward in the next time period.
That's a trade-off between long-term and short-term costs.
It might say that if we need to defer gratification
to get a reward sometime in the far future,
it should be a bigger reward.
But those are problems that we could
choose to include or not include in our specification
of the problem.
And what we're looking for is an optimal policy.
That is, we're looking for a set of rules that tell us
in any situation we might find in the future
with any given set of state variables
at a given point in time what is the best
action we should take at that time to move us forward.
And those actions do two things.
One of them is they might get us immediate rewards.
But they also position our state variables such
that we have access to future rewards as well.
The general kind of problem that we're trying to solve
could be formulated like this.
And I'll leave out the notation and some of the jargon.
Let's imagine that we start in a particular state.
Let's call it state 0.
So we've got something in our environment.
We then take an action.
And that action earns a reward, which we can keep.
And we find ourselves in a different state.
That is, we may have had some impact on our environment.
When we looked at examples before
of say algorithmic trading, we assumed
that the markets were the same after we participated
in them as when we came.
But that's often not the case and certainly not
for significant financial transactions
and for significant financial intermediaries.
So let's assume that our action did change the world.
And now we have to deal with the world that's been changed.
And that's part of the problem that we need to solve.
We then take a new action.
It earns a new reward.
And it puts us in another state.
And these are going to be iterated forward.
And we want to solve for the best policy.
And the complications that we may have
are that the evolution might be stochastic.
That is, maybe we don't exactly know
what state we'll end up with.
Maybe the best we have is a probability distribution
telling us what state we would end up in next.
Maybe the rewards are stochastic.
Maybe we don't know what the return
is we receive on an investment.
But we only understand-- we're only given it's probability
distribution.
Maybe the environment itself is unknown,
and maybe the optimal policy to deal with that environment
is unknown as well.
Maybe at certain points in time we should flip a coin
and randomize our own decisions.
So all of these are things that we
might consider as being within the scope of solving
for finding an optimal policy.
And let's take a look at some applications
where we can start very concrete and then look at expanding out
and think about different places where they might be applied.
Needless to say, this is a very big topic.
And we're just going to introduce it, show
what some of the thought processes
are, what some of the characteristics
are that show up in typical problems,
and see where they might be helpful, reformulating them
for solving different kinds of financial problems.