PROFESSOR: Let's look at two approaches
to the question of optimal trading, where
we'd like to minimize execution costs in a trading
setting, where we need to deal with randomness, and possibly
market impact.
First solution, the dynamic programming solution,
is described by Bertsimas and Lo.
So here is the question.
We have fixed quantity of shares-- let's call it big Q--
that we need to buy in a particular period of time
or a horizon, t.
And the optimal trading policy is
to find the best sequence of trades that satisfies
the boundary conditions.
So what we'd like to do is we need the set of trades.
Let qt be the trade quantity at each period.
And I have t periods.
So the sum of q sub t from one to big T
needs to add up to the total number of shares.
And what we'd like to do is minimize the cost
when we bought, and this is the market value.
So you notice the qt is going to vary in each time period.
And we have control over the q's, but we do not
have control over the prices.
Those are in the market, and those
may be subject to random fluctuations,
and they may be subject to feedback effects
from our trading.
But here the objective is to minimize this function subject
to this constraint.
So in each trade period, we'll model the price process
as being arithmetic Brownian motion,
so rather than log normal motion.
And that's so that we can solve the problem analytically.
But also, these typical trading problems, the overall time
horizons are fairly short.
They might be a matter of days.
And this is not a terrible model for price movements.
So here's our model for the price movement.
This is price, not return.
The price in period t is the previous price
plus our random increment, that's going to be 0 mean,
and a term that depends on the amount that we traded.
So this is a market impact term.
We're going to assume it's proportional to the size.
So theta is a coefficient.
And this says that if we make a trade if we're buying,
and we buy a large quantity, the price
goes up by a large amount.
Now you might think that that's good.
Your trades became more valuable.
But what's happened is the price went here
after you executed your trade and makes your future trades
even more expensive.
So we're going to hold theta fixed.
And we're going to assume that this is a linear function.
And we'll see that's actually pretty conservative.
In the real world, transaction costs
tend to be for large quantities, a faster varying function,
possibly quadratic as a function of q.
But for purposes of this model, this is nice.
It's easy to describe.
And it's easy to solve.
So epsilon is going to be a 0 mean process.
And we want to think about which of the variables we control
and which are the ones we have to observe in the environment.
So p is the price.
And we unfortunately cannot determine the prices.
We have to take the prices we get.
So we can observe them, and they're
going to have a random component.
The other state variable is the number of shares
that we have remaining.
And we'll designate that by W. W is
going to be the total quantity at time t,
minus the number of shares that have been done previously.
So this decrements the number of shares.
W is the inventory.
It's the number of shares that we have remaining.
So at a given point in time at a point t,
we have two things that describe the state.
What's the current price?
How many shares do we have left to trade?
And this is a Markov decision process.
It's in the family decision problems,
where the future decisions depend
only on what the current state variables are,
not on the history for how we got there.
Q is a control variable.
We get to pick.
At least we get some control over something.
And what we get to do is choose a sequence
of q's to find the optimal sequence
to minimize our overall result for the overall transaction
costs.
So our goal is to find a sequence
of cues that minimize the cost.
And this is a policy.
So the optimal policy is the one that minimizes
the total expected cost.
The dynamic programming principle
says let's frame our decisions as a recursive set of problems,
so that the optimal decision and the optimal sequence
at each step is also optimal for all the remaining shares.
So if we can have a set of sub-problems, each of which
is of the same structure, then when we solve one,
we can solve them all and recurse our way back
from a definite point, usually the terminal point,
back to the beginning, and find the optimal solution.
So the optimal policy satisfies this.
Now we are going to solve it from the end.
But we need to frame each decision with respect
to uncertainty that occurs in the future.
So in one step what we would say is that our value function is
going to be given the prices available through t minus 1,
and given the number of shares we
have available that we need to move W sub t.
Having completed all the trades through q of t minus 1,
we want to minimize over all possible trades
in the next period, the expected value of our final cost.
And that's going to be equal to the trade in the next period,
qt, whatever it is, times the price in the next period,
plus whatever is left over after we do our next trade.
And that's going to be whatever is left over having not
done this at time t plus 1 for the next period,
involving a new price.
The new starting price will be p sub t.
And The new starting quantity is W of t plus 1.
But these quantities are unknown at this point,
because we haven't picked a q yet.
And that's why these are all inside the expectation value.
And the expectation value is taken at time t.
So I have a recursive problem, where I don't know what V is.
But I have the same unknown function on the left
and on the right.
It's in the expected value on the right,
because these are future values.
Over here, these are taken at present values,
which are taken to be known.
I know what the last observed price is.
I know what the inventory remaining is.
And I'm going to minimize with respect to my control variable,
the average over all possible outcomes for what the price
the expected future price might be,
so that I can minimize the expected total cost of trading.
So we can't solve this, because it's
got a V on the left and a V on the right.
But what we can do is we can set it up recursively and work
our way backwards from a known point back to the beginning.
So the easy place to start is at the end.
And the reason it's easy at the end
is in our very last trading period, we have no choice.
Whatever we've got left, we have to sell.
That's the importance of the terminal condition.
And we've seen that in many other settings
for boundary value problems that we've done.
If you know the terminal conditions,
it helps fix many other aspects of the problem.
So if you get your last period and you've
got some shares left over you haven't traded yet,
you've got to trade them.
So that is not a random variable.
In the final period left, we need
to trade the number of shares remaining.
So therefore, the terminal condition at time t
is that this expectation where we're
going to minimize the final price
and there's not going to be anything left over,
because there won't be any additional quantity,
is going to be the expectation over qt times the final price.
And that's something that we can write down
this way in terms of our price process.
So this piece is from our equation
for how the price evolves.
And there's no more V because we're in the final period.
There is nothing left over.
Everything has been liquidated at this point.
So let's take expectations of this.
That's pretty easy.
Where is our random variable?
Well, there's a random variable here in terms of epsilon.
Everything else is actually known.
We know the previous price.
And we know we know what q sub t is when
we're in that final period.
So we're going to get the expectation
is going to be qt times the previous price plus theta times
q sub t.
We don't minimize with respect to qt,
because we don't have any choice.
It's fixed.
We have to dump all the shares we have left.
So in the final period we can re express this
as a function of W, because Wt and qt are the same thing.
And we've got this expression, that our value
for the final period is going to be
W sub t times the price plus theta times Wt.
And this is a quadratic function of Wt.
And it's a linear function in the price.
So no more expectations, no minimizations.
This is an explicit formula for V
in terms of the state variables, p and W.
That's what we mean by describing the state in terms
of a value function.
What about one period previously?
In the next to last period, we can take this result
and substitute it into our recursion.
So our recursion-- we're going to put this result
from the previous slide, which is
a definite, non-stochastic form of known form.
We're going to put that function in,
and here it is in closed form.
And now we're going to think about this,
where we haven't yet realized the next to last trade.
So we'd like to solve for what is qt minus 1
in order to minimize the expected cost.
Well, the expected cost of our total trading program
is going to be the cost in the next to last period
plus whatever the cost is in the final period that's dumping
whatever shares are there.
The reason we have expectations now,
compared to the previous case, is
we haven't done yet, our next to last trade.
We have some choice.
That is we're going to pick q some t minus 1.
That's going to affect the final period.
So whatever is left over, we have to pick.
But this is in the next to last period.
It's the last discretionary choice that we have to make.
So that's OK.
Let's just expand things out.
And inside the expectation, we now
can write this out in terms of our known variables
with this expression.
And then, what are we going to do with this expression?
Well, we're going to compute the expectation.
We're going to minimize the result for all possible values
of q or control variable.
And then we're going to re express things
in terms of the state variables as they
were known at time t minus 1.
And then we're going to do this again and again
and again until we get back to the beginning.