PROFESSOR: Now let's draw the payoff diagram that
corresponds to this payoff.
So let's start with when s1 equals to 0.
So, when s1 equals to 0, we get our payoff is $200.
Now, if s1 ends up being $90, our payoff,
according to this expression, is going to be 200 minus 2
times 90, which is 180.
So 200 minus 180 would be $20.
So, therefore, we're getting $20 if the stock price ends up
being $90.
So, therefore, this would be the first part of this diagram
where we get this line.
So, because we have minus 2 s1 here, so the raise here
and, therefore, the slope of this line is 2.
Now so this is the first part.
Now, if s1 is above 90 but below 110--
let's put 110 here--
then our payoff is going to be 110 minus s1.
So, if s1 is just exactly 90, so this function is still--
would equal to 20.
So, therefore, we don't have any breaks here.
So we're going to start exactly at this point.
And then, if s1 goes all the way to 110,
then this payoff, this function, is going to be equal to 0.
So, therefore, the second part here
is just the straight line that connects these two points.
And then, of course, if the stock price
ends up being above 110, we get zero payoff here.
And so here, because we get 110 minus s1,
the slope of this line is negative 45 degrees.
And so there is here just 1.
So, therefore, this is how the total payoff
from this portfolio would look like.
So we get a steep line that starts at 200.
It goes down to 20 when s1 equals to 90.
Then it becomes less steep, and it goes to 110.
And then it becomes 0.
And, intuitively, of course, so the steepness here
comes from the fact that both of these options
expire in the money.
And, therefore, this is the payoff that we get.
So, once we cross the $90 threshold,
the first option expires out of the money,
and, therefore, we get nothing from it.
And we still get the payoff from the second option,
and this is its payoff.
And, when s1 goes above 110, we get zero payoff
from these two put options.
So, therefore, this is how the diagram
for this particular portfolio would look like.
Now let's consider the following.
So let's assume that you're an investor,
and you're buying one put option with a strike price of $90
and one put option with a strike price of $110.
What would be your payoff in this case?
Let's follow the same approach as we've done
in part a of this question.
I will write down the mathematical expressions
for the payoffs from these two put options,
and then I will mathematically add them up.
And then I will draw the diagram that corresponds
to this particular portfolio.
So let's start with the first put option.
So this put option has strike price of $90.
So, therefore, it pays off 90 minus s1 if s1 is below 90.
If s1 ends up being above 90, this option
expires out of the money, and it pays off 0.
Similar, for the second put option,
we get 110 minus s1 if s1 ends up
being below 110, which is the strike price, and 0 otherwise.
So what I will do right now is that I will mathematically
add up these two expressions.
So what we will end up having is that let's
first kind of mentally break down the domain of s1
into three pieces.
So it's above 110, between 90 and 110, and below 90.
So what happens if the stock price ends up being above $110?
Well, then, in this case, both of these options
expire out of the money, and our aggregate payoff
from both of these options is just 0.
So we get 0 if s1 is above $110.
Now what happens if s1 ends up being between 90 and 110?
Well, in this case, the first option still expires out
of the money, and exercising it becomes not optimal,
but the second option actually expires in the money.
And, therefore, we're exercising it,
and we're getting 110 minus s1 as the payoff from this option.
So, therefore, we get 0 plus 110 minus s1 or 110 minus s1
if s1 one ends up being above 90, but below 110.
And now, if the stock price ends up being below 90,
then, in this case, both of these options
expire in the money.
And our payoff becomes 90 minus s1 plus 110 minus s1.
So, adding these two up, we get 200 minus 2 s1
if s1 ends up being below 90.
So this is the combined payoff from holding these two options.
So we get 200 minus 2 s1 if the stock price is below 90.
We get 110 minus s1 if the stock price is between 90 and 110.
And we get 0 if the stock price is above 110.