PROFESSOR: All right, so this is our portfolio of the options
that we think should represent this payoff.
Let's verify that.
So, for each of these options, I've written down the payoff.
So I'm starting from the bottom, so long four
puts with a strike price of 10.
This is their payoffs.
So, four of these options, each of them,
the payoff is 10 minus s because this is a put option,
and we'll long it.
And so this happens when the stock price
is between 0 and 10.
And, if the stock price is above 10, the payoff from these puts
would be 0.
Now then we are short one put with a strike price of 20.
So, therefore, it's negative 20 minus s.
So this is just the payoff from being short one put.
And we get this, if the share price is between 0 and 20,
and 0 otherwise.
Then, next, we'll long three puts with a strike price of 30.
So the payoff is 3 times 30 minus
s if the share price ends up being between 0 and 30, and 0
otherwise.
And, finally, we have two long call options.
And we get 0 if the share price is between 0 and 40.
So these calls have strike of 40.
And we get 2 times s minus 40. s minus 40
is the payoff from each individual call option.
And so we have two of them.
So it's 2 times s minus 40 if the share price ends up
being above the strike price of $40.
So all we need to do is that we need to add up these, again,
piecewise functions and make sure that what we have here
is exactly what we have here in the green color.
So let's do that.
I will start to add up these four functions
by assuming that s is above 40, and then I
will go into these domains--
30 to 40, 20 to 30, 10 to 20, and 0 to 10.
So, if the stock price is above 40, we only get 2 times
s minus 40 right here, and we get 0 from the other three
types of options.
So, for this particular case, if s is above 40,
we get 2s minus 80 as our payoff.
And you can see that we're off to a good start
because this actually matches to what
was given to us in this problem in the very beginning.
Now what is our payoff if the stock
price is between 30 and 40?
So you could see that the option at the bottom
pays nothing because, if it's 30 to 40, we get 0 here.
And all of these other options, if s
is above 30, 20, and 10, so they also give us $0.
So, in this part of the share price domain, so 30 to 40,
we get $0 payoff.
And, again, it matches to what we were
given in the very beginning.
Now, if the share price is between 20 and 30,
we get nothing from the bottom option,
but we do get something from this third type of options.
And we get nothing from the other two.
So, if the share price is above 20
and above 10 and, in our domain, 20 to 30,
so these options give us 0.
This option gives us 0 as well, but this gives us something.
So it gives us 3 times 30 minus s.
And so, together, we get-- so this is 90 minus 3s.
And, again, so this matches to what
we were given here as well.
Now what about in the 10 to 20 range?
So the share price is between 10 and 20.
We get the payoff from this second type of options
and, actually, the third and the second one as well.
So we get negative 20 minus s.
Plus we get 3 times 30 minus s.
So let's put this together-- so negative
20 minus s plus 3 times 30 minus s.
So, if I were to add this up, I get so minus 20 plus 90.
So this is 70.
And then I get minus 3s plus s.
So this is minus 2s.
And so then, in this domain, because this type of options
pays off something, and this type of options
pays something off as well, so, in this range of 10 to 20,
we get 70 minus 2s.
Now, if we compare this to what we're given in this question,
it's going to, again, match precisely what we're given.
So here, from this collection of options
in this particular range, we get exactly the same payoff
as the function that we were given in the very beginning.
Finally-- and I will continue writing here.
So in this domain of--
so, when s is between 0 and 10, what we get
is that the first three type of options.
So you can see that we get some payoff from the first one,
we get something from the second one,
and we get something from the third one as well.
So we have to add up this, this, and that.
And this would be our payoff in this particular domain.
So we get 40 minus 4s, 4s.
Then we get negative minus 20 plus s.
And then we get 90 minus 3s.
And so we're going to-- if we're going to add this up, so 40
minus 20 plus 90, this is 110.
And we get negative 4s plus s minus 3s.
So this is minus 6s.
And so this will match, again, exactly what
we're given in the problem.
So, in this range, when s is between 0 and 10,
this collection of options give us 110 minus 6s.
So, therefore, what we've just proven here
by doing this exercise, we've proven
that the collection-- the portfolio
of these options and these positions and these options,
so long two calls at $40, long three puts at $30,
short one put at $20 strike price, and long four puts
at $10, so this portfolio of options
gave us exactly this payoff.