PROFESSOR: In this question, I will teach you
how to draw payoff diagrams and understand
the payoffs of a portfolio of different options.
This is a very useful application.
So let's consider the following example.
We have a stock, ABC.
Its current price is $90.
And then we have four one-year options.
Two of them are put options, and the remaining two
are call options.
The two put options have strikes $90 and $110.
And two call options have the same strikes, $90 and $110.
The first question asks us to draw
a payoff diagram for two puts and one bond
with a face value of $20.
So think of-- see yourself as an investor who
buys these two puts with a strike of $90 and one bond
with a face value of $20.
Now what your payoff diagram would
look like in one year from now when these two puts expire?
Now let's first start with understanding
how the payoff from buying two put options with a strike
price of $90 would look like.
Recall that the payoff diagram from buying just one
put option with a strike price of $90
is going to look like this.
So we have a positive line that goes
at a negative 45-degree angle from 90 to 90,
and the payoff function looks like this.
So it's 90 minus s1.
s1 is the price of the underlying asset--
in this case, it's a stock--
at the expiry date, which is one year from now.
So, therefore, I denote it by just s1.
Recall that the current price of the stock
has nothing to do with this payoff diagram.
It's relevant, of course, for the pricing of the option,
but it's irrelevant for what would
be our payoff from buying this one put
and holding onto it for one year.
So this is just one put option.
Now what's going to be-- if we're
going to be buying two put options,
what would our payoff diagram look like?
Well, one way to figure this out is just
to mathematically multiply this payoff
that we get from one put option by 2
because, if we are buying two put options, therefore,
we would get twice the payoff.
So multiplying this by 2 would give us the following.
So the first part would be just 90 minus s1 multiplied by 2.
So it'll be 180 minus 2 s1--
and this is for the case when the share price ends up
being below 90, and, therefore, exercise becomes optimal--
or 0 otherwise if the share price ends up being higher
than the strike price.
Now, this is how, mathematically,
the payoff from buying two put options would look like.
And, graphically, if we were to graph this,
it would be just the line that starts, if s1 is 0,
this would be-- this function would be 180.
So it's the line that starts at 180.
It has a negative 2 slope, and it goes all the way down to 0.
So, if s1 equals to 90, this expression is 0.
So, 180 and 90 here, that's a straight line.
And then it goes at 0 if the share price ends up
being above $90.
So this raise here is 2, as opposed to,
when we have one put option here, it is just 1.
Now we can extend this and just generalize.
So, if we had three put options, we would get 270,
and this line would start at 270.
And it's going to go to 90 and then continue
being just a flat line at 0.
And any other number of put options
would just go all the way up, and we're
going to start at that.
For example, 10 put options is going to start at 900.
It's going to go down to 90.
And then it's going to be a zero line.
Once we figured out how the payoff
diagram from buying two puts looks like,
let's bring the bond back in.
So now this is the payoff that we get from buying a bond.
If we buy a bond that has a face value of $20,
it means that it pays off $20 to us at the end of year one.
We'll assume that it has one year to maturity, no coupon
payments.
So it's a zero coupon, $20 face-value bond.
So it pays $20 at the end of year one,
and it gives us this $20, irrespective of the price
of stock ABC in year one.
So, for any s1, this is just going to be 20.
So it's a flat line at 20.
So now we're constructing this portfolio
by buying these two puts and this one bond.
So, therefore, we need to add up this diagram with this diagram.
The easiest way to do that is to, first, start
mathematically, just looking at the mathematical expressions
for the payoff for the bond and payoff for the two
puts, and add them up.
So this is the payoff for the bond.
This is payoff for the two puts.
If we add them up, we are adding 20
and plus 180 minus 2 s1 if s1 is less than 90.
So this is going to be 200 minus 2 s1 for s1
less or equal than 90.
And, if s1 is above 90, it's going to be 20 plus 0.
So is going to be 20.
So, therefore, the combined payoff
from buying two puts and this bond
is going to be 200 minus 2 s1, if s1
is less than or equal to 90, and 20 if s1 is above 90.
Now so this is a mathematical expression.
All we have to do right now is to plot it.
Well, we can simply plot it just kind of piecewise
by starting at, for example, if s1 equals to 0,
then this payoff is going to be 200.
And, if s1 goes all the way to 90,
it means this payoff is going to be 200 minus 2 times 90.
This is 180.
So this will be just $20, somewhere here,
so at 20 and 90.
And then, all the way, if s1 ends up being above $90,
so this payoff is going to be $20 as well.
So it's $20 from here, from 90 and above, and starts at 200
and goes down to 90.
So this is the payoff diagram from buying two puts
with a strike price of $90 and buying one bond with a face
value of $20.