PROFESSOR: Now, next, let's construct a payoff diagram
from the following portfolio.
We're going to short two puts with a strike price of $90.
And we're going to long one call with a strike price of $110.
So what I've written here are the payoffs
to shorting two puts.
So, if we short two puts, we get the negative
of what we would have gotten if we actually are long these two
puts.
So we get negative 180 plus 2 s1 if s1 ends up being 90.
And we get 0 because the options--
these two options would expire out of the money
if s1 is above 90.
And, the payoff from the call option, one call option,
is simply s1 minus 110, which is the strike price of this one
call, if s1 ends up being above 110 and 0
if the stock price is below 110.
So now we will add up these two payoff functions,
and we'll get the payoff of our portfolio.
So let me make a remark that what we're doing here
is just a very universal approach where
you can find the payoff of a portfolio of any types
and however many different kinds of options you actually have.
So, if you have discipline of writing down
the payoffs for individual options
and then add them up piecewise, you
will always get the right answer.
The more you practice with this, the more clear it will be.
For example, at some point, it's going
to be very clear to you, without writing
these mathematical expressions, how the payoff
diagram for this portfolio would look like,
but this would come only with practice.
And a good practice is to have the discipline
of writing down the payoffs and actually adding them up.
Now so we have this payoff.
We have this payoff.
Let's add them up.
So, if the stock price is below-- so let's
always start with sort of the lower part.
So, if the stock price ends up being somewhere below 90,
then we get this much from these two puts.
And we get nothing from the call.
So we get negative 180 plus 2 s1 if s1 is less or equal than 90.
Then, if s1 is above 90, but below 110, we
get 0 payoff from the two puts, and we also get,
actually, 0 payoff from call.
So we get 0 if s1 is above 90 and below 110.
And then, once we're crossing 110, so if s1 is above 110,
we get nothing from the two puts, and we get s1 minus 110
from the call.
So, in this part, we get s1 minus 110 if s1 is above 110.
Let me also make another minor remark
that where exactly I put the equality
signs in these expressions does not matter because,
all of these functions, they are continuous in the sense
that there are no breaks.
So, therefore, if I put, for example, equality, instead
of here, here, the end result would not
change because, again, you have continuity in all of these--
in all of these breakpoints.
Now the final step is to draw this mathematical expression
in the form of a diagram.
I'm going to start from the left-hand side.
So, if s1 is 0, then we get negative $180, the payoff.
So I'm going to start from here, negative 180.
And then, if s1 equals to 90, then we're
going to get 0 payoff because it's going to be negative 180
plus 2 times 90.
That's going to be 0.
And we could also see that we have 0 here.
So, if s1 equals to 90, we get 0 here as well.
So we're getting-- so this is 90.
We're getting this point.
And so this is the line that goes straight line
from negative 180 to 90.
The slope of this line, you could see that it's also--
so this part is 2 because we have two of these puts.
And then we get--
then our payoff is 0 from 90 to 110.
And, from this point onwards, from 110 and above, our payoff
is s1 minus 110.
So this is the line that will look like this.
And so the slope of this line is 45 degrees.
So this raise is 1.
And so this is how our combined payoff from the strategy
is going to look like.
And, in fact, so, if you look at this,
you realize that this is really just a combination,
a simple combination, of two short puts here at the bottom.
And then you have one long call option
with a strike price of 110.
So, therefore, you're staring at negative 180 all the way to 0
when s1 equals to 90.
Then it's 0.
Then it's in the positive domain when s1 goes above $110.
So this is the payoff diagram for this question.