PROFESSOR: In this video, we will find
the market value of ABC's debt.
Recall that, next year, in year one,
ABC's debt value will either be $5 million in the bad state
or $20 million in the good state.
Let's contrast these payoffs with the payoffs
to the risk-free debt.
If ABC's debt was risk free, it would have paid $20 million
in both good and bad states.
Let me introduce a default put option.
This option compensates the holder of risky debt
for the value lost in the event of default. In our case,
this default put option will pay $15 million in the bad state
so that the value of assets plus the payoff from this option
would equal to the face value of the loan, which is $20 million.
Based on this, we can derive the key insight.
The current value of ABC's debt should equal the current value
of $20 million, face-value, risk-free debt, minus the value
of what we called the default put option,
an option that pays $15 million in the bad state
and $0 in the good state.
Now we need to price the default put option.
To do this, we will compare the payoffs
that we get from this default put option with the payoffs
that we get from the put option written on the stock.
Recall that we had an option traded
in the market with a strike price of $7.
Remember that, in the bad state, the share price will be $0,
and, in the good state, it will be $10.
Therefore, this put option written on the stock
will pay $0 in the good state, and it
will pay $7 in the bad state.
Similar to the way we priced equity in the previous video,
let's contrast the payoffs of the default put option
and the put option written on the stock.
In the bad state, the default put option pays $15 million,
and the put option on the stock pays $7.
In the good state, both of them pay $0.
Based on this, we can derive the key insight.
The value of the default put option should equal 15 million
divided by 7 times the value of the $7 strike put
option on the stock.
Recall that the value of this $7 strike put option written
on the stock was $2.52.
Therefore, the value of the default put option
is $5.4 million.
Putting it all together, we can find the value
of ABC's debt right now.
It's going to be the present value of the risk-free debt,
which is $20 million--
this is because the risk-free rate is 0%--
minus the value of the default put
option, which is $5.4 million.
This gives us the value of ABC's debt.
That equals $14.6 million.
Notice something very interesting.
The yield to maturity on this bond, which
we can compute by taking the face value of this loan,
$20 million, divided by its current market value,
which is 14.6 minus 1, will be 37%.
Even though the risk-free rate in this economy is 0%,
the yield to maturity on this bond is 37%.
This high yield to maturity is explained by the fact
that, in the event of default, the holder of this loan
loses $15 million out of $20 million face value.
And, therefore, the high YTM captures the risk of this loss.
We will further explore this topic
in the second part of this course.