PROFESSOR: Let's look at more expectations involving
our stochastic processes.
We know that db is a Gaussian random variable
with a mean 0 and variance dt.
We also know that if we integrate
db from, say, 0 to time t--
And for convenience, I can write this as bt minus b0.
Let's agree that b0 is going to be 0.
It will simplify our notation.
So this I'll just write is bt.
And we know that this is distributed as n 0t, that
is, it has variance t.
So since that is the case, we have an easy way
that we can write things.
We know that the expectation of d is going to be 0.
We know that its variance is going to be t.
So let's just replace the random variable bt, or really,
bt minus b0, by square root of t times
z, where z doesn't have any time dependence.
z is just n 01.
So that's just simplifying things and putting everything
in an even more standard form.
But it also makes explicit the time dependent.
And it's the scaling with time that's
going to be important for a lot of financial applications,
and for risk management.
So, what that means is that any time
where we see a bt, or a bt minus b0,
we can replace it by that function.
So if we want to compute the expectation of some function
of bt minus b0, we can just write
that the expectation of square root of t times
z, our function of square root of t and z, and compute that.
OK.
And remember these are our Gaussian intervals.
So we just need to do an integral.
That's all it is.
So this is equal to 1 over square root of 2 pi integral
from minus infinity to infinity of e
to the minus z squared over 2 times
f of square root of t times z.
Easy.
So for example, suppose we wanted
to compute the fourth power.
The expectation of the fourth power.
So suppose that we had f of x is the function x to the fourth.
So we'd like to compute.
This is an example.
So we'd like to compute f of et minus e0.
That's going to be the expectation of bt minus b0
is to the fourth power.
That's the same thing as expectation
of square root of tz raised to the fourth power.
We can pull out square root of t,
which is nonstochastic to get t squared
times the expectation of z to the 4th, which
is a well-known Gaussian integal that we use in the kurtosis.
It's just equal to 3.
3t squared.
All right.
So this way of standardizing things and writing things
in terms of z when we work in the integral form,
when we integrate our processes, is very convenient.
Let's do an example, and I want to review
a very useful trick with you.
So let's take a look.
So, for example, suppose we do another example.
Suppose we wanted to compute the expectation of e to the 6x
where dx, let's just say it's ordinary Brownian motion, udt
plus sigma db.
So because it's in this form, we can
integrate x, like xt minus x0.
OK, it's going to be mu times t plus square root of t times z.
So if we go to compute the expectation of e to the 6 times
ut plus square root of tz.
We could also-- you might see it sometimes in the form
before it's been replaced.
It's just e to the 6 times mu t plus b.
Either way, we'd like to do an integral.
Looking at the first form, obviously e to the six mu t
is just a factor.
It's a scalar, so we can write that-- we can pull that out
in front.
6 mu t times the expectation of e to the 6
square root of t times z.
Now in this case, this is a form that we'll see a lot.
I'd like to give you a useful general formula.
That if we'd like to take the expectation of e
to the something, linear and z.
And in fact, we already know what this is.
Because we already did, in our first lecture,
the characteristic function.
And it's also related to the moment generating function,
e to the something times z.
But let me just connect it with the Gaussian intervals
and remind you of where we got that.
And let's get a useful formula.
So, a useful formula.
Suppose that we have e to the, let's say, alpha
z plus b, plus beta.
So, some linear function.
So, I would like to compute the expectation of some exponential
of a linear function of z.
And this shows up a lot in particular in asset
pricing formulas.
So this is clearly equal to e to the beta,
because that's just a pre factor.
Times e to the alpha z.
And this we do by doing the Gaussian integral,
with the trick of completing the square in the exponent.
So this is 1 over 2 pi e to the minus z squared over 2 times
e to the alpha z dz.
That's just our definition for the expectation operator.
And of course I had the e to the beta in front,
so let's not lose that.
So inside the integral, what I can
do in the integrand is I can write this as,
let's keep our prefactory e to the beta
over square root of 2 pi.
And I can write this as e to the minus z minus alpha
to the quantity squared over 2.
Now you notice if we expand this, I'll get minus e
squared over 2.
I'll get minus minus alpha z times 2
over 2, which is exactly the coefficient with the weighting
that I need over here.
But then there's an extra piece.
There's an alpha squared over 2.
So let's correct for that.
Let's put in our integral, and let's write this as plus alpha
squared over 2 times dz.
But this expression is e to the beta plus alpha squared over
2 times 1 over square root of 2 pi integral
e to the minus z minus alpha quantity squared over 2 dz.
And because the integral goes from minus infinity
to infinity, the difference in the exponential between z
and z minus alpha makes no difference at all.
If you'd like, you can shift the variable of integration.
The integral inside the square brackets
with 1 over square root of 2 pi in front is equal to 1.
So our final result, our final useful formula,
is that the expectation of e to the alpha z plus beta,
for any alpha and beta that are constant,
is going to be e to the alpha squared over 2 plus beta.
Now, let's apply that to our example.
We had-- this is our useful formula.
And our example was the exponential of e
to the 6x was expectation of e to the 6 mu t
plus 6 square root of t times z.
So applying our formula, this is going
to give me e to the 6 mu t plus the square
of the coefficient of z.
That's going to be 6 times square root of t divided by 2.
So 6 squared over 2.
6 squared Is 36, over 2 is 18.
And square root of t squared is t.
And there's my answer for my expectation.
Yes, except we left out one coefficient,
which was the sigma squared.
So, this is my mistake.
If you didn't catch the sigma squared, I hope you did.
Because t should always come in with the sigma
squared in front of it.
But let's go back and fix my formulas.
There should have been a--
we began here with mu t plus sigma, square root of t.
There should have been a sigma square root of t there.
We have a sigma b here.
This should have had a sigma here.
And then as we come down here, we needed a sigma here.
And then keep in mind that our expression
was to take this quantity in the red parentheses squared
divided by 2.
That's our alpha that we see over here.
So I apologize for the typo, but I hope
you caught it before I did.
So this is 6 squared over 2 is 18.
Square root of t is t.
And sigma squared is sigma squared.
So there's our answer for finding this expectation.
And this works, generally, for a larger class
of functions that show up for different kinds of Ito
processes.