PROFESSOR: Let's now gather the results
we have obtained from Modigliani Miller.
The key insight is that a firm's value is primarily
determined by its assets.
That is, by its real investments.
Holding the asset constant, financial transactions
such as the choice of financing do not change the firm's value.
Although the MM theorem was originally
aimed at firms' financing or capital structure choices,
this insight it reveals actually applies to all aspects
of financial policy.
In particular, in the absence of frictions
in the financial market, we have the following MM irrelevance
results.
Capital structure is irrelevant.
Long-term versus short-term debt is irrelevant.
Payout policy is irrelevant.
Risk management policy is irrelevant.
And so on.
Generally speaking, holding the asset side fixed,
financial transactions involving the liability side
are all zero NPV activities, since they're all
properly priced by the market.
The MM insight is a powerful one,
but it holds only under its assumptions, which leave out
important aspects of reality.
It is the starting point of modern corporate finance, not
the end.
It helps us to avoid some potential misconceptions
and confusions, like the cheap debt fallacy,
but more importantly, it guides us
to ask the right questions, such as true reasons for capital
structure to matter.
For example, in the case of financing,
how the choice of capital structure
may change the total size of this pie--
that is, the total value of the firm in the presence
of various frictions.
We will extend analysis of financing
to these situations in the following lectures.
But before doing so, we would like
to spend the rest of this lecture to examine
the risk of corporate debt.