PROFESSOR: So in practice, we almost always
have to deal with inequality constraints
to keep allocations that are just unreasonable.
Typically, for Long-only managers,
we say that weights should be between zero and one,
but they really have to be much less than one.
Any responsible manager is not going to be undiversified,
put all of his or her eggs in one basket.
So we'll often see things where the weights may be constrained
to be, say, between zero and 5%, zero and 10%,
depending on the liquidity the assets.
Could be zero and 1%.
And the zero lower bound would be for a Long-only manager
where they're not permitted to short securities.
So these are cases that quadratic programming handles
perfectly.
So we can add in addition to equality constraints,
we can add any number of inequality constraints.
And those inequality constraints can
be framed either at the level of individual weights,
individual components within the weight vector,
or linear combinations of them which is useful
if we want to say, for example, that our weight, our exposure
to a particular industry in the economy, our exposure
to a particular country in an international portfolio
needs to be bounded by a certain amount.
And then we take a linear competition of certain assets
and say that that bound lies only in that case.
So these are all things that we can
do using quadratic programming.
So let's set up a few things on the computer,
and this R Notebook is going to be available to download along
with the data file that you can use for rerunning
these simulations.
And then what I'd encourage you to do is go get your own data,
build your own covariance matrix,
make your own estimations of risk and return, and run this.
Or take a look at your own personal portfolio
or your retirement portfolio and run this and see
is your investment portfolio efficient.
So what are the things we need to do computationally?
Well, the nice thing about this R Notebook
is it contains both code and text.
So when you download it and you run it,
you can turn it into a nice pretty PDF HTML
file you can take a look at, but we're
going to look at it in code view here.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to start,
you can set this up anyway.
And I hope these colors show up on the video.
But this background color here in gray is a block of code.
And the code are commands in R.
And the lines that begin with the pound sign,
these are comments.
The libraries are loaded once, so these libraries
such as quadprog for quadratic programming,
they need to be downloaded from CRAN from the R archive.
You can do that with the install.packages command.
And you'd need to put the name in quotes
for installed.packages.
Library loads the package.
It's not the packages command, don't ask me why.
It doesn't use quotes.
But the install.packages you do once then
it's on your computer.
And you can see which packages are installed in your computer
by looking at the Packages tab over on the right
and see which ones are here and which ones are loaded
at a given point in time.
And you can load them, and then they'll be available to use.
Here are a few others.
I'm not sure if we use all of these today for this,
but none of them is bad to have.
You have a reshape command for changing and arranging data.
The tidyverse command is useful as is actually tidyquant,
and I think we've seen it already in the course,
for a bunch of data handling commands that
give logical structure to data that
have different kinds of relationships.
ggplot is a package that does prettier and more sophisticated
plots than the base R package.
And in the code, I think I've got
some done both ways, the base R command and the ggplot.
If you take a look in your RStudio,
I think in the Help file, you will
find that there is a set of cheat sheets,
and you will find a bunch of things, including--
I'm not sure if ggplot is on here.
It may be, but there are a bunch of things here
that are very useful and you can find more.
Yes, there is a ggplot one right there.
So you can take a look at that and download that,
see some of the commands, look at examples.
So we're going to get all this stuff and run this code walk,
and we'll be ready to go.
One of the things that we have is this data file,
and this data file is taken from an example given
in book by Richard Micheaux called
efficient asset management which I encourage
you to take a look at.
We've got here just some data that he
took from historical data.
And as I said, you can get your own.
So these are a bunch of country indices.
And we have the correlation in each country with each other
over on the left-hand side.
Then we have a couple of other assets.
And then we have for each asset, its expected mean
and its expected standard deviation.
Now, the true estimation of those
is very, very tricky business.
Here, these are taken by doing estimates from history
and assuming that the future is going
to be like the past, which is always a problematic way to go.
But it doesn't matter.
The assumption is you provide the inputs,
the algorithms tell you what to do next.
So we've got a clear separation of responsibility.
Your job is to make estimates for the future--
co-variances, correlations, and expected returns.
So we've run that.
And what we'd like to do then is construct some of the objects
that we saw.
So here what we're going to do is we're going to pull out,
first, the appropriate columns to make a correlation
matrix to have a vector of standard deviations.
Mu is going to be the vector of expected excess returns
and iota is going to be the vector of ones.
There are eight because, in this example, we have eight assets.
The covariance matrix here is constructed
as the correlation matrix with the diagonal matrix of sigmas
of the volatility is on the left and on the right,
and that generates exactly what we expect
for the covariance matrix the element CIJ, our sigma
i sigma j times rho_ij.
And then, the thing that we really need in all our formulas
is the inverse covariance matrix.
And in R, that's given by the solve command
because it's also used for solving
systems of simultaneous linear equations.
We have a few constants that came out of our algebra
for looking at solving the Lagrange multiplier
problem, which we call a, b, and c, maybe lower case.
But in any event, we have these as matrix operations in R.
Matrix operations are formed by having a percent sign,
so % star % is matrix multiplication.
The t operator is a transpose.
So here we have iota transpose times c inverse times iota.
And we're converting this to as.numeric
to take it away because the classes of objects and the data
typing that are implicit sometimes
don't work well in some of the subsequent operations.
So it doesn't hurt to force things to the form
that you want them to.
They may not be elegant, it may not be necessary,
but this works for me.
And I'm pretty sure I've tested this,
it will work for you, too.
But, by all means, feel free to do better.
So I'm going to run this whole block, and what I want to do
is I want to look at a couple of things.
What I've done is we've defined parameters--
the correlation, the covariance matrix, the means,
the standard deviations, those are
things we're going to need for our optimization problem.
Those are our inputs.
But let's take a look at them first
from a business perspective.
So what do we see in the data?
Well, if we look at the data, here
is a correlation plot of each country and asset
with every other one.
So a correlation matrix is symmetric,
so we only need to see half of it.
In this form-- and this is using a package in R called coreplot,
this correlation plot shows for each pair,
for example, Canada with Germany, a dot here
whose size is the magnitude of the correlation
and whose color is given on this scale on the right-hand side.
So dark blue is a correlation of one,
and we see that along the diagonal
because a correlation of anything with itself,
by definition, is one.
And for the other values, we see different magnitudes.
And notice that are all positive,
and this is fairly typical.
It's hard to find assets that are negatively
correlated with each other.
And when you can, you should pay close attention to them
because they let you lower risk and, in general,
let you take bigger positions for the same level of risk
and earn more return.
It depends on the balance of risk and return.
In any event, our method is agnostic about that.
You could put in any valid covariance matrix.
One thing to be aware of when you're
getting numerical estimates, if you're
tempted to approximate things from historical series
where the time series for the data might be different,
maybe we have more data available for one market than
for another, we need to make sure it's
very easy to get pairwise estimates for the correlations
by looking between any pair of what their longest
common period is.
And that's a typical way that we might do it.
And R has a bunch of features for how
to deal with missing data and doing a covariance matrix.
You can look at Help pages for that.
However, there's an important overall property
that could get lost if we do things pairwise,
and that's the covariance matrix must be positive definite.
The positive definiteness follows--
or at least positive semidefinite.
The positive definiteness follows
because it comes from the expectation of a square.
It has to be positive definite.
It really has to-- it can't be positive semidefinite,
it shouldn't have singularities or zeros,
those would be a sign that we included some redundant assets.
You might think here the US bonds that
are included would be uncorrelated with everything,
but of course, interest rates are not completely fixed.
There is risk in US bonds.
There's interest rate risk, even if there's not default risk.
So the correlation is not zero with other risky assets.
But we can't have something that's strictly
constant in the conference matrix,
we wouldn't be allowed to invert it.
So that's our data in terms of how things are correlated.
What about the risk and return of these different assets?
Let's take look at that.
So here's a plot where we have conventional terms.
We have risk on the x-axis.
We have excess return along the y-axis.
And each of the assets that we're investing in,
the market for each country, is plotted on this risk return
diagram.
So we see in the lower left, we've
got very low risk, very low return assets,
currencies and government bonds.
And during this particular time period where this is estimated,
we have a bunch of very high risk, high return assets moving
as we move toward the upper right.
And we see, generally, the behavior
that we would expect, that to get higher returns,
you need to take higher amounts of risk.
The one interesting thing in this numerical example
is that France and Japan are so close in their values
that, actually, they're difficult to resolve
at the screen and the data labels have taken over.
So you should look at the numbers.
And in fact, the fact that they're
so close, to a certain degree, fakes out
the optimizer a little bit.
So it's not a good state of affairs,
and it leads to some numerical instabilities
that we want to be aware of.