PROFESSOR: We'll apply it to our global asset allocation
problem.
And let's pick 100 points, let's say,
and we're going to run this chunk of code right here.
And we're going to do 100 points on the efficient frontier.
We're going to run our function.
It's the mvef as a function of the covariance,
the historical expected returns, and our number of points.
We'll put this in an object we'll call big MVEF for lack
of imagination.
You can plot the results either using the base R plot
commander.
Here, I've done it using ggplot to get
something that's a little bit more nicely formatted.
And there are a couple other things
that are nice about ggplot.
One of them is it really respects
the structure of the data when we've got more complex,
related data.
And at the practical level, it lets us layer and add things
to build more complex plots if we
want to put several graphs on the same page,
where the base R command doesn't do that as elegantly.
So our first command here is we're
defining this object because we're going to use it again,
mvef.plot.
The ".plots" is just a naming convention,
and what we're doing is we're telling it,
plot these xy things and put some labels out there.
So what do we get?
We get something that looks qualitatively
like the hyperbolas we saw.
There's a curve.
But it's obviously not a hyperbola because it bends.
Instead of going asymptotically straight,
it has a non-conic curve.
It's got a kink in there, and it ends.
It stops at a point, which is the highest
return in our data set.
And similarly, it stops down here at the bottom.
But there it is.
We've solved.
So these points here represent the portfolios
subject to the constraints that have
the maximum level of return for a given the level of risk.
Or the exact problem that we solved,
they've got the minimum risk for a given level of return.
Everything in the graph that is below and to the right
is feasible but not optimal.
Everything that is above and to the left
would require violating one of the constraints.
Now, how do we compare this to the unconstrained problem?
Well, let's take a look at that.
So let's look at running this chunk of code.
Remember that we defined A, B, C to be the numbers that we
did in lecture for looking at the exact problem
without inequality constraints, so we can do it.
And remember that we solved explicitly
for a function of-- sigma p was a quadratic function of mu sub
p.
So let's solve for this here, and let's
plot the results together.
And that gives us the blue line.
And in addition, I plotted the red dots
are the original assets in our data set.
So what we can see is that blue line is indeed a hyperbola.
We've cut it off at the same upper level of mu sub p,
so it's commensurate so it doesn't run off the page.
We see that there's a region between the blue
and the black lines.
That's what we give up by imposing our constraints.
The things between the blue and the black lines
are risk-return combinations that
are not allowed with our inequality constraints, that
would be allowed, that would not violate a budget constraint,
but they do violate one of the inequality constraints.
So that's the cost of not taking short positions.
That's the cost of not using leverage.
This is the area between the two curves
is how much more return we could have gotten per unit of risk
or how much risk reduction we could have gotten, particularly
with the short positions, that generate
a synthetic negative correlation, how much less risk
we could have taken for a given level of return.
So the blue line is computed analytically,
and that's our Lagrange multiplier method.
The black line or the black set of dots connected by a curve
through them is the numerical result of quadratic programming
that we've done by running this algorithm
and running it through the computer.