PROFESSOR: Can we find the efficient frontier in practice?
The optimizations would be absolutely optimal
if we knew the exact value of the inputs
and we knew that the returns were generated
in exactly the way these models predict,
but neither of those things is true.
Let's take the inputs first of all.
Even if we knew the exact data-generating process,
the parameters we need to estimate
from historical data using statistical techniques,
or we need other forecasting techniques
to predict what the future excess returns will be.
Given that they're drawn from some distribution,
getting the parameters and fitting
those from the limited and noisy data we have can be tricky.
We also have the issue that the data-generating process,
if there is such a thing, is not stable over infinite periods
of time.
Here, we've got attention.
We'd like to use longer and longer historical periods.
If we can to get better statistics.
But the longer we go, the less likely
it is that a given covariance matrix really
held that would be a good basis for forecasting the future.
So in practice, it's quite challenging
to get good estimates for what the inputs are even
under the assumption that there's
a fixed data-generating process that we know what it is
and that the time series are stationary.
And probably none of those things is true.
But let's take a look.
We can at least see how big the estimation side is
by making the assumption that everything is held fixed
and that we know how the noise is generated.
Let's do it via Monte Carlo.
We've already seen how these techniques can
be used to get visualizations of the evolution
of random processes.
We've seen how Monte Carlo techniques
can be used to approximate the prices of options.
And now let's use it to simulate a whole bunch
of different scenarios.
So this kind of scenario analysis
is quite a typical application of Monte Carlo techniques
as well.
What are we going to do?
Well, here's the idea.
Let's assume that the data that we have,
the code that we've been working with,
the covariance matrix, the expected returns--
let's suppose that those are actually the truth.
That's the way the world really works.
But let's forget that we know where they came from.
Let's pretend we don't know what their actual values are.
Let's suppose that what we have to look at is historical data.
We're going to simulate it.
But what we're looking at is realizations
of data that are drawn from a probability distribution
with a particular covariance and with a particular set
of expected returns.
And we're going to do that a whole bunch of different times.
So here's the setup.
There's a true data-generating process.
We're going to generate a whole bunch
of decade-long simulations.
Each one is going to be a possible outcome that we could
have had, data that we could be looking
at by which we need to estimate what the true values are.
And we don't get the true values.
There's no answer in the back of the book here.
What we need to do is we're charged with making investment
decisions.
So what we're going to do is each time we
get a chunk of simulated historical data,
we're going to act on it.
We're going to try to infer the most likely values for what
the covariance matrix and the expected excess returns are.
We will find where we think the efficient frontier should be,
and that will be a set of portfolios.
But then each of those portfolios,
we're going to plot on the risk and return graph,
not against where we thought it's risk and return would be,
but where they actually are based on the true values.
So this is all under some almost perfect--
this is like the best case we could possibly have.
There is a stable data-generating process.
Everything is stationary.
We know what the model is.
We just don't know the parameters.
So this is all-- any uncertainties
we see, any imprecision we see all comes from the parameter
estimation side.
None of it comes from this other more challenging problems
like our markets changing with time.
Can we use historical estimates from the past?
Are they good predictors of the future?
Do we need something else?
This is our baseline.
So let's see how well we can do that.
So what we're going to do is write a function
to do mean variance.
We'll call mvmc for "mean variance Monte Carlo."
And let's take a look at what it consists of.
So here's our code, our mean variance Monte Carlo,
and I've defined a function which has a similar function
call.
It takes a covariance matrix.
It takes a vector of expected returns and a bunch of points.
So let's run this to define the function.
And what we're going to do is generate a simulated covariance
matrix.
Now, the data that we started with
was based on the simulation's monthly returns.
It could be anything.
There's a standard technique for generating
correlated random variables that are normally distributed,
which we're going to use here.
And that's to use this Cholesky decomposition, which basically
takes the square root of the covariance matrix,
and we'll sandwich it and reconstruct something.
So you can take a look.
This is a standard technique that you can look up
for generating jointly normal correlated random variables,
and what we're going to do is we're
going to generate a bunch of simulated time series
with those parameters.
So what happens is we're using this
for generating normal random numbers.
The parameters are going to be the mu inputs that we have
and the covariance matrix that we have.
So this tells us that we're going to generate things
from a random distribution whose parameters are the ones
that we're setting to be exactly the ones that we started with.
But of course, because it's a random sample,
we're going to get different actual values.
Then, for each set of simulated historical data,
we're going to run our computation of where
the efficient frontier is.
So what we'll do is we'll do a loop.
And for each one, we're going to run an efficient frontier.
We'll do that a whole bunch of times,
and then we'll plot them and see how it looks.
So the rest of this is pretty much the same
that we saw before, and we're going
to output this into something we'll call mvmc.
It's going to have sigma p on the efficient frontier
as a function of mu sub p, the grid of points
that we work with, and we'll put the weights as well for what's
on the efficient frontier.
So let's see how it looks, shall we?
Let's do 100 simulations.
You can run the code and do more.
And what we're going to do is generate a bunch of points.
So we'll have this for loop over simulations.
So within this for loop, we're going to run our mean variance
Monte Carlo.
Because it's going to overwrite the variables each time, let's
pull out the ones we want.
So sigma_sim will be our--
in this case, for step n in our for loop.
This will be the n-th set of sigma variables
on our efficient frontier plot.
Remember that we're having pairs of mus and sigmas,
and the ensemble of them for giving in
is going to sweep out the curve.
And here are the corresponding mus,
the points that we held fixed as we build up
our efficient frontier.
And that's it.
So we're going to run this loop, and then we're
going to plot it.
So let's take a look and see what we get.
Oh, boy.
So the blue line is our unconstrained efficient
frontier.
The black line that's the envelope
curve of all these red dots, that's
the true efficient frontier under the constraints
with the inequality constraints we've been talking about.
So the blue line and the black line
are exactly the ones that we saw above.
What are the red dots?
Well, each line of red dots that you see
is the output of one of our 100 simulations.
Using our best historical estimates and our best
techniques of optimizing based on a given
set of inputs that we had, this is where we think--
these are things that we thought were on the efficient frontier
plotted against where they really truly are.
So we don't plot their locations based on what
we thought the values were.
This is based on where they actually were.
And of course, in the real world, we couldn't do that.
So this is absolutely a best case.
We would just find out when the investment returns came in
and we found that a particular portfolio landed far away
from the efficient frontier.
And you can see that these red points are not all
clustered really close to the efficient frontier.
It might be what you would expect.
Some of them are very, very far away.
Of course, a lot of them are close, and we could get lucky.
But if we were to end up with a point far away,
we might say, well, what happened?
How did that happen?
I thought we were doing something that was optimal.
And in this case, we did.
We did everything right, and we still
ended up with the red points.
So it's a challenging thing to see how to do it in practice.
There are many things that are going on.
What you might think of as being the simplest one,
doing statistical estimation even
in a case where we know exactly how everything works,
leads to portfolios being all over the place.
So we do need to deal with that.
We do need to deal with the possibility the market
structures are changing over time.
We do need to think about alternative ways of using data
for forecasting future risk and return,
and we need to think about the optimization we have.
Not only in a pure world, does it
give us something that is truly the best?
But is it something that actually
is going to be robust and useful when we apply it
in the financial markets or in other decision-making settings?
Try it out on your own with this notebook.
Run it, tweak the parameters, go get your own data
sets, and have some fun.