PROFESSOR: OK, now for problem 2--
problem 2 states that you are managing a pension fund that
has a single payment liability in the amount of $25 million
coming due four years from today.
You wish to immunize this liability
by making investments today that will have a guaranteed terminal
value of $25 million in four years.
Two investments are available--
first, two-year zero coupon notes
and second, five-year zero coupon notes.
In Part A, it's stated that, if today's yield curve
is flat at 10%, how much must be invested
in each security in order to immunize this liability?
Assume annual compounding.
Generally, immunization involves two steps--
equalizing both the present values
and the modified durations of our assets and liabilities.
Let's assume that the two-year and five-year
zero coupon notes have face values of $1,000.
Since the yield curve is flat at 10%,
the price of the two-year zero coupon note
is simply $1,000 divided by 1.1 squared, which
is equal to $826.45.
Similarly, the price of the five-year zero coupon note
is $1,000 divided by 1.1 to the fifth, which
is equal to $620.92.
Since the liability involves a single payment of $25 million
in four years, its present value is $25 million
divided by 1.1 to the fourth, which is equal to $17,075,336.
Since we know that the Macaulay duration of a zero coupon bond
is equal to its time to maturity,
the modified duration of the two-year zero coupon note
is the time to maturity, 2 years, divided by 1.1,
which is equal to 1.82 years.
Similarly, the modified duration of the five-year zero coupon
code is 5 years divided by 1.1, which
is equal to 4.54 years and the modified
duration of the liability is 4 divided by 1.1,
which is equal to 3.64 years.
Now, let n2 be the number of two-year zero coupon
notes required to immunize liability, and n5
be the number of five-year zero coupon notes.
In our first step of immunization,
we can equate the present values of assets and liabilities
in the equation shown--
826.45 times n2 plus 620.92 times n5 equals 17,075,336.
In the second step, we're going to equate
the value-weighted average durations of assets
and liabilities in the equation below.
1.82, which is the modified duration
of the two-year zero-coupon note, times n2 times
the price of the two-year zero-coupon note divided
by the total value of our portfolio plus 4.54,
which is the modified duration of the five-year zero coupon
note, times n5 times 620 divided by 17,075,336
equals 3.64, the modified duration of our liability.
We can solve the system of two equations and two unknowns,
n2 and n5, and find that we should invest
in n2 equals 6,836 of the two-year zero-coupon notes
and n5 equals 18,401 of the five-year zero-coupon notes
in order to immunize the liability.
Remember, each of the bonds here have a denomination of $1,000.
In dollar amounts, that means that we
should invest in 6,836 times 826.45, which
is equal to $5.65 million of the two-year zero-coupon notes,
and 18,401 times 620.92, which equals $11.42 million
of the five-year zero-coupon notes.
Notice that 5.65 plus 11.42 is roughly
equal to the $17,075,336 amount of our liability.
OK, Part B says that if interest rates at all maturities
rise from 10% to 11%, would you consider
yourself better or worse off than if interest rates had
remained at 10%?
Explain your choice with the calculation,
and also explain intuitively why you think this is the case.
Well, first, let's go over the intuition.
It's very similar to the barbell versus bullet intuition
that we reviewed in Problem 1.
Specifically, since the cash flows
of our immunizing portfolio, which
consists of two-years in five-years zero-coupon notes,
are more spread out, like a barbell,
than the single bullet liability that comes due in four years,
the convexity of our immunizing portfolio
is likely greater than that of the liability.
And all else equal, we like convexity
when interest rates change.
Thus, if interest rates rise from 10% to 11%,
we will likely be better off as the value
of our immunizing portfolio will fall by less
than that of our liability.
To verify this intuition mathematically,
we can simply calculate the present values
of the liability and our immunizing portfolio
under the assumption that interest rates are now 11%.
In particular, the present value of the liability
coming due in four years will decrease
from $17,075,336 to $25 million divided by 1.11 to the fourth,
which is equal to $16,468,274.
The price of the two-year zero-coupon note,
now that interest rates are 11%, is
1,000 divided by 1.11 squared, which is equal to $811.62.
And the price of the five-year zero-coupon note
is now 1,000 divided by 1.11 to the fifth,
which is equal to $593.45.
Thus, the present value of our immunizing portfolio,
using our n2 an n5 amounts that we found in Part A,
is equal to $811.62 times $6,836 --
that's n2, the amount that we invested in the two-year
zero-coupon note --
plus $620.92 times $18,401--
that's n5, the number of five-zero zero-coupon notes we
purchased -- which equals $16,973,783 --
which, compared to the new present value of our liability
of $16,468,274, is greater.
One thing to note before we end Problem 2 is that, in practice,
once there is a change in interest rates,
like the increase from 10% to 11% in this example,
our portfolio shares --
the n2 two and n5 --
have to be adjusted in order to reimmunize the liability
to match the present values and duration of the liability.
Such adjustments in practice can involve non-trivial trading
costs that make reimmunization a little bit more difficult
than it is in this stylized example.