INSTRUCTOR: In this video, we will
compute the price of the put option, which
has the same parameters as the option we
studied in the previous video.
The strike price of this option is $55, and time to maturity
is six months.
To compute the price of this put option,
we will use put-call parity.
Recall that the price of the call
option plus the present value of the strike K
should equal to the stock price plus the price
of the put option, to avoid arbitrage.
Let's apply this to our case.
The price of the put option will equal
the price of the call option, which
we computed in the previous video (it's $3.15),
plus the present value of the strike
price of this option, which is $55, minus the current share
price, which is $50.
This gives us the price of this option, which is $7.81.
As a more general note, to compute
the price of a European put option using
the Black-Scholes-Merton approach,
we first need to compute the price of the corresponding call
option with the same strike and same time
to maturity by using the Black-Scholes-Merton formula,
and then use the put-call parity to get the price of the put.