PROFESSOR: This section deals with PPE, property, plant,
and equipment, and depreciation.
Property plant and equipment, or PP&E, or PPE,
is located under assets, and is categorized as fixed assets.
There are two main aspects of PP&E,
capitalisation and depreciation.
PP&E is put on the balance sheet and is capitalized,
because PP&E is believed to serve
to generate future revenues.
As firms realize benefits from PP&E, the part of cost of PP&E
is transferred over time from the balance sheet
to income statement via depreciation expense.
Therefore, depreciation is consistent with the matching
principles.
Calculating the ending PP&E balance and accumulated
depreciation is somewhat similar to what
we have seen for calculating ending inventory.
First, we start with the beginning balance of PP&E,
then we add capital expenditures,
which is the gross amount of PP&E purchased.
If a firm bought machinery for $1 million,
this is considered as a capital expenditure.
We subsequently subtract the gross value
of assets disposed or sold.
If a firm sold the building that they had,
we subtract the gross value here.
Gross value, meaning the value not considering depreciation.
We arrive at the ending balance.
The ending balances is basically the capitalized cost
of PP&E purchase.
The ending balance here assumes that there's
no impairment of PP&E. We'll get to what
this means in a few slides.
We also need to calculate accumulated depreciation, which
is a contra asset account, to derive the net PP&E value.
Recall that a contra asset account
is used to record reduction in the value of an asset.
Accumulated depreciation is depreciation
of an asset accumulated over the life of an asset.
To calculate accumulated depreciation,
again, we start with the beginning balance
of accumulated depreciation.
We then add depreciation expense to the beginning balance.
Next, we subtract accumulated depreciation
of disposed assets, if there are any.
We will have the ending balance.
How do we then estimate the depreciation expense.
The most commonly used method is the straight-line method.
Using this method, an asset is depreciated evenly
over an expected life.
Depreciation expense per year is calculated
as acquisition cost minus the salvage value, divided
by estimated useful life.
Let's go over one by one what each term means.
First, acquisition cost is the same as gross PP&E purchased.
If you bought a car for $50,000, then your acquisition cost
is exactly that amount.
Second, salvage value is the expected realizable value
of an asset at the end of useful life.
When you use your car up and take it to a car scrap,
how much would you receive?
The term acquisition cost minus the salvage value
is called the depreciation base, i.e.
the portion of the cost that is depreciated.
Finally, estimated useful life is the period
over which the asset is expected to provide
economic benefits to the firm.
Know that this is not the same as physical life.
After calculating depreciation expense,
what financial statements are affected by depreciation then.
First, income statement is affected.
In particular, depreciation expense
increases by the expensed amount,
so that net income will decrease.
How about the balance sheet?
Accumulated depreciation, which is a contra asset account,
will increase by the depreciation expense amount.
Will statement of cash flows be affected?
Think about whether depreciation expense affects cash flows.
Since depreciation does not involve any cash inflow
or outflow, depreciation will not
have any effect on statement of cash flows.