PROFESSOR: Exercise-- let F be the natural logarithm of B.
Find dF by using Ito's lemma.
Pause the video, take a moment to do it on your own,
then come back, and we'll do it together.
This case is especially simple.
So we have that dX is dB.
So we only need to worry about taking partial derivatives
with respect to B. There's no dt term in our underlying Ito
process.
And F depends on B only, not on time.
So we have that the partial of F with respect to time
is equal to 0.
The first partial of F with respect to B is 1 over B.
And the second partial derivative
of F with respect to B squared is minus 1 over B squared.
So let's compute dF.
Well, dF is partial of F with respect to t dt.
That doesn't exist.
Then, we're going to have partial of F
with respect to B times dB.
Plus, we have the Ito term, which,
because we've got this specially simple form for our Ito
process, is going to involve just 1/2 times
the second partial derivative minus 1 over B squared
times dt.
So we're done.
This is dB over B minus 1 over 2B squared dt.