PROFESSOR: In this video, I'm going
to review how to interact with the teaching team
and with your peers during this course.
The answer is very simple--
the discussion forum.
If you want to interact with your peers
or if you have a question that you
would like to ask the teaching team, go to the forum.
The forum has two types of posts, a question
or a discussion.
The difference between the two is as follows.
If you want to share some insights or to make a comment,
post your comment as a discussion.
However, if you'll like to receive an answer,
then post it as a question.
Let me give you some specific tips.
First, before asking a question, take time
to think about the material.
To gain deep understanding of finance concepts,
you need patience.
So take time.
Re-watch the lecture video or a recitation video.
We have invested considerable resources
in making the content very clear.
So chances are, if you have a question,
the answer is already there.
Second, when asking a question on the forum, be specific.
Provide a descriptive title so that it's easy for your peers
to find your question and it is also easy for us
to understand what is your question about.
Third, always be polite and respectful.
We have learners from all over the world,
from different cultures and from different backgrounds.
Please be polite, and respect each other.
We take ethics in finance very seriously.
During the final exam period, we will
close the discussion forum.
Final exam is an individual work.
And we do not allow learners to share information
or to collaborate.
We expect you to follow the honor code of MIT.
My final tip for you is to study consistently
throughout the course.
It is a bad idea to cram for the exam.
If you do, you likely won't pass.
So get ready to work and explore the exciting world of finance.