PROFESSOR: The plan for the next few weeks
is to help you build a solid understanding of options--
both the models used to price them
and their role in risk management strategies.
The outline for this week is, first, we'll
review some basic definitions and go over payoff and profit
diagrams.
Second, we'll look at a variety of popular trading strategies
and how they're constructed.
Third, I want you to understand how options
can be priced by no arbitrage on binomial trees
and, importantly, the idea of risk neutral probabilities.
And finally, you'll learn about how binomial trees can be
used to price American options.