PROFESSOR: Like forward contracts,
options can be priced using no-arbitrage logic.
One of the greatest achievements of modern finance
was to recognize this fact and use
it to develop models that are both practical
and mathematically elegant.
We'll start by learning a relatively simple,
but powerful and flexible, approach, which is to price
options using binomial trees.
We will also use the binomial approach
to explain risk-neutral pricing and illustrate its application.
A major theme running through all
of the courses in the MicroMasters program
is that the value of any asset is the net present value
of its future cash flows, discounted
at an appropriate risk-adjusted interest rate.
That principle also holds for valuing
options and other derivative securities.
However, the reason we don't directly value options
by discounting their expected future cash flows
is because of the difficulty of identifying
the right cost of capital.
In fact, there's no single discount rate that could work.
That's because an option is equivalent
to a leveraged position in the underlying asset, where
the leverage changes over time with changes in the underlying
asset price.
As the implicit leverage changes,
so does the cost of capital.
A no-arbitrage approach eliminates the need
to identify any cost of capital.
Instead, risk adjustment is incorporated via the price
of the risky asset.
This idea is most easily understood using
a binomial pricing approach.
Binomial trees incorporate the six main factors affecting
the price of a stock option.
First, the current stock price, S0, second, the strike price,
K, third, the time to expiration,
T, fourth, the volatility of the stock price,
sigma, fifth, the risk-free free interest rate, r, sixth,
any expected dividends.
These same factors are the inputs
that go into the Black-Scholes-Merton model
that we'll look at next week.
We'll start with one-step trees, and then
extend the idea later to a tree with many steps.
Let's say that today is T equals 0
and you're evaluating a stock.
You approximate the distribution of the stock's price
at time 1 with a two point distribution.
You say that the stock price will
be $70 with a probability, q, of 0.7.
And it will be $35 with a probability of 1
minus q of 0.3.
Also imagine that you believe that the market expects
a return of 19% on a simple interest basis.
In that case, the stock price today
can be calculated as the expected value of the stock
at time 1 discounted at that risk-adjusted rate.
Taking the probabilities and the values that we just looked at,
we have a 70% chance that the stock
will be at $70, a 30% chance that it will be at $35.
That's the expected price at time 1.
We discount at 19%.
And we get a stock price today of $50.
We can take this information and represent it
in a binomial tree.
At time 0, we have a stock price of $50, and at time 1,
the stock price, in the up state,
will be $70 and a time 1 the stock price, in the down state,
will be $35.
Given this model description, the expected return
of the variance of the return can
be computed using the formulas for each,
as shown on the slide.
Plugging in our values, the expected gross return
on the stock is 1.19.
Its variance is 0.1029.
And its standard deviation is 0.3207.
We took the assumptions about the probabilities
and the time 1 stock values as given
but you should think of the model
as having been calibrated beforehand
to match the expected return and volatility,
based on historical data on the stock return
and a model of returns like the CAPM or the APT.
Intuitively, it should be clear that a higher volatility will
be captured by assuming more distance between the time 1
up and down nodes.
We'll return to how trees are actually calibrated
with data in the next class.
This slide starts with a question.
Can an option on the stock be valued
using the NPV rule directly?
The answer is no, because as I mentioned a little while ago,
we don't know how to find the right cost of capital
for discounting the payoffs on the option.
However, we can price a call option
on the stock using the idea of a replicating portfolio.
Consider a call option on this stock that matures at time 1
and that has a strike price of $50.
We can compute its payoffs a time 1 at each node.
On the up node, the option will be exercised
and the payoff will be the difference between the stock
price of $70 and the strike price
of $50, so a payoff of $20.
On the down node, the stock price
is less than the strike price and the option
expires worthless.
We can put this information on our binomial tree.
We had the tree where the stock price is currently $50.
We want to know the value of the call option, which
we'll call C of 0.
The stock goes up to $70 at the up node at time 1.
And we just calculated that the value
of the option at time 1 on the up node is equal to 20.
On the down node, the stock price is $35.
And the call option at time 1 on the down node is worth nothing.
We'll now see what it means to say we are pricing
with a replicating portfolio.
Let's add one additional piece of information, too,
that we'll need, which is that the risk-free rate is
11% on a continuously compounded basis.
Consider a portfolio that has the stock and risk-free
zero coupon bonds.
Our position in the stock, which we'll call delta,
will consist of 0.5714 shares of the stock, which
will give dollar value of our stock holdings of delta times
the current stock price, which gives us $28.57 in the stock.
Our position in the zero coupon bond
will be worth minus $17.9167.
And recall that this negative bond price position means
you're short in the bonds.
The value of the portfolio today,
then, is the sum of the stock and bond positions.
So the $28.57 minus the $17.91 gives us the portfolio
that today is worth $10.6547.
We can find value of the portfolio at time 1
based on the time 1 value of each position in the tree.
A little algebra will show us that in the up node,
the value of the portfolio will be $20
and the down node will be $0.
For example, if we look at the up node,
the stock will be worth the delta shares times the stock
price on the up node, which is 0.5714 --
we fixed delta --
and $70 is the new stock price.
And then the bond position will be the original investment
with interest.
It's a short position so it's negative,
and the net value is $20.
What's important here is that these payoffs
are identical to the payoffs that we
computed on the call option.
So now, we can apply the no-arbitrage idea.
That if we have two portfolios with identical payoffs
in every state of the world, they
have to have the same value today.
That allows us to conclude that the value of the call option
is the same as the value of this replicating portfolio, which
we calculated to be $10.6547.
I'm sure you're wondering, how did
we know how to choose the delta and bond
position in the last example to find
this replicating portfolio?
Well, it was calculated using the logic
that we have two free variables, delta,
and B0, that are tied down by two linear equations
in those variables.
Those equations say that the payoff
on the replicating portfolio on each node
has to equal the value of the call option on that node.
Here's the two equations --
first for the up node, second for the down node.
We can rearrange each of these two equations
to solve for the future value of B0
in terms of the difference between the call
option on the node and delta times
the stock price on that node.
Well, now we have this equality, which is an equation in delta.
And we can then solve for delta as the ratio of the difference
of the call option in the up node and the call option
in the down node divided by the difference in the stock prices
between the up and down node.
The idea that the stock option delta represents
the sensitivity of option prices to changes in the stock price
is one we will keep on coming back to.
Once we know delta, we can find B0
using either of the original linear equations.
Here, we're using the one with the up node.
Know that we could have started with a put option instead.
And the same general approach would have applied.
Now we can verify that the general approach for finding
delta and B0 works for the example we just looked at.
Here again is the binomial tree, and stock prices,
and the corresponding call option payoffs.
Based on this information, and the risk free rate of 11%,
we can confirm that the replicating portfolio
has a delta of 0.5714.
We can also confirm that the portfolio has a short position
in bonds of $17.9167.
We can draw another important conclusion
from this example, which is that a stock
option is like a levered position in the underlying
stock.
There's leverage, because B0 is negative,
which represents borrowing.
And there's a long position in the underlying stock,
because delta is positive.
So it's as if you've borrowed to invest
in a stock, which is a leveraged position in the stock.
The amount of leverage in the position
will change over time as the stock price changes.
To sum up, in order to price any derivative of a stock
on a one-step binomial tree that has a payoff of V1u on the up
node, and the V1d on the down node,
these are the steps you'll follow.
First, calculate the amount of shares, delta,
to invest in stocks.
Second, calculate the amount, B0,
to invest in risk-free bonds.
And third, compute the value of the security
based on the value of that replicating portfolio.