PROFESSOR: Now, we're going to do two things.
We're going to talk about acquisitions.
And we're going to look at a case
where AT&T corp, which is the telephone company,
bought DirecTV, which is the cable or pay TV company.
We'll also do financial investments.
So again, this class is first acquisitions.
We're going to look at the AT&T/DirecTV case.
And acquisitions are a special case of financial investments.
And then, in the second part of the class,
we're going to do financial investments more broadly.
So our objectives in acquisitions
are to understand some of the basics of mergers
and acquisitions, which is an interesting topic.
This is an accounting class, so we're
going to be focusing on how firms account
for mergers and acquisitions.
And as part of that, we're going to introduce goodwill
accounting and talk about the inherent difficulties
associated with accounting for goodwill.
As motivation, here's a story or a picture from The Journal
back in February 2020.
And it just compiles the number of acquisitions
done by Google, Microsoft, Facebook, Apple, and Amazon,
so the big tech companies in the US.
So Google or Alphabet has done 180 acquisitions since 2010.
Many of these are small acquisitions.
What we're going to look at today is a bigger acquisition.