PROFESSOR: All right, so now, this segment,
we're going to do the accounting for this acquisition.
So here's DirecTV's balance sheet as of June 30, 2015.
It comes out from their quarterly report or their 10-Q.
And I chose this balance sheet because it's right
before the merger was finalized.
I'm going to recast the balance sheet
to show assets for first minus liabilities equals
stockholders' equity.
So you see the balance sheet.
We got three types of assets.
We got tangible assets like property, plant, and equipment
and investments.
We've got intangible assets like customer list.
And we've got goodwill.
So those are the three assets that DirecTV
has before the merger.
You got a total assets of about $25 billion,
total liabilities of about $29.
Billion and that's why their book value of net assets
is a negative $3 and 1/2 billion.
Notice that they have some intangible assets and goodwill.
What does that tell us?
Looking forward to later in the class,
this tells us that DirecTV has itself done acquisitions.
And those acquisitions have resulted
in intangible assets and goodwill
on their balance sheet.
So now.
We're going to walk through the accounting for the acquisition.
So given the acquisition price, what's
the market value in that assets, not
the book value but the market value of the net assets?
So as we talk to Bob, AT&T is paying $47.8 billion for this.
So AT&T purchases saying the market value of net assets
is $47.8 billion.
And this is purchase accounting, how
we account for the acquisition.
So under purchase accounting, the entire acquisition payment,
in this case, $47.8 billion is added to the acquirer's balance
sheet.
And it's going to be distributed across fair value
of tangible assets and liabilities.
So in the case of DirecTV, they got some satellites up
in the sky.
They've got other property, plant, and equipment on land.
They've got some financial assets.
They've got some other assets.
And they've got some liabilities.
So that's their tangible assets and liabilities.
And then we're going to identify intangible assets.
So in DirecTV's case, they've got some orbital slots,
so they have rights to put a satellite up
into the sky in a certain place.
That's an intangible asset.
They've got relationships with their customers.
They've got the DirecTV trade name.
And they may have some patents as well.
And then goodwill is an intangible asset
that we can't separately identify.
So we can say we've got these customer relationships.
And we know that we have customer relationships
because we've got the customer's name, email, and phone number.
But goodwill is more squishy.
So we can't separately identify it.
So that's going to be everything else in our valuation.
And it's going to be a plug meaning that we're just
going to solve for the amount of goodwill
after we value the tangible assets and liabilities
and after we've valued the identifiable intangible assets.
So working again through our example,
this is called allocating the purchase price.
The accounting records at the time
says our property, plant, and equipment
is worth $9.5 billion.
But remember, from our class on property, plant, and equipment,
accumulated depreciation can be either more or less
than economic depreciation.
So now when we do the acquisition, we got experts,
they say how much the satellites are worth.
They say how much the other property, plant, and equipment
is worth.
And this is our fair value of tangible assets.
So we've got a bunch of experts go in
and value the property, plant, and equipment.
And that gives us a fair value of tangible assets.
The customer list is not on DirecTV's balance sheet
nor is the value of DirecTV's orbital slots
nor is the value of its spectrum nor is the value of its trade
names.
So in the process of the acquisition,
we bring in experts.
We bring in marketing experts.
And they look at the customer list.
And they say this kind of customer list
is worth whatever, $1 a person.
And they multiply the number of customers
times that valuation per person and come up
with the value of the customer list.
So that's the value of the identifiable intangibles.
And finally, there may be synergies.
OK so again, one plus one might equal three in this case.
But synergies are not something we can point to in particular.
And that's going to be goodwill.
Now, let's work back through our purchase price allocation.
So remember we figured out what the market value of net assets
and liabilities are.
The second step is we're going to value the tangible assets,
and we're going to value the liabilities from the materials
in the case, the value of the tangible assets
are worth slightly less than the book value.
And the value of the liabilities is worth about $14 billion more
than their book value.
Notice that once we value the liabilities,
we know what the market value of the net assets are.
So now we know the market value of the total assets.
Our second step is to value the intangible asset.
Remember that AT&T has hired valuation experts.
And those experts have determined
that the value of DirecTV's customer
list and other intangible assets is $36 billion.
And once we know the value of the tangible assets,
we can solve for or plug for goodwill.
So we've got one equation and one on none there, basically,
and we use the balance sheet equation to solve
for goodwill of $34 billion.