PROFESSOR: So under purchase accounting,
the whole acquisition payment, which is, again, $47.8 billion,
is added to the acquirer's balance sheet.
And we're going to distribute it across the fair value
tangible assets and liabilities, identifiable intangibles,
and goodwill.
Remember, our total purchase price is $47.8 billion.
We're paying this purchase price with cash of $14.4 billion.
And we're issuing new stock of $33.4 billion.
So that's the acquisition payment.
Now, what did we get for that acquisition payment?
Well, we got fair value intangible assets
of $20 billion, fair value of liabilities about $43 billion.
We got our intangibles of $36.2 billion.
And then we plug for what we saw for goodwill.
So that's the balance sheet equation
under purchase accounting.
And this shows how AT&T's balance sheet
changes as a result of the DirecTV acquisition.
So notice that in our calculations here,
we had book value before the merger, book value
of net assets, was minus 3,463.
Market value after the merger was $47.88 billion.
And you can see all the changes in the assets and liabilities,
which are the acquisition adjustments we just discussed.
So what companies will often show
you is a pro-forma combined balance sheet.
So they'll show you AT&T right before the merger.
So it's a big company with $87.5 billion in net assets.
DirecTV, a smaller company, with minus $3.5 billion
in net assets.
There's a column there showing the acquisition payment,
a column there showing the changes
in the value of the assets and liabilities.
And then that gives you the pro-forma balance sheet of AT&T
pro forma for having executed this merger.
So in a more familiar example, Facebook back in 2014
spent $18 billion to buy WhatsApp.
WhatsApp was a private company which
had mainly an international texting service.
And you can see the purchase price allocation.
About $2 billion went to intangible assets
in terms of acquired users.
There was a little bit that went to trade name,
acquire technology, and other.
Most of the purchase price went to $15 billion
worth of goodwill.
So right after the acquisition, Facebook
put out a pro-forma combined balance
sheet as of June 30, 2014.
And the first column of the balance sheet
shows Facebook's historical financial statements,
shows WhatsApp's historical financial statements.
Notice what a tiny little company WhatsApp was.
Then it shows how much it paid for the tiny little company,
which was close to $18 billion.
And then it shows what it got for the tiny little company,
WhatsApp, which was $18 billion, mainly
goodwill, and also intangible assets.
And then the final column shows the pro-forma combined balance
sheet, so what Facebook would look
like after the WhatsApp acquisition
had been consummated.
Now, one sort of note here.
Those of you that know don't this,
was an incredibly successful acquisition.
So by acquiring those users, which
were a different set of users than Facebook ordinarily had,
mainly international users, Facebook
was able to cross-sell Facebook to those international users.
And this was a huge win for Facebook.
So the goodwill here of $15 billion
is probably an understatement of the amount of synergies
that Facebook created here.
And I want to say that because we're
going to get into several examples
here where we're writing off goodwill
because the acquisitions did not turn out so well.
Now, just continuing on for a second on purchase accounting,
so post acquisition, basically what happens
is you add the income and revenue of the acquirer
and target.
And you make sure to eliminate any kind of intercompany sales.
Income in the later years is going
to be reduced by if you've written up the property, plant,
and equipment, so you may have some extra depreciation.
And then you've written up the intangibles,
so you'll have extra amortization
charges on those intangibles.
And then later on we'll talk about goodwill impairments,
if those things happen.
So again back to Facebook, so Facebook is saying its purchase
price allocation is mainly going to acquired users, $2 billion;
and to goodwill, $15 billion.
Now, it's also showing how it's going to amortize
those intangible assets.
So for example preliminary fair value of acquired users
was $2 billion.
We're going to estimate a useful life of that with no salvage
value of seven years.
And you can see how the 289 per year comes to be calculated.
So Facebook and companies will also put out a pro-forma income
statement.
So for the six months ended 6/30/2014,
first we see Facebook's income statement.
Then we see WhatsApp's income statement.
Notice that WhatsApp is losing lots of money
on almost no sales.
Then we see the pro-forma adjustments.
And those pro-forma adjustments are
going to include the amortization of intangibles
we were just looking at on the prior slide.
And then it shows Facebook's pro-forma income statement.
And notice as a result of this acquisition,
Facebook's net income went from $1.4 billion to $0.7 billion.
So its net income got cut in half.
But over time, again, this was a hugely successful acquisition,
and the profits came in over time.