PROFESSOR: So takeaways from acquisitions, we
talked about acquisitions.
The alternative is to grow things internally.
With acquisitions, when you buy intangible assets,
they come on balance sheet.
When you grow those same intangible assets,
within the firm, they don't come onto your balance sheet,
because of the differences in how intangibles are treated.
When they're purchased, rather than when they're
developed internally, both in the US and also under IFRS,
firms are required to use purchase accounting.
And as we saw, assets will be written up to market value.
And at that time, intangible assets
will be added to the balance sheet
and amortized or depreciated over time.
And then finally, we talked about goodwill,
how it comes about, and when it's impaired,
and the fact that the impairment decision is
fairly discretionary.