PROFESSOR: Accounting for passive investments
in an extended example--
so first we're going to do the accounting
for the security, which is a bond, as a trading security.
And then we'll do the accounting as an available for sale
security so that we can see the differences in the accounting.
So the SPY transaction--
so Attila is a company that has a bond that's
trading at $1,000 a bond.
Eva is a company that buys 100 of these bonds.
11 months later, Eva receives $1,250
in interest on the bonds, or $1,250 per bond.
A year later, Attila is now trading at $1,050 a bond.
Eva keeps the bonds.
A year after that, the bond price drops back to $1,020.
Eva still keeps the bonds.
Finally, a year after that, the bond price
goes up to $1,010 per bond.
And then Eva, at that point, sells all of the bonds.
So first let's do the example where the accounting is
a trading security.
So we buy the bond.
We buy 100 bonds at $1,000 a bond.
So cash goes down $100,000.
And then we've got marketable securities, or the bonds,
of $100,000.
In November, we get interest.
So cash goes up.
And then we're going to recognize
interest income of $1,250.
One point on the third column on the chart
there, which is called OthCI, or other comprehensive income.
We'll see in a few minutes that this
is a stockholder's equity account that
does not affect net income.
And it's used to record gains and losses
on available for sale securities, among other things.
A year later, Attila's gone up to $1,050 per bond.
So how much are the bonds worth at this point?
So 1,050 times 100, so the bonds are worth $105,000.
So to reflect that, we're going to increase
marketable securities by $5,000.
So now we've got marketable securities
that have a value of $105,000 on our balance sheet.
And then we're going to put a gain on our income statement.
And this is an unrealized gain, which
means that we haven't sold the bonds to realize the gain.
It's just a paper gain so far.
A year later, the bond price drops to $1,020.
So now the bonds are worth $102,000.
But we've got them on our balance sheet for $105,000.
So we're going to reduce marketable securities
by $3,000.
And then we've got an unrealized loss of $3,000.
Unrealized, again, means that we have not
realized the value in cash.
So once again, we're adjusting the security
to its market value, which is $102,000 now.
And then finally, when we look at the trading security,
on December 31, 2006, Attila is now trading at $1,010 per bond.
And Eva sells all of its bonds.
So 1,010 times 100 is $111,000 cash
that Eva receives from the bonds.
We clear out marketable securities, which
now has a value of $102,000.
And then we recognize a realized gain of $9,000.
So that's our illustration of a trading security.