PROFESSOR: Until recently, equity investments
could be accounted for as available for sale
securities, which means that you wouldn't have these income
effects.
And that brings about this article,
where an investor's talking about I can't see Berkshire
Hathaway's bottom line.
This new accounting rule, which meant that all equity
securities had to be accounted for as trading securities,
so the FASB decreed that stock gains and losses
must be reported as earnings.
So equity securities must be accounted
for as trading securities.
So Berkshire Hathaway's pretax earnings
jumped from $5.3 billion to $23 billion.
Did its earnings quadruple?
No, we just had a different accounting standard.
And according to this writer-- and I
agree with this-- the meaningful portion of Berkshire's profits
are the profits of its businesses, not its securities
portfolio.
But now, investors have to dig around in income statements
to figure out what the comparable numbers are.