PROFESSOR: So here's Intel's 2013 annual report,
their statement of stockholders equity.
Notice, as we've seen before, we've got common stock,
we've got retained earnings, but now we
have this new account, which is accumulated
other comprehensive income or other comprehensive loss.
We see that begins with a negative balance of 399.
Intel has some comprehensive income,
probably from their available-for-sale securities.
And their balance of accumulated other comprehensive income
is 1,243 as of 2013.
Other disclosures Intel provides--
in their footnote 5, they talk about cash and investments
and, in particular, available-for-sale securities.
They first show adjusted cost, which
is how much they pay for the securities
plus any transactions cost.
They show next unrealized gains, unrealized losses.
And then if you sum the columns across that
gives you the fair value.
And these fair values are reported on their balance sheet
as cash equivalents, short-term investments, marketable equity
investments, and other long term investments.
And then what we're mainly concerned about here
is these gains and losses are going
to be recorded in other comprehensive income or equity.
In terms of the statement of cash flows,
passive investments are going to affect
the statement of cash flows.
So transactions and trading securities
can be reported either in cash flow from operations
or in cash flow from investments.
Transactions in available-for-sale securities
should be reported in cash flow from investments.
So that these changes in the fair value securities
are going to be, of course, removed from cash flow
from operation from net income when we compute
cash flow from operations.