PROFESSOR: So takeaways, we got two takeaway slides
for this investment section.
So passive investments, we mark 'em to market.
With some not complete control, we're
going to do the equity method, which we just
saw was favorable.
And if we got more than 50% ownership,
we're going to consolidate.
So whether it's equity or consolidated
makes a big difference on the appearance of the statements.
And as we saw, the leverage ratios
can be very different depending on whether you're
using equity method on your sub or whether you're
consolidating your sub
And then when there's changes in market values
as we talked about at the beginning of this class,
accountants make market valuation adjustments.
So for inventory and PP&E, accounts
use lower cost to market in the US.
That just means if the market value of the property, plant
and equipment say falls below the book value
as we talked about in the class on property, plant
and equipment, we're going to impair the property, plant
and equipment.
So for large investments, 20% plus either under the equity
method of accounting or under the consolidation
method of accounting, we're going
to use lower of cost or market.
Whereas for passive investments, either trading securities
or available for sale securities,
we're going to use mark to market accounting.
And the type of security is going
to determine the effect on income.
Trading securities realized gains
are going to be reported as part of net income.
Unavailable for sale securities, unrealized gains and losses
are going to be part of other comprehensive income
until they become realized gains and losses.