PROFESSOR: Finance involves a lot of uncertainty,
and we use language of probability
to model that uncertainty.
The common distributions of finance occur in many ways,
sometimes directly and more often
as the building blocks for more complicated processes.
So let's take a look at a couple of examples
of how we compute expectations from distributions,
how we can solve some interesting problems
from some simple ones.
And let's start thinking ahead already
as we review probability to thinking about how we're
going to use these basic tools of probability to describe
processes that evolve over time, where
we need to think about uncertainty
over multiple horizons in the future
and where information may arrive gradually
from one point to another and get incorporated
in our description.
So our starting example, let's just think of a random variable
x, a binomial random variable where I have probability
p that we sometimes call success of getting
a 1, probability q which is just shorthand for 1
minus p of getting a 0.
The typical question we ask and that we saw in lecture
is, what's the probability of observing a fixed number,
say, k successes out of a total number n of trials?
So to do that, there are two common things we do.
First, we ask for a given sequence,
what would be its probability?
Well, if there are k successes and there
are n minus k failures, then the probability
has to be p to the k q to the n minus k.
Because the events are independent,
our probabilities multiply.
And then, there are a lot of different ways of doing that.
How many?
Well, we've got a sequence of n events.
The 1's could be placed at any orders between them.
The number is n choose k probabilistically,
and this is the familiar binomial distribution,
sometimes written k of n with parameter p,
the probability for success.
Now, suppose we ask a different question.
Suppose we ask how long it would take us to observe success.
That is, we don't know what n is in advance.
We'd like n to be the outcome.
So n is our random variable or we
might call it T to think about a waiting time.
So let's call T the waiting time.
And that's how long we would need to wait for success.
So what might happen?
Well, we could have it happen on the first event.
So we could have a T equals 1, we get a success,
and that could happen with probability p.
It could happen on our second trial.
T equals 2.
That is, we could fail it first--
have a failure and then a success.
And that would be probability q times p.
Third trial, if it happened at T equals 3,
we would have fail, fail, succeed.
That would be q squared p.
And in general, we can see that for T equals n,
we're going to have probability q to the n minus 1 p.
That is, we have a string of n minus 1 failures followed
by a success, and this is the geometric distribution.
So we have that the probability that the waiting time is
equal to some particular n is given by q to the n minus 1 p,
or we can write that of course as 1 minus p
to the n minus 1 times p.
So how long should we expect to wait on average?
Let's compute.
When in doubt, compute.
The expectation of our waiting time
T is going to be the probability weighted average of the waiting
time.
So we have a formula for that.
So we can write this as the sum from n
equals 0 to infinity of n times q to the n minus 1 p.
Now, if we look at this, we notice
that this combination here looks familiar, doesn't it?
It's the derivative of q to the n.
So we'll use a trick.
What we're going to do is we're going
to write it as a derivative.
And then, because q is positive and less than 1,
the sums are convergent.
And we'll interchange the order of differentiation
in summation, which will give us something
that will be a nice, quick answer and something that
generalizes for more complex cases.
So let's see how that goes taking, it step by step.
This is equal to--
I'll pull the p out in front times the summation of d
by dq of q to the n, which I'll write as p d
by dq times the sum of q to the n.
And the term in parentheses right here is a geometric sum.
So we can do that sum.
This is just p times 1 over 1 minus q.
And its derivative gives us 1 over 1 minus q squared.
Now we remember that p plus q equals 1, so this is p times 1
over p squared.
Therefore, we find that the expectation of T
is equal to 1 over p.
So this should make some amount of sense.
First of all, we see that as p gets small,
the expected waiting time gets large.
If we have a 1 over 6 chance of throwing
a seven with a pair of dice, we wait on average six turns
till we get that.
If we're looking for a set of two aces and playing poker,
then we'll have to wait on average 221 turns.
Now, it's important to note that in both these cases they
satisfy the Markov property, which
says that there's no memory of what happened before.
That is, if we just got a pair of aces
our expected waiting time for another pair of aces is 221.
But if we've been waiting 220 hands,
we still have an expected waiting time of 221.
Regardless of what came before, the future expectations
depend only on the present-state variables for where we are now,
not on how we got there.
And this notion of Markov processes
will be important for characterizing
different kinds of time evolution
and for the way in which information
gets incorporated into interesting financial
variables.
So when it comes to games of chance,
certainly we know that in a fair game
that the next outcome is independent of the ones that
came before, that each one should be independent.
Let's now extend and ask, what would
be the variance of the waiting time?
So for the variance, let's remember
that the variance of the waiting time or for any random variable
is the expectation of the variable
minus its mean value, which here I just
to simplify the notation.
Instead E of T within the expectation,
I'll just call T-bar quantity squared.
And we have the general property for all expectations
that the variance is the expectation
of the square minus the square of the expectation.
Let's just review that.
This is expectation, and I'm going
to expand out the quadratic.
T squared minus 2 T-bar T plus T-bar squared.
Remember, the T-bar, the expectation of T,
is just a number, whereas T is a random variable.
Now applying linearity, we have that the expectation of the sum
is the sum of the expectations and the expectation of a scalar
times an expectation-- we just bring the scalar out front--
plus T squared.
Now, we notice it in this second term, right here,
that we have T-bar times T-bar.
That is, this combines to be minus 2 T-bar times T
bar, which gives us minus 2 T-bar squared
plus T-bar squared.
Minus 2 plus 1 is minus 1.
So we have that this is equal to, as advertised,
the expectation of the squared minus the square
of the expectation.
So how do we apply that to our Bernoulli trial case?
Well, we'd like to find the second moment.
T-bar, we've already computed.
It's 1 over p.
So T-bar squared is going to be 1 over p squared.
So we'd like to do for our Bernoulli case is
compute the second moment.
So we'd like to compute expectation of T squared,
and that's the second moment.
So this is going to be the sum from n equals 0
to infinity, this time of n squared times the probability
that T equals n which is the same as we saw before.
Now you notice we're not quite in as good shape
as we were before because I have n squared instead of n,
and this quantity here is not just the derivative of q
to the n.
But we can come close.
We can still use a derivative trick in a slightly different
formula.
And what we'll do is we'll notice that every time
when we took a derivative once, we brought down a power of n.
If I want repeated derivatives, I
would-- if I just keep taking repeated derivatives,
I'd end up with n factorial which isn't what I want.
So if I take a derivative but multiply back by q,
then I will have what I want.
So let's take a look.
So specifically, let's look at the more general problem
of computing, say, the moment T to the power r--
and that I can write as--
let me take out this p here.
And let me take out 1 over q out front.
So let me write this as p divided by q times
the sum from n equals 0 to infinity of what would
be an n to the r q to the n.
And I'm going to write that in the following way, q d by dq
with this operator raised to the r-th power times q to the n.
So if r is equal to 1, I take q d by dq.
d by dq gives me an n times q to the n minus 1 multiplied by q.
And I'm left with n with a single power of n in front.
If I do that repeatedly-- twice, three times, r times--
each time I act with the operator q
d by dq, I'll bring down in front a power of n.
So this is going to be equal to--
this is going to be the same thing as p over q
times the sum of n to the r q to the n.
So obviously, we can apply this in the special case
where n equals 2.
But we want to do one more thing, which
is to do our derivative trick--
so where we interchange the order of the derivative
and the summation.
So let's put this in the form p over q q d by dq.
Let's take this operator to the r-th power times 1 over 1
minus q.
So here's your chance.
Take these formulas that we have here.
Take a moment right now to go ahead and compute,
what is the variance of T?
So compute the expectation of T squared
and subtract the expectation of T quantity squared
and express the results in terms of our original probability
value p.
Hit pause now if you haven't got it yet
and you want a little more time to work it out.
But the value that we have is we have now
that the variance of T for the waiting
time for a success in a single series of Bernoulli trials
is going to be the expectation T squared minus the expectation
of T quantity squared.
And this is equal to 1 minus p over p squared.
So we have a general formula that we
could extend to computing higher moments,
and we can apply this to other settings
where perhaps a Bernoulli process like this
might be part of a more complex sequence
of conditional probabilities.