PROFESSOR: Let's take a look together
at the code for simulating the scaling
of the binomial distribution in R. You can install RStudio.
It's freely available for PCs, for Macs, for Linux.
And when you install it and you open it up,
you should see something like this.
So there are four panes.
On the left-hand side, on the lower left
is the console area, which is where we'll type commands
interactively.
On the upper part is where you'll see source files.
And this is the code that is in the slides
as during recitation.
On the lower right is where plots will show up,
where help information is given, where you can see list
of installed packages that are part
of your particular installation.
And on the upper right is where you can see the variables
you've created.
So let's take a look through the code one step at a time,
run it together.
You should do this along with me, or after watching
this short video.
And go in and tweak the code.
Tweak the parameters.
Run it yourself.
You should get your hands on with the code.
Try it out.
There's nothing special about R, necessarily.
But it's a great language to learn.
It's very practical.
If you don't know it, now is a great chance to learn.
And in the finance industry, you will
find that while people may have all kinds of different opinions
about what the pros and cons are of different computational
environments, usually on the job, you don't get to choose--
or even if you're in charge, you'll
eventually have to interface with the counterparty who's
going to have another choice.
So it's always good to know new languages,
to keep the ideas separate from the particular code
implementations, and ready to pick things up and try them
out, particularly when you've got a problem
to try as, you do here.
So let's do this together.
Anyway, so let's go through a demonstration.
So the first thing, which is a bit R-specific,
is I'm going to define a list of values that I want to try.
So nlist is going to be the name of my variable.
The left assignment arrow, the less than dash,
you can use in the equation.
That works fine.
That's a symbolic thing, and it's conventional in R.
And then the c operator concatenates the list operator.
It creates them.
So my list consists, instead of going every step, one, two,
three, four, five, up through 1,000.
I just picked some convenient samples.
In RStudio, I can take this--
I certainly could take this line,
and I can type it in the lower part and run it.
And if I type n list, I'll get my values out.
And you notice that in my list of my environment variables,
it showed up here in the upper right.
However, if we're working with code,
and you've got more than just a couple of lines interactively,
you may find it helpful as I do to open a new window for an R
script as a scratchpad.
Or in more structured examples, in R notebook.
Keep them up here, and then if you
want to run something that's highlighted up here,
you can highlight one or more lines of code.
Click on run, and it will run your selection.
So let's take a look for those values of n,
I'm going to define my probability to be 10%.
And we can change that in a moment.
And then I've got a for loop.
So the for loop is going to take n
to run through all the values in the list.
And then the contents of the for loop are enclosed in brackets.
So white space is not important.
Unlike Python, indentation is just
for the convenience of user.
It's not read by the language.
So everything between those two brackets
is repeated within the for loop.
I'm going to go let k go from 0 to n
is going to be a list of all the integers.
If you want to see what that looks like,
if you just type 0 to--
oops, 0 to 5, it will give you the value 0 to 5.
Or 0 to 12.
It will give you 0 to 12.
So what we're doing is for each value of n--
so for n trials, we're going to let k go from 0 successes up
through all of them being successes.
You could think of the number of heads
in n flips of a biased coin.
And then we're going to compute the probability for each one
from the binomial distribution.
Now this is a built-in function in R.
And if you want to take a look at what it is for any function,
you can type question mark dbinom to get the description.
Or over here in the help panel, you
can just type in what you want.
So if you want to see for any other distribution,
for the data distribution or so on, you can get its details.
So this is all the details you need
for the binomial distribution along with some examples
and some references.
So we're going to use binomial distribution.
The conventions are the same ones that we use.
F will be our distribution function.
K is the number of successes.
N is the total number of trials.
P is the probability of success.
Then having done that, we just need to draw some pictures.
So we'll use the bar plot command,
and you can read about that here.
I'm going to use, for now, the basic base package r commands.
There's other popular packages, like ggplot,
which have much more sophisticated and interesting
aesthetic options.
But we'll just get our base results for right now.
So the barplot is going to plot the values of f.
It's going to plot the names label--
is going to give the labels that correspond to each bar.
And then xlab and ylab are the labels
on the plot for the x-axis and the y-axis labels.
Main is the title of the graph.
And this paste command concatenates
a bunch of string variables and numbers
together, so that we can get numerical values on our plot.
And then readline() is just a pause command.
It waits for input at the keyboard,
so that we can build the graph successively, as I showed you.
So let's take this whole thing.
I'm going to select all of this text.
I can include the comment.
And I'm going to hit Run.
And now, down at the bottom, it's
waiting for me to hit a key.
So if I want to expand this graph so it fills up
the whole thing, these little icons over here will expand it.
If I want to see both of those at the same time, I can do it.
And I can resize the window between them.
For right now, let's make this big.
Let me resize this to give us a little more room.
So what we can see here is two plots.
I've done one trial.
There's 10% probability of success.
Therefore, the chance of zero successes is 90%.
The chance of one success is 10%.
No surprise there.
Now I'm going to click, put focus in the lower right,
and hit return.
And it draws the next.
So this is incremented by 1.
So now we're looking at n equals 2.
There are two trials.
I could have zero, one, or two successes.
The probabilities are 81%, 0.9 squared, down to 1%
for the chance of getting two successes.
If we keep going, these are the different values.
And as I hit return each time, you
see the graph drawn in the way that we did in class.
OK, so I can go all the way to the end.
Now if you want, you can go in, and you
can pick a different number.
You could pick that this could be, let's say 30%.
And rerun the whole thing to your heart's content.
And if we rerun this now, we have-- that's for one,
two, five, 10, 20, 50, 100.
And you see the features we saw in class, which are,
we started with an asymmetric distribution.
And we're getting something which is actually fairly
symmetric about the mean.
It's also looking pretty Gaussian, isn't it?
We'll see in a moment how we can rescale the variables to get
the true universality behavior that we expect
from the central limit theorem.
Keep in mind that whenever we're running a numerical simulation
now, whenever we think about either using a random number
generator to get Gaussian variables or looking
at the relationship between binomial,
binomial tree models and Gaussian distributions,
the binomial distribution with a finite number of steps cannot
go from minus infinity to infinity.
Can't go negative at all.
And in this case, the maximum value that we could have
would be 100.
Given that the probability of being in the tails
becomes very, very small very quickly,
we wouldn't see that on the graph.
But remember, in finance we often care about rare events.
And getting the probability of rare events
wrong on a picture like this might not seem that big a deal.
It's a rounding error in the number
of pixels in the corners.
But in finance, the consequences are often
proportional to the distance away from the mean.
So we frequently run into situations
where we have events of interest that
have very low probability but very high consequence.
Multiplying the two together gives us
an economically significant number.
So we can't just look crudely at pictures on a graph like this.
OK, so if we keep going, that's 1,000.
Now let's take a look at our scaling variable.
Remember what the basic idea was?
We want to have the scaling variable, under which
the distribution looks stable.
It doesn't keep shifting around and moving to the side.
And there's one thing that we might
want to keep in mind, which is that we always
have, for any random variable x, that where its moments exist,
if we have x, and we can compute its expectation--
let's give that a name.
Call it mu, or x bar.
And we can compute its variance, and let's assume
that that exists also.
And let's give it a name.
Let's call it sigma squared.
That if these are-- if mu and sigma are
any numbers for our distribution,
we know that for our binomial distribution,
the mean is n times p.
We know that the variance is n times p times q.
But for any values of mu and sigma,
we can take any variable x where mu and sigma exist,
and define standardized variable.
And we do it in a very trivial construction.
Let's call it define z to be x minus the mean of x.
Guess what?
The mean of that variable by construction is 0.
What about its variance?
Well, its variance is going to be sigma squared.
So let's just divide this by sigma.
And if this is a definition, this variable z
is always going to have 0 mean and unit variance.
So let's go back to our example.
And now let's look at our code for rescaling the sequence.
In here, we're going to look at the same set of values.
But now what we're going to do is, after we define k,
we're going to define z to be a rescaled variable.
That is we're going to take k, we're
going to subtract its mean, and we're
going to divide by the square root of the variance.
And then we're going to plot the results.
OK.
I'm going to cut off--
so we're going to cut off our graph
at values of plus or minus 5, just so that we can see
everything that we're doing.
And now, if we take our list, let's run this again.
Same commands.
So this time z is going to be our scaled variable.
F is going to be the binomial distribution,
and let's take a look at the plot.
So I've highlighted the text here.
I'm going to hit run.
Oops, let's make sure that we get that right.
We need to highlight the entire thing, including
the top definitions of those variables.
So let's do that, and hit run.
And you could run these one at a time or type them in.
So here is, in terms of our scaling variable.
So here we've got for n equals 1,
and I've set p back to point 1.
And now for n equals 2, n equals 5, n equals 10, n equals 20.
And now you can see that within the same picture,
our graph is staying centered.
And as I get to larger and larger values,
we see that we've reached the central value
to be in the middle of the graph to be our rescaled variable
equal to--
centered around 0, around the mean value in terms
of our rescale variable.
And our shape is looking quite Gaussian.
Try it out yourself.
Change the numbers.
And play with the code.